<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>"Our vicar is away"</title>
				<author>Erhard Oeglin</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Christopher Hutchinson</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Christopher Hutchinson</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The first printed songbook with songs primarily in German was printed in July 1512 by the Augsburg printer Erhard Oeglin (ca.1470-1520). The songbook consists of four partbooks – it is also the first German song collection with four voices throughout - and contains 49 songs with a mixture of spiritual and secular content, 43 of which are in German and 6 in Latin. Oeglin was an innovative printer, credited as one of the first printers to print musical notation using movable type and as one of the first printers of “Zeitungen” – news-sheets. Oeglin does not attribute any of the songs to particular composers but some of these songs do appear in other songbooks of this period where they are attributed to various composers active at the Imperial court, including Ludwig Senfl, Paul Hofhaimer and Heinrich Isaac. These songs are collectively known as tenor lieder, as the melody is usually carried by the tenor line. This was the prototypical song type in Germany at the turn of the sixteenth century and enjoyed particular prominence at the court of the Emperor Maximilian (1459-1519).</p>
				<p>Digitized copies of these partbooks from the Bayerische Staatsbibliothek in Munich are available online here: https://stimmbuecher.digitale-sammlungen.de//view?id=bsb00082229</p>
				<p>Saunders, Steven. “Music in Early Modern Germany.” Early Modern German Literature 1350-1700, edited by Max Reinhart, Camden House, 2007, pp. 653-698.</p>
				<p>Keyl, Stephen. “Tenorlied, Discantlied, Polyphonic lied: Voices and instruments in German secular polyphony of the Renaissance.” Early Music, vol. 20, no. 3, 1992, pp. 434–445.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek München 00082229 Rar.27 Stimme T f.47r</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">"Unser pfarrer ist auf der pan"</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">"Our vicar is away"</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Our vicar is on his way" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title in original language, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title in English, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							Unser pfarrer ist auf der pan /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							Our vicar is away.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							was getz dich an /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							What’s it to you?
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							ich wais und kan /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							I can and know how
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							dy junngen feilel müstern über gan /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							to ogle the young violets as I go.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							es fleügt do her ein weisser schwan /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							A white swan flies by,
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							wil kurtzweil han /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							it wants to have fun;
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							er prangt gar schan /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							it shows off nicely:
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							do můsst ich armer půb gar pald dar von /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							Thus I, poor lad that I am, soon had to leave.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							ich gyeng durch ayn zerrissens haus /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							I walked through a tumbled-down house;
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							still was dy maus /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							the mouse was quiet,
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							sy ruckt her aus / ayn flügel mein gans /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							my goose spread apart her wings:
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							gyng gang / gyng gang /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							gyng gang, gyng gang
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							also laut unser gsang /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							- so our song goes.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							schaubhůt der ist fürd sunnen gůt /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							A straw hat, it’s good for the sun.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							das pferd ist wild kumbt aus der stůt /
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							The horse is wild, it comes from the mare.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							das pferd ist will kumpt aus der stůt.
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							The horse is wild, it comes from the mare.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>