<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title><!--Title in English--></title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"<!--Title in English-->" is part of <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi>, a digital compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. This larger project comprises computer-readable transcriptions and/or editions of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century, and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia; accompanied by new English translations; high-resolution digital images of manuscript/early print sources, where available; an apparatus that includes critical introductions, textual notes and annotations; and a flexible user interface with which to navigate these materials.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title in original language, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title in English, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div n="1">
				<!--Divisions should be used if your text has sections larger than paragraphs-->
				<p n="1">
					<!--Paragraphs should be numbered-->
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mors secundum philosophum et æternum somnus, diviyum pavor, pauperum desiderium, incurabilis eventus, latro hominis, fuga vitæ, resolutio hominis.  </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Death, according to the Philosopher, is eternal sleep, the fear of the wealthy, tthe desire of th epoor, an irremediable outcome, the banditt of mankind, the rout of life, and Man's release.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vita vero est bonorum lætitia, miserorum mœstitia.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Life, on the contrary, is the delight of the good and the grief of the evil.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et homo quidam juvenis formosus, immutabilis, misere mei et exaudi me, supplicium, quod a te exspecto, noli emittere ad me, aurum et argentum, lapides et quid quid vis, tibi dabo, tamtumnodo noli me tangere.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Some young man, handsome, wealthy, strong, and healthy, approaches death and says: ‘O unchangeable Destiny, have pity upon me and hear my entreaty: that you not visit upon me the punishment which I expect from you. I shall give you gold and silver, precious stones, slaves
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Mancipia often refers to property more generally; however, as possessiones is mentioned within this sentence, it is likely that the author refers to ‘slaves’, who along with ‘horses’ – the next item listed – would reasonably have populated the promised ‘estates, manors, palaces’, etc. </p>
								</note>
							, horses, estates, manors, palaces, property, and whatever you want, as long as you do not lay hands upon me.’
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">

				</p>

				<p n="3">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ait enim Seneca: nemo tam imperitus est, ut nesciat se aliquando moriturum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After all, Seneca writes: ‘No one is so ignorant that he does
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tamen, mors eum propere accesserit, tremis, ploras.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">nevertheless, when death draws near, you tremble and cry.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quid fles, quid ploras, quia morieris, ad hanc legem natus?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quid tibi novi est?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">What do you find odd in this?</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ad hanc legem natum es, hoc patri tuo accidit, hoc et matri et majoribus tuis, hoc omnibus ante tte, hoc omnibus post te, vita enim cum exceptione morttis data non est.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You were born under this law; this fate befell your father, as well as your mother and your ancestors, along with all who came before and will come after you, for life is never granted together with immunity to death.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Lex universalis est, quæ jubet nasci et mori, hoc autem intelligas vitam gerendo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It is a universal law which dictates that we be born and then die, and you should understand this in the course of living your life.'
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>These ideas are a loose paraphrase of Sen. Ep. 76.11-13.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ait idem: debemus nos porttare, quod non possumus vitare.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He also writes: ‘We must bear that which we cannot avoid.’
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>An approximation of Sen. Vit. Beat. 15.7: Ad hoc sacramentum adacti sumus, ferre mortalia nec perturbari iis, quae vitare non est nostrae potestatis (‘This is the sacred obligation by which we are bound – to submit to the human lot, and not to be disquieted by those things which we have no power to avoid’). </p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Exemplum de David de filio morttuo: quia mortuus est, quare jejuno?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">David, upon the death of his son, exemplified this maxim: ‘Since he is dead, why do I fast?</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Numquid potero revocare eum?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Surely I shan’t be able to summon him back?</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ego vadam magis ad eum, ipse non revertetutr ad me.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">On the contrary, I shall go to him, but he will not come back to me.’
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>2 Samuel 12:23.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde nuntitta cuidam philosopho mortte filii ait: quoniam eum genui, inquit, morutrum scivi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Hence some philosopher also responded thus, after the death of his son had been reported to him: ‘Given that I fathered him’, he said, ‘I knew that he must die.’
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>2 This line was spoken by no ‘philosopher’; it was originally spoken by Telamon, father of Ajax, in Ennius’ tragedy Telamo, line 319: ego cum genui tum morituros scivi et ei rei sustuli (‘When I fathered children, I knew that they must die, and I brought them up for this purpose’). The misattribution may have arisen from the transmission of these verses in Cic. Tusc. Disp. 3.13.28, or, more likely, in Sen. De Cons. 11.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

				</p>

				<p n="4">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Narrat Valerius 1. V. c. X dicens, quod Anaxagoras audita morte filii respondit : nihil quidem inexspectatum aut novum nuntias,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Valerius [Maximus] also tells this story at Book 5 Chapter 10 [of his Memorable Doings and Sayings], by noting that Anaxagoras, upon hearing of the death of his son, responded: ‘You announce to me nothing unexpected or new.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Novum also means ‘odd, strange’ in this context (cf. Hor. Carm. 1.2.6, nova monstra, ‘bizarre portents’).</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ego eum natum ex me sciebam esse mortalem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I knew that he was born from me and mortal.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>These first two clauses (nihil quidem…mortalem, corresponding to ‘You announce…and mortal’ in the translation) are taken almost word-for-word from Anaxagoras’ speech at Val. Max. 5.10 ext.3, but the following sentences in Anaxagoras’ purported response have been cobbled together from Valerius’ own comments, as set out a few lines below in the aforementioned chapter.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">atque a lege naturae ac20 cipiendi Spiritus et redclencli legem didici, neminem mori, qui non vixerit, ita nee quidem vivere aliquem, qui non sit moriturus naturaliter.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I also learned that the terms upon which we receive breath and give it back are derived from the law of Nature, so that no one dies who has not lived, and likewise no one lives who will not die in accordance with his nature.’ </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ibidem, quod Xenophon auclita morte filii sui majoris natu, qui in bello oeeiderat, coronam tarnen deponere contentus fuit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In the same place, Valerius reports that Xenophon, having heard of the death of his elder son, who had fallen in battle, was content merely to take off his garland.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Agebat enim solemne sacrificium, deinde per25 contatus, quomodo oeeubuisset, ut audivit fortissime puguantem interiisse, capiti reposuit coronam et per numina, quibus sacrificabat , testatus est , majorem se ex virtute filii voluptatem quam ex morte amaritudinem sentire.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For instance, he was conducting a regular sacrifice, when he then asked how his son had died, and learned that he had perished while fighting most courageously, he replaced the garland upon his head and called the gods to whom he was sacrificing to witness that he felt more pleasure from his son’s bravery than bitterness from his death.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>A summary, or rather a restructuring with large parts of the original Latin kept intact, of Val. Max. 5.10 ext.2. </p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>

					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">
								<note anchored="true">
									<p><!--This is an example note. Notes on textual interpretation should usually be contained within the <rdg> and not the <lem>--></p>
								</note>
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
								<note anchored="true">
									<p><!--This is an example note--></p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
