<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Dialogus Creaturarum 1: de sole et luna</title>
				<author>AUTHOR</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>TO BE DECIDED! SOMETHING ABOUT STANFORD</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p></p>
				<p></p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Dialogus Creaturum: de sole et luna</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Dialogue of the Creatures: Concerning Sun and Moon, the first dialogue</witness>
				</listWit>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sol est secundum philosophum oculus mundi , jocunditas dei, pulchritudo coeli, mensura temporum, virtus et origo omnium nascentium, dominus plantarum, doctor et perfector omnium stellarum.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After the philosopher’s saying, the Sun is the world’s eye, God’s delight, sky’s beauty, time’s measure, birth’s potency and birth’s originator, the planets’ lord, all the stars’ leader and all the stars’ perfector.</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna vero, ut dicit Ambrosius in Exameron, est decor noctis , mater totius humoris et ministra, mensura temporum, dominatrix maris, immutatrix aeris et aemulatrix solis, et propter quod est semulatrix solis, soli incepit detrahereet eum diffamare.</lem> 
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The Moon is the night’s finery, all liquid’s mother and minister, time’s measure, sea’s lady, the air’s changelessness and Sun’s imitator. So says Ambrose, in Exameron, On the Six Days, truly.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">And because she has long been the Sun’s imitator, she began to detract from him, and to defame him. Sun, sensing this, spoke to Moon, saying, “Why do you pull me down, and blaspheme me? </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sol autem hoc sentiens loquutus est lunse dicens: quare mihi detrahis et blasphemas? </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">I have always illuminated you, and gone ahead of you. But now you hate me, and attack me.”	
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Ego semper teilluminavi et prsecessi, tu autem semper me odis et impugnas.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui luna : recede a me, quia te non diligo, cum propter tuum magnum splendorem ego nihil appretior in mundo; si non esses, seculo superlata essem ego.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To Sun Moon answered, “Depart from me; I don’t love you. Because of your great splendor, the world does not value me at all. If you were not, I would be held the highest in the world.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui sol: ingrata sufficiat tibi magnificentia tua; si ego in die, tu vero in nocte perlustras. Obediamus ergo creatori nostro et noli superbire super me, sed me permitte lucere in die ac bona domini munire.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To Moon Sun responded, “Thankless, your magnificence suits you. If I shine in the day, you shine at night. Let us obey our creator. Cease to be proud beyond me. Let me glow during the day and serve the good of the Lord.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna vero magis animata recessit cum furore et Stellas ad se clamavit aggregavitque magnum exercitum et cum sole proeliari ccepit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Moon drew back, enlivened all the more with fury, and called the stars to herself. She assembled a great army, and began to battle with Sun.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">formata non loquantur Inclinacione tamen et naturalis institucionis proprietate + nos docere nostrosque mores corrigere si bene pensamus + non desinunt </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And yet, if we ponder them well, they do not cease to inform us with the guidance and instruction of the institution of nature, and to correct our customs.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sagittas enim mittebat adversus solem et cum jaculis percutere nitebatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She sent arrows against Sun, and strove to pierce him with darts.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et ideo auctor libri istius hec rite considerans quosdam dyalogos creaturarumad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit ad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Rightly considering this, The author of the Dialogue devised, composed, and applied creatures’ dialogues to healthy and moral doctrine</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sol autem cum esset superius, descendit et lunam cum mucrone partitus est et Stellas dejecit dicens: sie semper, cum eris rotunda, faciam tibi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sun, being higher, descended, and split Moon with the point of his sword, and cast down the stars, saying, “Whenever you are full, each time I shall cleave you.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">per rerum similitudines procuratur Salvator enim noster omnium predicatorum perfecta forma fabulis + palestinorum more + usus estut rerum similitudine ad viam veritatis homines produceret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Savior made use of both anointment and the perfected preacher’s fable to lead men, by way of imitation, toward the way of truth. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hac enim de causa, ut fabulse dieunt, luua nunquam rotunda permanet et Stellas casum habent.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> It is because of this that, as the stories say, Moon never stays full, and the stars fall.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna ergo coufusa in verecundia mansit dicens: turgidam melius partiri erat quam totam perire.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And so Moon remained, confused, in shame, saying: “It is better to share the overfull than to lose all.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">In this way many of the proud and the exalted want alone to be lord, and they desire that none be alike or superior to them.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sic enim multi superbi et elati volunt sibi dominari nee superiorem vel similem cupiunt habere.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde glosa: superbia est elatio incensa quae inferioribus despiciens superioribus et paribus satagit dominari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Whence comes this gloss: “pride is incensed dignity which, despising those below, sets to dominating those above and those equal to it.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ludentem invenit + dicitur illi mandasse qui arcum gerebat ut sagittam traheret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Johannes is said to have ordered the man to carry a bow with him in order to attract an arrow. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam velle quidem esse super omnes vituperabiliter malum est, sustinere alterum sibi similem gloriosum est, ut ait Chrysostomus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To desire to be beyond all others is wicked. But it is glorious to hold another up as equal to oneself.” So says Chrisostomos.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>												
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De talibus enim dicit poeta: tolluntur in altum ut lapsu graviori cadant. Et nota, quod, quanto est major assensus, tanto est major et periculosior casus. Qui enim de piano et infimo loco cadit, cito resurgit, qui autem de alto, cito surgere nequit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Concerning such things, the poet says, “The revered, who are lifted on high, are raised up in order that, when they slip, the more grievous will be their fall. And it is known that the greater is the assent, the more perilous shall be the fall. For he who falls from a flat and low place rises again swiftly, and he who falls from the height shall not be able to return.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>		
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">in talibus de iocundis actionibus seu verbis caveamus + ne dum relaxare animum volumus + omnem armoniam bonorum ope+rum per contemptum quendam soluamus </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In these ways, though, we might beware of pleasurable actions or words, lest, when we want to relax our minds, we instead undo all the peace of good works with something contemptible.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Rami enim arboris, ut dicit Chrysostomus, qui staut in summitate, cito a magno vento franguntur, qui autem sunt ad radicem, conservantur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“The tree’s branches growing aloft are quickly broken by a great wind, but those at the root are saved.” So says Chrisostomos.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quintus Curius says more, that someone once said to Alexander, “It is permitted for a great tree to grow into heaven, though it will be uprooted so quickly by wind, and it is permitted for a lion to be so proud, though he will be made into the food of the smallest birds’.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Unde etiam ait Quintus Curtius , quendam dixisse Alexaudro quod, licet arbor magna crescat in altum, tarnen vento citius exstirpatur, et licet leo tarn sit superbus, tarnen parvarum avium efficitur cibus.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Some philosopher coming to Alexander’s tomb said, “Yesterday the whole world was not enough for this man. Today, with his five-foot grave, he is happy.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">.Quidam philosopbus veniens ad sepulturam Alexandri ait: heri non sufficiebat isti totus mundus, hodie quinque sepultura pedum est contentus.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>