<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Preface to the Dialogus Creaturum</title>
				<author>Attributed to Mayno dei Mayneri or Nicolas de Pergamen</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Prefacio in librum qui dicitur dyalogus creaturarum morilizatus</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Preface to the book in which the moralised dialogue of the creatures is told</witness>
				</listWit>
				<p></p>
				<p></p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Prefacio in librum qui dicitur dyalogus creaturarum moralizatus omni materie morali iocundo et edificatiuo modo applicalibis feliciter</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The preface to the book, (The Moral Dialogue of Creatures)—applicable to every moral matter for edification and enjoyment’s sake—,happily begins thus:</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">quoniam sicut testator ysidorus </lem> 
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Just as Isidor the Witness says </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">in libro de summo bono libro primo capite quarto dicens</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">says in his book De Summo Bono, On the Highest Good(part one chapter four)</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">quod ex pulchritudine circumscripte nature ostendit nobis deus</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">that natural things are closed off from beauty, God,</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">pulchritudinis sue partem aliquam qui circumscribi nequit et intelligiut ipsis eisdem vestigiis homo revertatur ad deum qui bus aversus est a deo</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He who cannot be comprehended or limited, reaches out to us some part of His beauty so that man might return to God from those tracks which turn him away from God;</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> ++ et qui per amorem pulchritudinis creature + a creatoris forma se ab stulit + rursus per creature decorem + ad creatoris sui pulchritudinem revertatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">so that the man who, through love of a creature’s beauty, snatched himself away from his Creator’s form for the creature’s charm, might turn back to his Creator’s beauty. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que qui dem creature etsi nobis sicut liber iste fingit + dyialetice voce </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Creatures do not speak to us in reasoned phrases, as this book pretends.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">formata non loquantur Inclinacione tamen et naturalis institucionis proprietate + nos docere nostrosque mores corrigere si bene pensamus + non desinunt </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And yet, if we ponder them well, they do not cease to inform us with the guidance and instruction of the institution of nature, and to correct our customs.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quod illud gloriosum lumen doctorum Sanctus augustinus optime intelligebat cum dicebat O domine deus omnes creature tue quas fecisti + ad me clamant + et clamare non desi nunt ut te solum deum creatorem meum super omnia diligam + </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The glorious light of the learned, Saint Augustine, understood this when he said, “O Lord God, all your creatures which You have made cry out to me and do not cease to cry out. I will love You alone, God, my Creator, beyond all things.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et ideo auctor libri istius hec rite considerans quosdam dyalogos creaturarumad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit ad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Rightly considering this, The author of the Dialogue devised, composed, and applied creatures’ dialogues to healthy and moral doctrine</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">et composuit ut per creaturarum quasi nobis loquentium proprietates +simul in moribus erudiamur et tedium audiencium evitemus et ipsorum audiencium memoriam adiuvemus quod maxime </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">so that, through the characters of creatures talking just as we do, we might be edified, avoid the boredom of listening, and help the memory of the audience, all of which is begotten best through parables.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">per rerum similitudines procuratur Salvator enim noster omnium predicatorum perfecta forma fabulis + palestinorum more + usus estut rerum similitudine ad viam veritatis homines produceret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Savior made use of both anointment and the perfected preacher’s fable to lead men, by way of imitation, toward the way of truth. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Auctor ergo libri presentis iocundo modo morales doctrinas in exterminium viciorum et virtutum promocionem introducit + quod utique licet et expediens est ut dicit doctor sanctus secunda secunde qu.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Likewise, the author of the present book introduced moral doctrines in a pleasant manner to bring about the extermination of vices and the promotion of virtues. As the learned Saint [Aquinas] says in the second part of the second part [of the Summa Theologiae],</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">CLXVIII in solucione ultimi argumenti + Et hoc si fictio exterior interiori devocioni et dispositioni bone conveniat Utilis est ergo </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">in the solution to the final argument of question 168: “ Undoubtedly, that which is expedient is permitted; it is [permitted] for an outward fiction of inner devotion and a good disposition to affect virtue.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">presens liber predicatoribus et aliis quibusque intelligentibus contra fatigacionem animalem + ut per delectacionem iocunde materie aliqualiter intermissa intencione ad insistendum racionis studio simplicium animi ad altiora trahantur+.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Hence, the present book is useful for preachers and all others who understand that by enjoying pleasant matters—wherein the strain is somehow lessened to allow for endurance--, by the simple study of reason, minds might be drawn to deeper things. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sicut in collacionibus patrum legitur quod beatus evangelista iohannes dum quidam scandalizaretur quod eum cum suis discipulis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It is said in collections of the fathers’ sayings that, once, a disciple of the blessed evangelist Johannes was tempted while he played with the others.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ludentem invenit + dicitur illi mandasse qui arcum gerebat ut sagittam traheret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Johannes is said to have ordered the man to carry a bow with him in order to attract an arrow. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">+ quod cum pluries fecisset quesivit utrum hec continue facere posset Qui respondit + quod si hec continue faceret + aut arcus frangeretur aut remissius telum proiceret +</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When the tempted man had done so for a long time, Johannes asked the man to bear the bow with him always. The man responded that, if he a bore a bow always, he would either break it or throw his spear less forcefully.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>												
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ex quibus Beatus iohannes intulit + quod similiter animus hominis frangeretur si nunquam a sua intencione relaxeretur </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">From this, Blessed Johannes inferred that man’s mind might break in the same way, if it were never released from its strain. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et hoc idem dicit philosophus in IV ethicorum quod in huius vite conservacio ne quedam anime requies cum ludo seu iocunditate habetur + quae utique virtuosa est sicut dicit ambrosius in primo de oficiis hoc</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the Philosopher says this same thing in book IV of the Ethics, that in the protection of this life rest is taken either in play or pleasantness, and that it is assuredly virtuous, and one of the foremost duties, just as Ambrose says.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>		
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">in talibus de iocundis actionibus seu verbis caveamus + ne dum relaxare animum volumus + omnem armoniam bonorum ope+rum per contemptum quendam soluamus </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In these ways, though, we might beware of pleasurable actions or words, lest, when we want to relax our minds, we instead undo all the peace of good works with something contemptible.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iste ergo liber dyalogus creaturarum appellatus sic materias iocundas fingit ut morum gravitas et aptitudo doctrine per sanctorum auctoritates doctorum exornetur habens duas tabulas prenotates +</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore, this book, called The Dialogue of Creatures, which consists of two marked sections, crafts pleasant matters in order to, with the authority of the learned saints, embellish customs’ gravity and increase doctrine’s aptitude.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quarum prima exprimit de quibus creaturis tractant singuli dyalogorum ut lector quo citius habeat circa que versatureius intencio </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The first sections speaks about the creatures that each of the dialogues discusses, so that the reader might possess those things faster around which the dialogue’s intention moves.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Secunda tabula alphabetica ordine generaliter singulas materias virtutum et viciorum ad mores componen dos et corrigendos predicatorem et inquirentem docet + Que scilicet cuilibet narracioni sibi in processu sermonum convenire possunt +</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">. The second section, in alphabetical order, demonstrates to preachers and seekers single matters of virtue and vice in order to assemble and correct customs.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>		
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>      


