<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Dialogus Creaturarum 9: De igne et aqua</title>
				<author>AUTHOR</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>TO BE DECIDED! SOMETHING ABOUT STANFORD</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">De igne et aqua</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Concerning Fire and Water</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dialogus Creaturum: de igne et aqua</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Dialogue of the Creatures: Concerning Fire and Water</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ignis est lenis, purus, subtilis, mobilis, lucidus et calidus, et quia est tarn pretiosus , in se sublimari eeepit dicens:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Fire is light, pure, subtle, mobile, bright and hot. Because he is so precious, Fire began to exalt himself.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ego in terra omnibns praevaleo et euneta consumo, sed si in aquis praevalerem, superlatus omnibus existerem.</lem> 
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I prevail over all on earth; I eat up all on earth. If I were to prevail against Water, I would be revered beyond all things.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Pro tanto ad se clamavit aquam dicens: soror carissima, elementum Dei es tu velut ego, quapropter , si tibi commoratus fuero et tecum connexus, non solum magnus sed magnificentior et excellentior apparebo. Unde obsecro te, permitte me tecum morari et inte gloriari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So he called Water to himself and said, “Dearest sister, you are an element of God like me. If I were to stay with you and be joined to you I would seem not only great but even greater and higher. I beg you, let me linger next to you and revel in you.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Aqua vero simulare se ingeniöse eeepit dicens:desiderio desideravi hoc pascha tecum manducare, accede ad me secure et te pro viribus meliorabo.	
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Shrewdly, Water began to pretend, saying, “I have wanted this for a long while, to share this Easter with you. Come over to me and for the sake of men I will make you better.”.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ignis quoque hoc audiens jueundari eeepit et amicabiliter ad aquam intravit, aqua vero, dum ignem in se haberet, assistentibus sibi dixit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Hearing these words, Fire began to rejoice and entered water smilingly. Once she fully held fire in herself, water spoke to those around her.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Histe inimicus et contrarius est generis mei ; hie me saepe con- sumpsit et ad nihilum redegit, modo me vindicare possum et ipsum exstinguere, si volo, sed juxta verbum apostoli nolo reddere malum pro malo, ne seculum privetur tanto bono, tarnen volo ipsum aliquantulum humiiiare.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“This one is my enemy; my kind is his opponent. Often this flame hasdevoured me and turned me back to nothing. I can claim revenge and extinguish him if I want, but, as the Apostle’s word goes, I refuse to exchange wrong for wrong, lest the world be robbed of something good. Still though, I wish tohumiliate him a little.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et haec dicens parum collegit se et in ignem mingere coepit. Et ob hoc orare aquam ignis coepit, ne ipsum exstiugueret. </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saying so, she collected herself somewhat and began to pee onto Fire, who began to plead with Water, anguished that he would be put out.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Aqua vero miserta est ei nec eum ex toto exstinxit, sed ad terram ipsum deduxit dicens: Deo damus dulcem sonum reddendo pro malo bunum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So Water took pity on him and did not extinguish him entirely, but led him back to land, saying, “We offer to god a sweet tune: in exchange for bad, I give back good.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed multi hodie per contrariura reddunt pro malo malum, cum volunt vindietam assumere nolentes offensas dimittere.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Today many return bad for good when they want to take their vengeance and not to forget offense.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Propter quod Hieroniraus dicit: quoniara Deus donavit in Christo peccata nostra, sie et uos diraittamus his, qui in nobis peccant, et Dei imitatio injuriam nobis factam frangit et revocat.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">But Hieronimus says thus: “Because God in Christ forgave our sins, so we must forgive them that sin against us, for our imitation ofGod breaks and revokes any injury done to us.” </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sicut legitur in historiis Alexandri, quod, cum quidani eum graviter oflendisset , uolebat ei dimittere, Aristoteles autem hoc cognoscens perrexit ad eum et ait: volo, domine, quod hodie sis victoriosus ultra quod fuisti.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It is written in the histories of Alexander that, once, when someone badly offended him, he was not willing to forgive them. Aristotle took notice and went over to him. “I want, lord, for you to be even more victorious today than you have been before.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo respondente ait: bene volo. Cui ille: tu, rex, superasti omnia regna mundi, sed hodie tu superatus es, quia, si te permittis superari, victus es;</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I desire this too,” said Alexander. “You, king, have overcome all the world’s kings, but today you have been overcome. If you allow yourself to be overcome, you are overcome.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">si tu quoque vincis temetipsum, victoriosus eris, quia, qui semetipsum vincit, contra omnia fortis est, ut dicit philosophus. Ad hsec verba vindictam remisit Alexander et placatus est.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If, on the other hand, you conquer yourself, you shall be more victorious, since whoever conquers himself is mighty against all. So sayeth the philosopher.” At these words Alexander forgave the offense and was placated.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Completis ergo septem mensibus revocatus est, non tarnen statim regnavit, </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Having completed the seven months, he was recalled, although he did not immediately resume his reign. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Propter quod dicitur Prov. XVI: melius est patiens viro forti et qui dominatur animo suo expugnatore urbium.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And so says Proverbs XVI: “better than a strong man is a patient man. And he that controls his mind is a taker of cities.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>												
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>