<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Dialogus Creaturarum 2: De Saturno et nube</title>
				<author>AUTHOR</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>TO BE DECIDED! SOMETHING ABOUT STANFORD</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p></p>
				<p></p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Dialogus Creaturum: de Saturno et nube</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Dialogue of the Creatures: Concerning Saturn and the Cloud, the second dialogue</witness>
				</listWit>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Septem sunt planetae secundum dicta philosophorum, scilicet Saturnus, Jupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercurius et Luna, sed distantia magna est inter planetam et planetam.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After the philosopher’s saying, there are seven planets: Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Sun, Venus, Mercury, and Moon, and the distance is great from planet to planet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quia refert magister Moyses maximus philosophus, ut habetur in Aurea Legenda, quod quilibet circulus cujuslibet plauetae habet in spissitudine viam quingentorum annorum id est tantum spatium, quantum posset aliquis ire in quiugentis annis de via plana,</lem> 
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This is why the teacher Moyses, the greatest philosopher, says that, as it is held in the Golden Legend, every revolution of every planet has, in terms of thickness, a five-hundred-year path.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ita tarnen, quod iter cujuslibet diei sit quadraginta milliaria et quodlibet milliare sit duorum millium passuum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That is to say, there is as much space as someone could walk in five-hundred years on a level road, such that each day his journey would be forty miles, and every mile two thousand paces.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quadam autem vice quaedam nubes magna et spissa se elevare ccepit dicens: magna est excellentia mea , quia propter meam maguitudinem planetae in mundo apparere non valent, dum in aere me pono;	
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Once upon a time, a great thick cloud began to revere herself, saying, “My excellence is great, and, on account of my size, the planets can’t make their way into the world, so long as I interpose myself in the air.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">sed cum sim sub ipsis et eas sie obnubilo, quanto magis, si adscendero superius, offuscare et suppeditare potero, multo magis certe.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When I am beneath them and I overcloud them like this, I am much greater. But If I were to ascend higher, I would be able to cover them and subordinate them. Certainly then I would be much much greater.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et hoc dicens sursum tendere ccepit cumque usque ad Saturuum ascenderet et superscandere vellet, ait Saturnus : quis es tu, qui ascendere cupis, ubi nunquam ullus ascendit?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saying so, she began to stretch upwards, and wanted to ascend all the way to Saturn, and to clamber over him. Saturn spoke: “Who are you? Who desires to ascend to where no one has ever ascended?”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui nubes: ego super ascendam et te praeeipitabo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To which Cloud said, “I will go beyond and cast you down.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc audiens Saturnus perturbatus ad arma cucurrit et viam ei clausit, insuper et nubem dejeeit et ad nihilum redegit dicens: convenit eum reeidivare, qui vult super omnes stare.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saturn, disturbed, ran to  fetch his weapons and shut off the road. From above, he threw down Cloud and reduced her to nothing, saying, “They fall down who desire to stand above all.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc enim accidit Nabugodonosor, qui super omnes reges et principes terrae scandere satagebat , ut esset rex regum et dominus dominorum terrenorum, nesciens prae superbia, quod dominetur excelsus super regnum hominum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So it was for Nebuchadnezzar, who strove to overthrow all the earth’s kings and princes, so that he might be the king of earthly kings and the lord of earthly lords, not knowing because of his haughtiness that He has dominion over the kings of men.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et ideo auctor libri istius hec rite considerans quosdam dyalogos creaturarumad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit ad sanam et moralem doctrinam applicavit confinxit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Rightly considering this, The author of the Dialogue devised, composed, and applied creatures’ dialogues to healthy and moral doctrine</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sol autem cum esset superius, descendit et lunam cum mucrone partitus est et Stellas dejecit dicens: sie semper, cum eris rotunda, faciam tibi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sun, being higher, descended, and split Moon with the point of his sword, and cast down the stars, saying, “Whenever you are full, each time I shall cleave you.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">per rerum similitudines procuratur Salvator enim noster omnium predicatorum perfecta forma fabulis + palestinorum more + usus estut rerum similitudine ad viam veritatis homines produceret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Savior made use of both anointment and the perfected preacher’s fable to lead men, by way of imitation, toward the way of truth. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hac enim de causa, ut fabulse dieunt, luua nunquam rotunda permanet et Stellas casum habent.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> It is because of this that, as the stories say, Moon never stays full, and the stars fall.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna ergo coufusa in verecundia mansit dicens: turgidam melius partiri erat quam totam perire.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And so Moon remained, confused, in shame, saying: “It is better to share the overfull than to lose all.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">In this way many of the proud and the exalted want alone to be lord, and they desire that none be alike or superior to them.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sic enim multi superbi et elati volunt sibi dominari nee superiorem vel similem cupiunt habere.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde glosa: superbia est elatio incensa quae inferioribus despiciens superioribus et paribus satagit dominari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Whence comes this gloss: “pride is incensed dignity which, despising those below, sets to dominating those above and those equal to it.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ludentem invenit + dicitur illi mandasse qui arcum gerebat ut sagittam traheret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Johannes is said to have ordered the man to carry a bow with him in order to attract an arrow. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam velle quidem esse super omnes vituperabiliter malum est, sustinere alterum sibi similem gloriosum est, ut ait Chrysostomus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To desire to be beyond all others is wicked. But it is glorious to hold another up as equal to oneself.” So says Chrisostomos.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>												
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De talibus enim dicit poeta: tolluntur in altum ut lapsu graviori cadant. Et nota, quod, quanto est major assensus, tanto est major et periculosior casus. Qui enim de piano et infimo loco cadit, cito resurgit, qui autem de alto, cito surgere nequit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Concerning such things, the poet says, “The revered, who are lifted on high, are raised up in order that, when they slip, the more grievous will be their fall. And it is known that the greater is the assent, the more perilous shall be the fall. For he who falls from a flat and low place rises again swiftly, and he who falls from the height shall not be able to return.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>		
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">in talibus de iocundis actionibus seu verbis caveamus + ne dum relaxare animum volumus + omnem armoniam bonorum ope+rum per contemptum quendam soluamus </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In these ways, though, we might beware of pleasurable actions or words, lest, when we want to relax our minds, we instead undo all the peace of good works with something contemptible.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Rami enim arboris, ut dicit Chrysostomus, qui staut in summitate, cito a magno vento franguntur, qui autem sunt ad radicem, conservantur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“The tree’s branches growing aloft are quickly broken by a great wind, but those at the root are saved.” So says Chrisostomos.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quintus Curius says more, that someone once said to Alexander, “It is permitted for a great tree to grow into heaven, though it will be uprooted so quickly by wind, and it is permitted for a lion to be so proud, though he will be made into the food of the smallest birds’.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Unde etiam ait Quintus Curtius , quendam dixisse Alexaudro quod, licet arbor magna crescat in altum, tarnen vento citius exstirpatur, et licet leo tarn sit superbus, tarnen parvarum avium efficitur cibus.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Some philosopher coming to Alexander’s tomb said, “Yesterday the whole world was not enough for this man. Today, with his five-foot grave, he is happy.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">.Quidam philosopbus veniens ad sepulturam Alexandri ait: heri non sufficiebat isti totus mundus, hodie quinque sepultura pedum est contentus.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>	
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>