<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Dialogus Creaturarum 2: De Saturno et nube</title>
				<author>AUTHOR</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jake Goulder</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>TO BE DECIDED! SOMETHING ABOUT STANFORD</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p></p>
				<p></p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Dialogus Creaturum: de Saturno et nube</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Dialogue of the Creatures: Concerning Saturn and the Cloud, the second dialogue</witness>
				</listWit>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Septem sunt planetae secundum dicta philosophorum, scilicet Saturnus, Jupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercurius et Luna, sed distantia magna est inter planetam et planetam.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After the philosopher’s saying, there are seven planets: Saturn, Jupiter, Mars, Sun, Venus, Mercury, and Moon, and the distance is great from planet to planet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quia refert magister Moyses maximus philosophus, ut habetur in Aurea Legenda, quod quilibet circulus cujuslibet plauetae habet in spissitudine viam quingentorum annorum id est tantum spatium, quantum posset aliquis ire in quiugentis annis de via plana,</lem> 
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This is why the teacher Moyses, the greatest philosopher, says that, as it is held in the Golden Legend, every revolution of every planet has, in terms of thickness, a five-hundred-year path.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ita tarnen, quod iter cujuslibet diei sit quadraginta milliaria et quodlibet milliare sit duorum millium passuum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That is to say, there is as much space as someone could walk in five-hundred years on a level road, such that each day his journey would be forty miles, and every mile two thousand paces.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quadam autem vice quaedam nubes magna et spissa se elevare ccepit dicens: magna est excellentia mea , quia propter meam maguitudinem planetae in mundo apparere non valent, dum in aere me pono;	
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Once upon a time, a great thick cloud began to revere herself, saying, “My excellence is great, and, on account of my size, the planets can’t make their way into the world, so long as I interpose myself in the air.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">sed cum sim sub ipsis et eas sie obnubilo, quanto magis, si adscendero superius, offuscare et suppeditare potero, multo magis certe.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When I am beneath them and I overcloud them like this, I am much greater. But If I were to ascend higher, I would be able to cover them and subordinate them. Certainly then I would be much much greater.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et hoc dicens sursum tendere ccepit cumque usque ad Saturuum ascenderet et superscandere vellet, ait Saturnus : quis es tu, qui ascendere cupis, ubi nunquam ullus ascendit?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saying so, she began to stretch upwards, and wanted to ascend all the way to Saturn, and to clamber over him. Saturn spoke: “Who are you? Who desires to ascend to where no one has ever ascended?”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui nubes: ego super ascendam et te praeeipitabo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To which Cloud said, “I will go beyond and cast you down.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc audiens Saturnus perturbatus ad arma cucurrit et viam ei clausit, insuper et nubem dejeeit et ad nihilum redegit dicens: convenit eum reeidivare, qui vult super omnes stare.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saturn, disturbed, ran to  fetch his weapons and shut off the road. From above, he threw down Cloud and reduced her to nothing, saying, “They fall down who desire to stand above all.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc enim accidit Nabugodonosor, qui super omnes reges et principes terrae scandere satagebat , ut esset rex regum et dominus dominorum terrenorum, nesciens prae superbia, quod dominetur excelsus super regnum hominum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So it was for Nebuchadnezzar, who strove to overthrow all the earth’s kings and princes, so that he might be the king of earthly kings and the lord of earthly lords, not knowing because of his haughtiness that He has dominion over the kings of men.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De quo dicitur Danielis IV: quando elatum est cor Nabugodonosor et spiritus ejus confirmatus est ad super biam, depositus est de solio suo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Daniel IV says, “When Nebuchadnezzar’s heart and soul were fortified and lifted into arrogance, from his own throne he was deposed.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde dictum est ei: ejiciet te deus ab hominibus et tum bestiis atque feris erit habitatio tua, foenumut bos comedes septemque tempora mutabuntur in te.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Wherefore it was said to him, “God casts you away from men. Your home shall be with the beasts and the wild ones. You shall eat say like an ox. For seven seasons of your life you will be transformed.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sicut dicitur in Hystoriis Scholasticis: non est factus secundum mutationem corporis sed secundum mentis alienationem et ablatus est ei sensus et usus linguae et videbatur sibi, quod esset bos sive taurus in anterioribus , in posterioribus autem leo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">But it is said in the Scholastic Histories, “His body did not change, but his mind was alienated and the use of speech stricken from him. And it seemed to him that he was an ox or a bull in the front, but in the back a lion.” </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Throughout the time of Nebuchadnezzar’s alienation, Daniel prayed for him so much that the seven seasons—seven years, that is—were changed, for his prayers, into seven months.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> Daniel quoque toto tempore alienationis ejus pro eo orabat, ita quod Septem tempora, id est septem anni ad preces suas in septem menses mutati sunt.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">In qüibus septem mensibus insaniam patiebatur per quadraginta dies, per alios vero quadraginta ad cor reversus flebat et orabat deum, ita quod ex magnis fletibus oculi ejus ut caro facti sunt.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">During the seven months Nebuchadnezzar suffered disease for forty days. For another forty, he wept for his turned-back heart and beseeched God; from their great tears his eyes were as if turned into flesh.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Multi autem ad eum exibant et eum videbant.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Many men went out and saw him.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Completis ergo septem mensibus revocatus est, non tarnen statim regnavit, </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Having completed the seven months, he was recalled, although he did not immediately resume his reign. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>			
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">sed statuti sunt pro eo septem judices et usque ad finem septem anorum poenitentiam egit, panem et carnem non comedens et vinum non bibens.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Rather, he established for himself seven judges and did penance for seven years. He ate no meat and he drank no wine.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam velle quidem esse super omnes vituperabiliter malum est, sustinere alterum sibi similem gloriosum est, ut ait Chrysostomus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To desire to be beyond all others is wicked. But it is glorious to hold another up as equal to oneself.” So says Chrisostomos.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>												
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>