<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Chastity of Mr. Wu’s Wife</title>
				<author></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Likun Yang</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Likun Yang</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI encoding by</resp>
					<name>Jordan Rosen-Kaplan</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p></p>
				<p></p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p></p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal">
			</variantEncoding>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"></witness>
				</listWit>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">譚氏節操</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Chastity of Mr. Wu’s Wife</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
			 <div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">英州真陽縣曲江村人吳琦, 略知書. 其妻譚氏。紹興五年閏二月, 本邑觀音山盜起, 攻剽鄉落。琪竄去。譚氏與其女被執, 並鄰社村婦數人偕行。譚在眾中頗潔白, 盜欲妻之。詬曰: “爾輩賊也。官軍旦夕且至。將為齏粉。我良家女。何肯為汝婦。” 強之不已, 至於捶擊。愈極口肆罵, 竟斃於毒手。後盜平, 鄰婦同執者皆還, 曰: “使吳秀才妻不罵賊。今日亦歸矣。” 因備言其死狀, 吳生始知之。聞者高其節, 予嘗為之傳云。</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In the Qujiang Village of the Zhenyang County under the Yingzhou Prefecture, there was a man named Wu Qi who had received some education and had a wife from the Tan family. In the second month of the fifth year of the Shaoxing era, some bandits emerged from the Guanying Mountain in the area and plundered many villages and counties. Wu Qi ran away. His wife and their daughter were captured and joined other women captured from the same village. Among this group of women, Wu’s wife was one of the more attractive, so one of the bandits wanted to have sex with her. Wu’s wife scolded him, saying: “People like you are nothing but bandits. The military will arrive in no time and you all will be crushed. I am from a reputable family. How can I become your woman?” The bandit tried to force her into it but failed, and then hit her. Wu’s wife started shouting and ranting but in the end was killed by the bandit. After the bandits were suppressed, the other captured women all returned home. They said: “If Mr. Wu’s wife had not scolded the bandit, she could have returned home too.” When they described her death in great detail, Mr. Wu understood what happened. All those who heard this story praised her chastity, and I therefore write this piece to spread her fame. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>