<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>To the tune “Sands of the Washing Stream”&#8212;"A new song, a single cup of wine"</title>
				<author>Yan Shu 晏殊</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 89.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Qian Jia</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Notes by</resp>
					<name>Nina Du</name>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Nina Du</name>
					<name>Manya Bansal</name>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>

				<p>This ci is regarded as Yan Shu’s masterpiece, because it conveys deep sentiments using few words. The first two lines of the second stanza are particularly admired for their parallelism and neat contrast. The song expresses feelings of sorrow and regret at the passage of spring. As in many of Yan Shu’s songs, there is no way to determine if the person being described is male or female. This is unusual and must be deliberate. It imparts to his songs a certain universality. The person before us could be anyone.</p>

				<p>The ci genre of Chinese poetry first emerged in the Sui dynasty (581-619), was further developed in the Tang dynasty (618-907) and matured in the Northern Song dynasty (960-1127). Ci is usually translated into English as "song lyrics". This is because ci were composed by poets to fit pre-existing tunes. The number of lines, the line lengths, and the tonal and rhythmic patterns of ci vary with the tunes, which number in the hundreds. One common occasion for composing ci would be a banquet: song lyrics would be scribbled down by guests and then sung by musical performers as entertainment. Other occasions for composing and enjoying ci would be more casual: the poet might sing the lyrics to himself at home or while travelling (many ci poets were civil servants of the Imperial Court and often had to travel great distances to carry out their work). Sometimes the lyrics would be sung by ordinary people in the same way as folk songs. This oral and musical quality sets it apart from other genres of poetry in China during the same period, which were largely written texts with more elevated objectives. There are two main types of ci: wǎnyuē (婉约, "graceful") and háofàng (豪放, "bold"). The wǎnyuē subgenre primarily focuses on emotion and many of its lyrics are about courtship and love, while the háofàng subgenre often deals with themes that were considered more profound by contemporary audiences, such as ageing and mortality, or the rewards and disappointments of public service.</p>

				<p>Yan Shu, a powerful statesman in the early Northern Song court, had a long and successful career both as an official and as a poet. Among his many literary achievements (which include poetry, song lyrics and prose) his ci compositions are best known. His lyrics are elegant in their choice of words, controlled in the emotions they express, and not as playful as the ci of other well-known poets. They often capture feelings of solitude and sorrow, creating a melancholic mood, but the poet is rarely explicit about what triggers the worry or sadness.</p>

				<p>Chang, Kang-i Sun. The Evolution of Tz’u Poetry: from Late Tang to Northern Sung. Princeton UP, 1980.

				A standard survey of the early history of Chinese song lyrics (romanized as both ci and tz’u).</p>

				<p>Egan, Ronald. “The Song Lyric.” The Cambridge History of Chinese Literature, vol. 1, edited by Stephen Owen, Cambridge UP, 2010, pp. 434-452.

				An overview of the genre. </p>

				<p>Owen, Stephen. Just a Song: Chinese Lyrics from the Eleventh and Early Twelfth Centuries. Asia Center, Harvard UP, 2019.

				A recent new history of the genre.</p>

				<p>Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋, editor. Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Zhonghua shu ju, 1965. 5 vols.

				A comprehensive edition of ci from the Song dynasty and the source text for the ci  in this collection (introductions and annotations are in Chinese).</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Text based on Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 89.</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">浣溪沙</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">To the tune “Sands of the Washing Stream”</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>To the tune “Sands of the Washing Stream”&#8212;"A New Song, A Single Cup Of Wine" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>The original text of this ci is based on the edition by Tang Guizhang 唐圭璋 (Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965). Punctuation follows the edition. Since ci poetry rarely includes personal pronouns, and gender-differentiated pronouns did not exist in Classical Chinese of this period, the gender of the speaker as well as their perspective (e.g. first, second or third person) must often be deduced by the translator from context.</p>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<punctuation marks="all">Punctuation follows the edition.</punctuation>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">浣溪沙</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To the tune “Sands of the Washing Stream”</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<!--Each stanza needs its own line group <lg>-->
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">一曲新詞酒一杯。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A single new song, a single cup of wine
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">去年天氣舊亭臺。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the old terrace in last year’s weather.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">夕陽西下幾時回。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The setting sun has gone west, when will it return?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="4"><!--Lines are continuously numbered through the song so check that they are correct-->
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">無可奈何花落去。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">There’s no help for it, the blossoms fall and disappear;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">似曾相識燕歸來。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I seem to recognize them, the swallows come back again.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">小園香徑獨徘徊。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the fragrant path of the little garden, I linger alone.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
