<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Song IV "Go quickly, little letter"</title>
				<author>Alcuin</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription based on</resp>
					<name>Ernst Duemmler ed., Poetae Latini Aevi Carolini, Vol. I, MGH (Berlin: Weidmann, 1881), pp. 220-3</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Samuel Cardwell</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>Alcuin (c.735–804 AD) was one of the leading figures in the so-called “Carolingian Renaissance” – the renewal or reinvigoration of education and literary/artistic production during the reign of Charlemagne (r.768–814) over the Frankish kingdom in Western Europe (encompassing much of modern France, Germany, the Low Countries and northern Italy). Alcuin was originally from York in Northumbria (what is now the North of England). He was educated at the Cathedral school in York, where he became known as a master of the liberal arts. In c.780, he traveled to Rome to receive the pallium (a sign of papal authority) for Eanbald, Archbishop of York, meeting Charlemagne for the first time on his return journey (later in the decade, he would be invited to move permanently to Charlemagne’s court, where he began his task of educational and literal renewal). On his return to England, he is believed to have written this short Latin poem, “Cartula perge cito” (“Go quickly, little letter”). It was likely composed no later than 782, since it addresses Bassinus, who ceased to be bishop of Speyer in this year. In this poem, he sends a letter of greetings to the people he met on the way to and/or from Rome. The central conceit of the poem is that Alcuin addresses (or “apostrophizes”) the letter itself, telling it to make its way down the Rhine river from Utrecht, through Cologne, to Charlemagne’s court (which was itinerant at this point, with no fixed capital), and on to Mainz, Speyer and finally to Saint-Denis (in an odd departure from the route). Given the detail of the description of the places on the way, it seems probable that the letter is following Alcuin’s own journey – for a traveler coming from the North of England, the Rhine would have been a relatively quick and safe route for travel into Italy and onto Rome. Travel literature per se is relatively rare in the early Middle Ages. As such, this poem offers remarkable insight into a major trading and pilgrimage route – the journey itself and the places and people encountered along the way. The letter’s (or Alcuin’s) arrival in Frisia is particularly striking for its treatment of the issue of lodging – the need for the traveler (in the days before travel agents and Airbnb!) to find accommodation and food on what would have been a long, uncertain journey. It is easy to imagine why Alcuin would warn travelers off the grim merchant Hrotberht in the bustling trading emporium of Dorestad – one imagines there were plenty of unwelcoming and unsavory inns and hostelries to contend with on such a journey. Elsewhere there are other charming details, like Alcuin’s fear that his gift of a grammatical manuscript might end up at the bottom of the sea. The poem is written in dactylic hexameters, the same meter used by Virgil, and the most common form of Latin verse in the early Middle Ages; it had previously been used by Alcuin’s great English predecessors, Aldhelm and Bede. Other Latin poets had used the conceit of a letter – most notably Sidonius Apollinaris’s Carmen 24, in which he sends his liber on a journey from Clermont to Narbonne. Sidonius, like Alcuin, divided his poem into a series of “frames” which fragment the letter’s itinerarium (journey) into a series of vignettes. In terms of style, the poem is also reminiscent of Virgil’s Eclogues, a series of relatively short pastoral pieces on a variety of subjects. Although little in the poem is “pastoral” in the strictest sense (there is no shepherd to be found, although there is a “cow-lord bishop”), Alcuin nevertheless evokes a world of rich produce, of “flower-filled fields” and calm rivers, a world in which one does not merely introduce oneself, but “knocks on the doors with Castalian lyre.” Alcuin quotes from Eclogue 8 in the poem, perhaps as a signal to learned readers that he was operating in this mode. At the same time, there are also echoes of Roman satire (especially Horace) in Alcuin’s playful, prodding addresses to his friends.</p>
				<p>The poem is preserved in a single manuscript, Paris, BNF, lat. 528. The manuscript is a complex compendium of poetic, grammatical and rhetorical texts, most notably including numerous epistles and poems by Paul the Deacon (d. 799). It is believed to have been compiled in Saint-Denis (near Paris) during the abbacy of Fardulf (793–806). Fardulf’s predecessor, Fulerad, is the last person addressed in Alcuin’s poem, which suggests that the “little letter” did in fact make the journey on which Alcuin sent it. It can certainly be dated to the first half of the ninth century on palaeographical grounds. By the eleventh century it had moved to the Abbey of Saint Martial in Limoges (in west-central France); it was transferred to the Bibliothèque Nationale de France at Paris in 1730.</p>
				<p>Bullough, Donald A. Alcuin: Achievement and Reputation. Brill, 2004. A useful (if slightly scattershot, having been edited posthumously from the author’s papers) introduction to Alcuin’s achievements.</p>
				<p>Godman, Peter. Poetry of the Carolingian Renaissance. Duckworth, 1985. A wide range of Carolingian poems in English translation (with Latin facing).</p>
				<p>Godman, Peter. Poets and Emperors: Frankish Politics and Carolingian Poetry. Clarendon Press, 1987. One of the only full-length studies of Carolingian Latin poetry in English.</p>
				<p>Sinisi, Lucia. “From York to Paris: Reinterpreting Alcuin’s Virtual Tour of the Continent.” Anglo-Saxon England and the Continent, edited by Hans Sauer and Joanna Story with the assistance of Gaby Waxenberger, ACMRS, 2011, pp. 275–92. An excellent recent study of the poem.</p>
				<p>Zironi, Alessandro. “An Educational Miscellany in the Carolingian Age: Paris, BNF, lat. 528.” Medieval Manuscript Miscellanies: Composition, Authorship, Use, edited by Lucie Dolez̆alová and Kimberley Rivers, Medium Aevum Quotidianum, 2013, pp. 168–81. A recent study of the manuscript in which the poem is found.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Paris BNF MS Latin 528 f.140v</p>
				<p>Published in Ernst Duemmler ed., Poetae Latini Aevi Carolini, Vol. I, MGH (Berlin: Weidmann, 1881), pp. 220-3</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Carmen IV "Cartula, perge cito"</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Song IV "Go quickly, little letter"</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Song IV 'Go quickly, little letter'"is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading. 
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>While the poem is not translated into verse, linebreaks are preserved from the original. Stanza breaks have been added corresponding to the poem’s “frames”, as described by Sinisi.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cartula, perge cito pelagi trans aequora cursu,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Go quickly, little letter, across the even surface of the sea.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ostia piscosi flabris pete fortia Rheni,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Seek out on the breeze the strong harbors of the fish-laden Rhine,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ingrediens rapidis pontum qua volvitur undis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which enters the sea where it is turned about with rushing waves.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tum tua prelongo ducatur prora remulco,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then your prow may be led by a very long tow-rope,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ne cito retrorsum rapiatur flumine puppis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Lest the vessel be seized back by the river.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Si meus Albricus veniens occurrat in amne</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If my Albricus 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Bishop of Utrecht (Traiectum), d.784.</p></note>
						should come and meet you on the river,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Vaccipotens praesul', properans tu dicito, 'salve',</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hastily say, “O Cow-Lord Bishop, greetings,”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam tibi Hadda prior nocte non amplius una</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Because Prior Hadda will serve you honey and porridge and butter <note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Alcuin uses a Germanicism butur (as opposed to butyrum).</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">In Traiect mel compultimque buturque ministrat:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In Utrecht, no more than a night’s walk from where you landed</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Utpute non oleum nec vinum Fresia fundit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">(Since Frisia pours out neither oil nor wine).</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3" type="stanza">
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hinc tua vela leva, fugiens Dorstada relinque:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Raise your sails here; flee and leave Dorestad 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>A trading emporium in Frisia, a few miles downstream from Utrecht, now known as Wijk bij Duurstede.</p></note>
						behind.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Non tibi forte niger Hrotberct parat hospita tecta,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I suspect black Hrotberht will not prepare friendly lodging for you;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Non amat ecce tuum carmen mercator avarus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">See, the greedy merchant does not love your song.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed diverte mei vatis tu litora Ione:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But pay a visit to the shores of my prophet Jonas.<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Otherwise unknown, although he must have been a reasonably significant individual, given that he is mentioned again alongside several very notable figures in line 42.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Est nam certa quies fessis venientibus illuc,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For there is surely rest for weary travellers in that place;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic holus hospitibus, piscis hic, panis abundat.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Here vegetables, here fish and bread abound for guests.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Urbis Agripina tibi pandit, scio, tecta benigne:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I know the city of Cologne  will kindly spread out lodgings for you:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic humili patrem Ricvulfum voce saluta;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Here greet father Ricwulf
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Bishop of Cologne, 772–794.</p></note>
						with humble voice;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dic: 'Tua laus mecum semper, dilecte, manebit'.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Say, “Your praise will remain with me always, beloved.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hinc castella petes currenti nave per undas,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Here you will seek out the fortified towns with a ship running through the waves,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Donec ad optatae pertingas flustra Musellae.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Until you reach the calm waters of the pleasant Moselle.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Remigio postquam spatium sulcaveris amnem,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After you have plowed this wide river with your oar,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic tum siste ratem, puppis potiatur harena,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Make your raft to stand here – let your ship occupy the sand –</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Et pete Wilbrordi patris loca sancta pedester</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And seek the holy places of father Willibrord 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Northumbrian missionary to the Frisians (c.658–739). Alcuin wrote a Life of Willibrord in both prose and verse.</p></note>
						on foot.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="5" type="stanza">
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Atque sacerdotis Samuhelis tecta require</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Find the dwellings of the priest Samuel. 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Beornrad, Abbot of Echternach (where Willibrord was buried) 776–798, from 785/6 also archbishop of Sens, at whose request Alcuin wrote the Life of Willibrord.</p></note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Castalido portas plectro pulsare memento,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Remember to knock on the doors with Castalian lyre,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Constanter puero Pithea dic voce ministro:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Constantly saying with Pythean voice to the servant boy:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Puplius Albinus me misit ab orbe Brittanno</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Puplius Albinus
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>In his later letters, Alcuin used the pseudonym Flaccus (“Flabby”) Albinus. “Puplius” here perhaps is meant to evoke Publius, the praenomen of the poets Virgil, Ovid and Statius. If the substitution of “pup” for “pub” is not due to scribal error, it is perhaps meant to suggest pupus/pupulus/pupillus – Alcuin is merely a “pupil” of the master poets.</p></note>
						sent me from the British world</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Predulci dulcem patri perferre salutem'.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To bring sweet greetings to a most kind father”.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Si tibi praesentis fuerit data copia verbi,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If an abundance of words is granted to you in person,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Fusa solo supplex plantas tu lambe sacratas,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Pour it out and go down on your knees to kiss his holy heels,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dicque 'Valeto, pater Samuhel', dic 'Vive sacerdos'.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And say, “Farewell, father Samuel”, say, “Live well, priest!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Detege iam gremium, patres et profer honestos</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Unlock your bounty and bring forth the honorable fathers</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Priscianum, Focam, tali quia munere gaudet,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Priscian and Foca,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Two fifth-century Latin grammarians.</p></note>
						for he delights in such a gift – </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Si non Neptunus pelago demerserit illos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If Neptune hasn’t plunged them into the sea!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="6" type="stanza">
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Se te forte velit regis deducere ad aulam,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If he wants to take you to the king’s court,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic proceres patres fratres percurre, saluta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Quickly review the nobles, fathers, and brothers there, and greet them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ante pedes regis totas expande camenas,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Spread out all your poetry at the feet of the king</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dicito multoties: 'Salve, rex optime, salve.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And say again and again, “Greetings, best of kings, greetings!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tu mihi protector, tutor, defensor adesto,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Be to me a protector, guardian, and defender,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Invida ne valeat me carpere lingua nocendo</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Lest jealous tongues seize me to do me harm –</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Paulini, Petri, Albrici, Samuelis, Ione,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Those of Paulinus, Peter,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Paulinus of Aquileia, Peter of Pisa, two leading figures in the Carolingian Renaissance</p></note>
						Albricus, Samuel and Jonah</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Vel quicumque velit mea rodere viscere mursu:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Or of anyone who wishes to gnaw my flesh with biting.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Te terrente procul fugiat, discedat inanis'.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let him flee away from you in terror; let the fool depart.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Mormure dic tacito: 'Cathegita Petre valeto!</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Say quietly in a murmur, “Farewell, Peter my maestro! 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Cathegita, a rare word even in Greek (but cf. Matthew 23:10), occurs three times in Alcuin’s carmina</p></note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Herculeo sevus clavo 
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Ms. claro, following emendation of Schaller (1970)</p></note>
						ferit ille, caveto'!</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Beware! That savage strikes with a Herculean club.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="47">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Paulini gaudens conplectere colla magistri,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Rejoicing, throw your arms around the neck of master Paulinus;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="48">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Oscula melligeris decies da blanda labellis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Give him ten charming kisses on his honey-bearing lips.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="49">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ricvulfum, Raefgot, Radonem rite saluta,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Greet Ricwulf, Raefgot and Rado in the right way;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="50">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Auriculas horum peditemtim tange canendo,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Touch their ears little-by-little with your singing.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="51">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dic: 'Socii fratres laiti salvete valete'.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Say, “My happy companions, brothers, hail and well-met!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="7" type="stanza">
				<l n="52">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Egregiam forsan venies Maggensis ad urbem</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Perchance you will come to the excellent and unchanging city of Mainz;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="53">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Perpetuumque vale doctori dicito Lullo,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Say hello to the doctor Lull,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Lull or Lullus (d.786) was an English missionary and successor to St Boniface as Bishop of Mainz. Mainz was elevated to an Archbishopric in 781 – it is not clear whether Alcuin was writing before or after this event.</p></note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="54">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ecclesiae specimen, sophiae qui splendor habetur,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A model for the church, who is considered the splendour of wisdom,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="55">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Moribus et vita tanto condignus honore.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Worthy of such honour for his customs and life.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>	
			<lg n="8" type="stanza">
				<l n="56">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O Bassine bone, Spirensis gloria plebis,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">O good Bassinus,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Bishop of Speyer until 782.</p></note>
						glory of the people of Speyer:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="57">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Me, rogo, commenda Paulo, pater alme, patrono,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I ask you, nourishing father, to commend me to your patron Paul,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Paul the Deacon, the highly influential Lombard scholar.</p></note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="58">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cuius et alma domus fratres nos fecerat ambos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Whose nourishing house had made us both brothers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="9" type="stanza">
				<l n="59">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Quis, Fulerade pius, lyrico te tangere plectro</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Who will dare to touch you, pious Fulerad,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Abbot of Saint-Denis, near Paris (d.784). This is an odd departure from the main route of the letter’s journey. Given that the poem survives in a Saint-Denis manuscript, I wonder if these lines represent an off-the-cuff addition to the poem, unless Alcuin expected Bassinus to pass the cartula on to Fulerad (perhaps making the poem a kind of Rhineland travelogue addressed to Fulerad).</p></note>
						with a plucked lyric?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="60">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Audebit? meritis Musarum carmina vincis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You surpass the songs of the muses with your merits.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="61">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nunc tamen hanc ederam circum sine timpora sacra</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But now let this ivy creep around your holy temples,
							<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Cf. Virgil, Eclogues, 8.11-13.</p></note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="62">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Serpere, summe pater, tibimet bonitate sueta,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">High father, through your kind goodness,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="63">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Vel demitte semel memet tibi dicere salve.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Or let me just once say ‘greetings’ to you.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="10" type="stanza">
				<l n="64">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Heia age, carta, cito navem conscende paratam;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right then, letter, get on board the ship – it’s ready to go:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="65">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Oceanum Rhenum sub te natet unca carina.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The curved keel will sail the Rhenish seas beneath you.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="66">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Materies auri non te, rogo, fulva retardet,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I pray that no yellow matter of gold may slow you down,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="67">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Accula quem fessus profert de viscere terrae.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which the weary countryman brings up from the bowels of the earth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="68">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Non castella, domus, urbes, nec florida rura</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let not strongholds, houses, cities, or flower-filled fields</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="69">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Deteneant stupidam spatio nec unius horae,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hold you back, dumbstruck, for the space of even one hour,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="70">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed fuge, rumpe moras, propera, percurre volando:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But fly! Put an end to delay! Make haste and take flight!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="71">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Incolomes sanos gaudentes atque vigentes</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I hope you joyfully find our friends</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="72">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Invenies utinam nostros gratanter amicos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Unharmed, in good health, enjoying life and on good form.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="73">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Det deus omnipotens illis per secla salutem,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">May almighty God give them health in the present world</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="74">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Postea caelestem laetos deducat in aulam.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And afterwards lead them happy into his heavenly court.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="75">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Omnibus his actis patriam tu certa reverte,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After doing all these things, be sure you return to your homeland,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="76">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Et quod quisque tibi dicat narrare memento,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And do remember to tell me anything anyone said to you.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="77">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ut cum vere novo rubrae de cortice gemmae</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So that, when the red fruits are bursting forth from new bark</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="78">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Erumpant, nostris videam te ludere tectis,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the spring, I will see you playing under our roof,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="79">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Atque novas iterum nobis adferre camenas.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And bringing us back new songs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="80">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tum tibi serta novis de floribus aurea fingam </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then will I fashion a golden wreath of new flowers for you,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="81">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Et sociata mihi pratis pausabis amoenis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And, reunited with me, you will rest in pleasant meadows.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
