<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On April – to the Praise of its Creator</title>
				<author>Bar ‘Ebroyo</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on the edition</resp>
					<name>compiled by Mor Philoxenos Yuhanon Dolabani in 1929 and republished by the Mor Ephrem Monastery in Glane, Holland in 1983.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Patrick Conlin</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>This poem by Maphrian Mor Gregorios Bar ‘Ebroyo (1226-1286) is from a collection of his poems (musḥotho) compiled by Mor Philoxenos Yuhanon Dolabani in 1929 and republished by the Mor Ephrem Monastery in Glane, Holland in 1983. Bar ‘Ebroyo (also latinized as Bar Hebraeus) was a prolific author who wrote on topics ranging from astronomy, medicine, theology, poetry, grammar, canon law, and more. He wrote in Arabic and Syriac and many of works are translations of earlier Arabic works, or at least rely heavily upon such works. As maphrian, Bar ‘Ebroyo oversaw the eastern half of the Syriac Orthodox Church, with his seat being in the Mor Matay Monastery, near Mosul, Iraq. This office was second only to the patriarch of Antioch, although in function the two were largely equal.</p>
				<p>The title of this poem implies that the month of April (nisan, in Syriac) is the subject of the author’s praise, yet the rose is really the recipient of the panegyric. The author seems to be alluding to the popular Arabic genre of the disputation poem, where two or more inanimate objects, animals, or even abstract concepts are anthropomorphized and debate their qualities. The rose and narcissus (daffodil) flowers were common interlocutors in such poems. In this poem, the rose is heralded as the most beautiful of all flowers, but is scolded by the narrator because it allows its beauty to be plucked and used by disreputable people. The Syriac text uses a 12-syllable meter with stanzas of four lines.</p>
				<p>Bar ‘Ebroyo’s poetry is largely undated, and relatively little has been written about it, although he wrote over 300 poems on topics as diverse as those found in his prose corpus. His poetry exists in several manuscripts, but there has been no critical edition published that includes an  apparatus and discussion of the manuscripts. Two collections have been published, the one I have used for this poem (Dolabani) and an earlier one by Augustinus Scebabi (1877). In Dolabani's collection, the poems are grouped by subject, and this poem is the first a section that focuses on the theme of nature.</p>
				<p>Bar ‘Ebroyo. Bar Hebraeus's Mush'hotho Book. Monastery of St. Ephrem the Syrian, 1983. This is the source used for this translation.</p>
				<p>Bar ‘Ebroyo, Gregorius Abū Al-Faraǧ, and Augustin Scebabi. Gregorii Bar-Hebraei carmina a patre Augustino Scebabi monaco maronita libanensi aleppensi correcta, ac ab eodem lexicon adjunctum. Ex Typographia Polyglotta S. C. De Propaganda Fide, 1877. Here is another earlier collection of Bar ‘Ebroyo’s poetry which includes this poem.</p>
				<p>Heinrichs, Wolfhart. “Rose versus Narcissus: Observations on an Arabic Literary Debate.” Dispute Poems and Dialogues in the Ancient and Medieval Near East: Forms and Types of Literary Debates in Semitic and Related Literatures, edited by G. J. Reinink and H. L. J. Vanstiphout. Peeters, 1991, pp. 179-198. This essay, from a collection on the Arabic dispute poem genre, discusses specifically the debate between the rose and narcissus flowers which Bar ‘Ebroyo alludes to.</p>
				<p>Takahashi, Hidemi. Barhebraeus: A Bio-Bibliography. Gorgias Press, 2013. This is a thorough biography of the author with an exhaustive bibliography of primary and secondary sources.</p>
				<p>Takahashi, Hidemi. “The Poems of Barhebraeus: A Preliminary Concordance.” Khristianskiĭ Vostok 6, no. 7, 2013, pp. 78–139. Further discussion of Bar ‘Ebroyo’s poetry with a list of major manuscripts.</p>
				<p>Taylor, C., “The Dirge of Coheleth.” The Jewish Quarterly Review 4, no. 4, July 1892, pp. 533-549. This is a discussion on the biblical book of Ecclesiastes, but contains a translation of the first two stanzas of this poem, in relation to the word ܛܺܝܛܟܘܣ (ṭēyṭkūs, “cicada”). To my knowledge, this is the only other English translation of this poem.</p>	
			</notesStmt> 
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Bar ‘Ebroyo. <hi rend="italic">Bar Hebraeus's Mush'hotho Book.</hi> Holland: Monastery of St. Ephrem the Syrian, 1983.</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">ܥܠ ܢܝܣܢ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܡܟܝܢܢܗ</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">On April – to the Praise of its Creator</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"On April" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>I have maintained the lines and stanzas in this poem, but did not follow the meter in order to better follow the literal meaning of the Syriac. The original Syriac is also rhymed, but this was not maintained either. I have translated the month nisan into April, rather than transliterating it for the sake of clarity, although it may not have exactly corresponded to the modern Gregorian month.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܗܳܐܡܛܳܐ ܢܺܝ݂ܣܳܢ ܘܰܠܥܰܝ݂ܝ̈ܩܐ ܒܝܰܐ ܢܰܦܶܫ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Behold, April has arrived and has given refreshment to those who grieve</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܒܗܰܒܳܒ̈ܐܶ ܠܛܘܪ݂ܳܐ ܘܕܰܒܪܳܐ ܫܘܒܚܳܐ ܐܰܠܒܶܫ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And in glory has clothed mountain and pasture with flowers</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܒܰܚܠܘܠ ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܠܦܰܩܚ̈ܐܶ ܐܡܺ̈ܝܢܐܶ ܩܪܳܐ ܐܳܦ ܟܰܢܶܫ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At the wedding feast of the rose, it invited, indeed, gathered blossoms as guests</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܕܡܶܢ ܓܢܘܢܳܐ ܢܶܦܘܩ ܚܰܬܢܳܐ ܐܘܪܚܳܐ ܕܳܪܶܫ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And prepared the way for the bridegroom to leave the bridal chamber.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܡܽܘܬ݁ ܟܰܠ̈ܬܳܐ ܗܳܐ ܐܶܨܛܰܒܬܘ̄ ܦܰܩ̈ܚܼܝ ܕܰܒܪܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Blossoms of the field are adorned like beautiful brides</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܡܶܢ ܩܘ݂ܠܳܪ̈ܶܐ ܕܥܘ݂ܙܳܐ ܕܣܰܬܘܳܐ ܩܢܰܘ ܚܘܪ݂ܪܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And they have attained freedom from the iron bands of winter’s fierceness</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܗܳܐ ܐܶܫܬ݁ܪܝ ܠܗ ܠܶܫܳܢ ܛܺܝܛܟܘܣ ܘܒܰܐܡܺܝܢ ܙܳܡܪܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Behold, the tongue of the cicada has been loosened and it ever sings</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܥܰܠ ܒܶܡܰܛܰܐ ܕܢܰܪܩܝܣ ܘܳܐܣܳܐ ܠܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܡܢܰܨܳܪܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And, on the seat of the narcissus and the myrtle, twitters to the rose.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3" type="stanza">
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܗܳܐ ܫܘܰܫܢ̈ܶܐ ܕܡܽܘܬ݁ ܟܰܠ̈ܳܬܳܐ ܡܶܢ ܩܰܝ݂ܛܘܢ݂̈ܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">O! the lilies look like brides from their bed-chambers</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܡܨܰܒܬܝܢ ܢܳܦܩܝܢ ܐܳܦ ܡܶܬܓܰܐܶܝܢ ܒܫܘܦܪܳܐ ܕܓܰܘܢ̈ܶܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He is adorned and he goes out, indeed, he bears himself grandly in colorful beauty</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܗܳܐ ܫܳܢܝܬܳܐ ܗܘܳܬ݁ ܠܳܗ ܛܺܝܛܟܘܣ ܒܚܘܒ݂ ܫܘܫܰܢ̈ܐܶ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">O! It is madness to the cicada – the love of the lilies</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܐܝܟ ܦܘܐ̣ܝ̣ܛܬܳܐ ܡܢܰܨܪܐ ܠܘܰܪܕܐ ܡܶܨܥܰܬ ܓܰܢ̈ܐܶ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His chirping is poetry to the rose in the midst of the garden.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܙܰܒܢܳܐ ܙܥܘܪܳܐ ܟܕ ܐܝ݂ܬܘܗ̄ܝ ܗܘܳܐ ܘܳܪܕܳܐ ܚܰܕܬܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The time when the rose is new is brief</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܨܒܳܐ ܢܶܣܬܰܬ݁ܪ ܢܶܬܶܒ ܒܶܐܣܟܺܝܡ ܡܶܨܥܰܬ݁ ܓܰܢܬܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It prefers to be destroyed, and will appear to rest amidst the garden</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܗܳܝܕܝܟ ܚܙܺܝܬܶܗ ܟܰܕ ܡܶܬܦܰܪܣܶܐ ܒܶܝܬ ܚܳܢ̈ܘܳܬܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then it sees the house of stalls when it is spread out</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܪܳܡܶܐ ܢܰܦܫܗ ܥܰܠ ܐܳܣܘ̈ܛܐܶ ܐܰܝܟ ܙܳܢܝ݂ܬܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And it lays itself down among the gluttons like a prostitute.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="5" type="stanza">
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܐܶܡܪܶܬ ܕܰܠܡܘܢ ܬܶܗܘܶܐ ܒܝ݂ܕܐ ܘܥܘܒܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I said to the rose, “Why will you be in the hand and on the bosom</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܟܽܠ ܐܳܣܘܛܳܐ ܐܳܦ ܪܳܘܰܝܳܐ ܫܪܝ݂ܚܐ ܠܰܥܒܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Of every prodigal, and indeed, wanton, greedy drunkard?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܦܰܢܝ݂ ܕܓܽܘܥ ܠܟ ܘܰܫܠܶܝ݂ ܬܠܝ ܡܶܢܝ ܪܰܘܒܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Pooh to you!” answered the rose, and it ceased and drew back from my uproar</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܚܰܝܰܝ̈̄ ܠܰܒܝܽܘܠ ܩܪܶܒܘ̄ ܘܶܐܬܡܰܛܝܘ̄ ܒܚܰܒܪܘܬ ܟܘܒ݂ܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They who are companions of thorns are reduced to dust and brought to Sheol.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="6" type="stanza">
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܐܶܡܪܶܬ ܠܡܽܘܢ ܬܶܨܕܰܠܰܠ ܒܰܕܡܽܘܬ ܦܰܚܙܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I said to the rose, “Why are you unrestrained in the appearance of licentiousness?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܡܽܘܢ ܠܐ ܬܣܰܬܰܪ ܫܘܦܪܟ ܦܰܐܝܳܐ ܒܰܙܒܰܢ ܥܘܙ݂ܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Why not reject your comely beauty in the harsh time?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܦܰܢܝ ܕܠܢܰܦܫܳܟ ܐܰܢܬ ܗܘܺܝ ܟܳܪܽܘܙܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The rose answered, “Be a preacher to yourself,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܛܳܒ ܠܝ ܦܘܚܪܳܐ ܡܶܢ ܕܰܒܟܽܘܒ݂̈ܶܐ ܐܶܗܘܶܐ ܚܪܺܝܙܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The banquet of thorns is better to me than to become strung together.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="7" type="stanza">
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܘܳܪܕܳܐ ܩܰܦܚܶܬ ܕܰܠܡܽܘܢ ܢܰܦܫܳܟ ܠܟܽܠ ܐܢܳܫܬܶܬܠ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I reprimanded the rose, “Why do you give yourself to any man?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܐܝܟ ܫܳܢܺܝܬܐ ܕܪܰܘܝܳܐ ܒܥܽܘܒܳܐ ܠܟ ܟܽܠ ܡܰܥܶܠ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he who is like a mad drunkard in the bosom every time you are new?"</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܳܪܕܐ ܦܰܢܺܝ ܕܰܟܪܶܝܢ ܚܲܝܐܶ ܘܙܺܝܘܝ̄ ܗܳܐ ܐܳܙܶܠ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The rose answered, “My life is short and of little value,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܡܽܘܢ ܐܬܦܰܠܰܛ ܕܰܠܦܰܐܝܘܬܗ ܫܘܦܪܳܐ ܚܳܡܶܠ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Why should its elegance and beauty flee when it is gathered?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="8" type="stanza">
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܘܲܪܕܳܐ ܐܶܡܪܶܬ ܟܰܕ ܓܰܢܳܢܳܐ ܠܳܟ ܗ̱ܘ ܩܳܛܶܦ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To the rose, I said, “When your gardener gathers you</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܩܽܘܪܳܝܗ̄ܝ ܒܟܘܒܳܐ ܘܠܐ ܬܶܫܒܽܘܟܩܝܗܝ ܕܠܳܟ ܢܗܶܐܚܳܛܶܦ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And you gore him with a thorn, he will not forgive, and you will be snatched”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܳܪܕܳܐ ܦܰܢܝ݂ ܕܡܶܢ ܓܰܘ ܬܰܪܥܺܝܬܝ̱ ܗܳܕܶܐ ܝܠܶܦ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the rose answered, “I thought to myself, he would have learned this:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܰܠܫܰܦܝܪܽܘܬܝ ܡܶܢ ܚܰܒܪܘܬܗ ܕܣܰܢܝܳܐ ܢܚܰܠܶܦ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His ugly companion will be renewed by my loveliness.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="9" type="stanza">
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܠܘܪܕܐ ܐܶܡܪܶܬ ܟܕ ܓܰܢܳܢܳܐ ܨܒܳܐ ܕܟܳܟ ܢܶܦܣܳܘܩ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To the rose I said, “When the gardener wants to prune you</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܒܥܘܒܳܐ ܕܩܘܪܳܝܗܝ ܘܰܕܢܶܚܛܦܳܟ ܣܳܟ ܠܳܐ ܬܶܫܒܘܩ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Interiorly, and you poke him, you will be snatched and not forgiven</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܳܪܕܳܐ ܦܰܢܝ ܕܦܽܘܡܝ ܥܠ ܗܳܕܐ ܦܶܬܚܶܬ ܕܶܐܫܘܩ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the rose answered, “Concerning my mouth, you open it and I will kiss</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܺܝܕ ܟܽܠ ܐܰܝܢܳܐ ܕܠܝ ܡܶܢ ܥܰܒܕܽܘ ܕܣܰܢܝܳܐ ܢܶܦܪܽܘܩ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The hand of all who will remove me from the thornbush.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="10" type="stanza">
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܡܶܢ ܩܘܠܳܣܰܝ̈ܟ ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܚܳܐܶܒ ܦܽܘܡ ܟܽܠ ܪܺܝܛܽܘܪ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The rose succumbs to the praises of every rhetor</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܳܐܦܶܢ ܢܶܡܠܶܐ ܡܶܢ ܣܘ̈ܓܳܬܶܗ ܪܶܒܽܘ ܐܶܫܛܳܪ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Even those who will fill up with myriad senseless songs</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܰܩܚ̈ܶܐ ܐܰܝܟ ܦܰܠܳܚ̈ܶܐ ܘܗܘ݂ ܩܽܘܪܰܛܘܪ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All blossoms are like laborers and he a curator</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܳܦ ܫܽܘܫܰܢ̈ܶܐ ܦܳܠܚ̈ܶܐ ܘܗܘ݂ ܠܚܽܘܪ ܐܘܛܘܪܐܛܘܪ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Even lilies are laborers and he alone is the emperor.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="11" type="stanza">
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܡܶܢ ܩܽܘܠܳܣ̈ܰܝ ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܚܳܐܶܒ ܟܽܠ ܠܶܫܳܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Colossian roses are conquered by every tongue</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܡܶܢ ܫܘܫܰܢ̈ܶܐ ܚܰܒܪ̈ܶܐ ܗܕܝ݂ܪܐ ܩܢܶܐ ܦܽܘܪܳܫܢܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Because magnificent lilies are obtained as a gift by charmers</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܰܩܚ̈ܶܐ ܐܰܝܟ ܦܰܠܳܚ̈ܶܐ ܘܗ݂ܘ ܪܺܝܫܳܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All blossoms are like laborers and he is the ruler</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܽܘܢ ܙܳܗܪ̈ܐ ܓܶܕܫܳܢܳܝ̈ܐ ܘܗܘ݂ ܐܳܕܳܫܢܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Every brightness is accidental and his is essential.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="12" type="stanza">
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܳܘ ܦܳܪܘܫܳܐ ܕܰܠܡܳܐ ܬܶܚܙܐ ܠܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܫܲܒܪܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">O! Is the rose not distinguished above Syrian rue?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܠܫܘܰܫ̈ܢܶܐ ܣܳܒ̈ܶܐ ܗܕܺܝܪ̈ܶܐ ܩܰܢ̈ܝܰܝ ܫܽܘܦܪܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And are not the lilies’ old splendors hated by beautiful ones?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="47">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܰܩܚ̈ܶܐ ܥܰܒ̈ܪܶܐ ܐܶܢܘܢ ܟܕ ܗܘ݂ ܚܺܐܪܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All blossoms are servants while he is noble</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="48">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܠܶܗ ܗܘ݂ ܣܳܓܕܝܢ ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܟܽܠ ܝܘܡ݂ ܐܰܝܟ ܕܰܠܡܳܪܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And to him they bow, every single day like to the Lord.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="13" type="stanza">
				<l n="49">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܬܳܐ ܚܺܙܐ ܠܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܒܰܕܡܽܘܬ ܥܽܘܠܳܐ ܒܓܰܘ ܥܰܙܪܘܪ݂̈ܶܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Come, see in the rose the image of a baby inside swaddling clothes</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="50">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܰܠܫܘܫܰܢ̈ܶܐ ܐِܚܪ̈ܢܶܐ ܕܫܰܪܟܳܐ ܣܳܒ̈ܶܐ ܗܕܝܪ̈ܶܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And in the rest of the other lilies are old splendors</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="51">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܶܠܐ ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܥܰܒܕܘ݂ ܦܳܠܚܺܝܢ ܠܗ ܒܪ ܚܺܐܪ̈ܶܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But they are all made to serve, working for freeborn sons.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="52">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܗܘܝ݂ܘ ܒܰܠܚܽܘܕ ܡܳܪܳܐ ܘܦܰܩܚ̈ܶܐ ܠܗ ܐܺܣܝܪ̈ܶܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That is to say, he alone is Lord and the blossoms are bound to him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="14" type="stanza">
				<l n="53">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܳܘ ܦܳܪܽܘܫܳܐ ܬܳܐ ܐܶܬܦܰܪܓܳܐ ܒܗܳܢܳܐ ܓܢܽܘܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">O discerning one, come be bright in this bridal chamber</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="54">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܕܠܰܝܬ ܠܶܗ ܦܶܚܡܳܐ ܒܦܰܐܝܽܘܬܳ ܫܘܦܪܳܐ ܕܪܺܝܚܳܐ ܘܓܰܘܢܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which has no equal in beauty and elegance of scent and color</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="55">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܒܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܐܶܨܕ ܕܰܡܥܶܠܶܝܬܳܐ ܥܛܺܝܦ ܟܘܬܝܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Consider the roses of the entrance which are clothed in a linen tunic</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="56">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܡܶܨܥܰܬ݁ ܦܰܩ̈ܚܶܐ ܘܠܐ ܬܶܬܦܰܠܰܓ ܕܗܽܘ݂ܝܽܘ ܚܰܬܢܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the midst of blossoms undivided, that is to say, married.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="15" type="stanza">
				<l n="57">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܰܩ̈ܚܶܐ ܐܰܝܟ ܩܳܦܺܝ̈ܠܶܐ ܘܘܰܪܕܐ ܒܽܘܟܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All of the blossoms are as if stripped bare, and the rose, a nobleman</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="58">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܐܳܦ ܫܽܘܫܰܢ̈ܐ ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܙܡܝܢ̈ܐ ܘܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܚܰܬܢܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The lilies are all like invited guests and the rose is married</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="59">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܙܰܗܪ̈ܶܐ ܐܝܟ ܢܰܗܝܪ̈ܶܐ ܘܘܰܪܳܕܐ ܥܰܝܢܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All flashes are like lights and the rose is the eye</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="60">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܝܰܬܝܪ ܡܶܢܗܘܢ ܗܘܠܚܽܘܪ ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܨܰܡܘܚܬܳܢܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the only one that surpasses them in brilliance is the rose.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="16" type="stanza">
				<l n="61">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܒܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܙܰܗܪ̈ܶܐ ܘܰܪܕܳܐ ܒܰܠܚܽܘܕ ܐܝ݂ܬܘܗ̄ܝ ܢܺܝܫܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With every flash, the rose alone has a banner</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="62">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܐܦܶܢ ܢܶܗܘܐ ܡܶܢ ܪ̈ܰܘܳܝܶܐ ܒܦܽܘܚܪܳܐ ܕܝܳܫܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Although it will be from drunkards in an evil banquet</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="63">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܰܩ̈ܚܶܐ ܒܰܕܡܽܘܬ ܪ̈ܶܓܠܶܐ ܘܘܰܪܕܐ ܪܝ݂ܫܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The rose tramples on all blossoms in the image of a foot</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="64">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܕܺܝܠܗ ܫܘܦܪܳܐ ܕܺܝܠܳܢܝܐ ܘܕܺܝܠܗܘܢ ܛܝܫܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And its own beauty is unique and theirs are bastardized.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="17" type="stanza">
				<l n="65">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܪܓܺܝܓ ܗܘܘܲܪܕܐ ܥܰܠ ܟܽܠ ܢܦܫܳܐ ܡܠܟܳܐ ܘܡܳܟܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The rose is desirable above every living king and lowly one</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="66">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܒܰܕ ܥܰܠ ܦܰܩ̈ܚܶܐ ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܦܳܠܚ̈ܶܐ ܗܘ݂ܝܘ ܡܰܠܟܳܐ܂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Because, concerning blossoms, they are all laborers compared to the king</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="67">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܙܰܗܪ̈ܶܐ ܠܗ ܒܰܠܚܘ ܕܰܘܗ̄ܝ ܣܳܝܡܶܝܢ ܒܘܪܟܳܐ܃</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All of their flashes are made to kneel to it alone</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="68">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ܘܪܰܢܩܪ ܒܘܢ ܠܗ ܕܳܫܢ̈ܶܐ ܕܫܘܒܚܳܐ ܢܳܣܒܺܝܢ ܡܶܠܟܳܐ܀</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And they who draw near to it receive gifts of glory from the king.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
