<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>First Decade of Asia</title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"First Decade of Asia" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">First Chapter, on how the Muslims came to conquer Spain: and on how after Portugal became a kingdom, its Kings drove away the Muslims to the overseas, both to parts of Africa and Asia, where the Portuguese Kings went to conquer them and on the reasons why this book has the title it has.</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Alevantado em a terra de Arabia aquelle grande antechristo Mafamede, quasi nos annos de quinhentos nouenta &#38; tres de nossa redempçam, assi laurou a furia de seu ferro &#38; fogo de sua infernal secta, per meyo de seus capitâes, &#38; calyfas: que em espaço de cem annos, conquistaram em Asia toda Arabia, &#38; parte da Syria &#38; Persia, &#38; em Africa todo Egypto daquem, &#38; dalem do Nilo.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the great Antichrist Mohammed emerged in the land of Arabia, sometime around the year of five hundred ninety-three of our redemption, he adorned the conquering fury of his infernal sect with fire and iron by deploying his captains and caliphs to conquer all of Arabia in the Asian continent, as well as parts of Syria and Persia, and all of Egypt around the Nile in Africa, which they did in the space of a hundred years.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E segundo escreuem os Arabios no seu Larigh, que he hum summario dos feitos que fizeram os seus calyfas na conquista da quellas partes do oriente: neste mesmo tempo, dela se leuataram, &#38; vieram grandes exames delles pouoar estas do ponente a que elles chamam Algarb, &#38; nos corruptamente Algarue dalem mar.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">According to what the Arabs write in their Larigh (which is a summary of their caliphs’ deeds in their conquest of the East), during that same period, the Arabs emerged from the East as great swarms and came to populate these lands of the West, which they called Algarb, and we mistakenly call Algarve overseas.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="3">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Os quaes a força de armas deuastando &#38; asolando as terras, se fizeram senhores da mayor parte da Mauritania, Tingitania, em que se comprendem os reynos de Fez, &#38; Marrocos: sem ate este tempo a nossa Europa sentir a perseguiçam desta praga.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It was through the use of arms, destroying and laying waste to the lands, that those Arabs made themselves the lords of most of Mauritania, Tingitania,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>North of Morocco.</p></note>where the kingdoms of Fez and Morocco lie: all these events happened without our Europe having felt the effects of such plague.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="4">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pero vindo o tempo [a]te o qual Deos quis dissimular os peccados de Espanha, esperando sua penitencia acerca das heresias de Arrio, Eluido, &#38; Pelagio de que ella andou muy yscada: (posto que ja per sanctos consilios nella celebrados fossem desterradas,)</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">However, the time came for God to undo the sins of Spain. Spain was awaiting its punishment for the heresies that influenced it for a long time, such as Arius, Helvidius, and Pelagius (even though those heresies had already been condemned by holy councils).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">em lugar de penitencia acresentou outros muy graues &#38; pubricos peccados, &#38; que mais acabaram de encher a medida de sua condenaçam, que a forca feita a Caua filha do conde Iuliam (ainda que esta foy a causa vltima, &#38; accidetal, segundo querem alguns escriptores.)</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead of granting Spain its penitence, God added other, more egregious and public sins, such as the harm done to Cava, daughter of Count Julian which filled the cup whereby God measured the need for punishment (even if this was ultimately accidental, as some writers claim).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="5">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Com as quaes cousas prouocada a justiça de Deos, vsou de seu diuino &#38; antigo juyzo: que sempre foy castigar pubricos &#38; gerâes peccados, com pubricos &#38; notaueis peccadores, &#38; permitir que hum hereje seja açoute doutro, vingandose per esta maneira de seus imigos per outros mayores imigos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All that brought God’s justice onto Spain, who employed His divine and ancient reasoning, which was always to punish public and overspread sin by deploying other public and notorious sinners, thus making one heretic the whip that punishes another, thus taking revenge on some of His enemies by deploying other and greater ones.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="6">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E como naquelle tempo estes Arabios eram os mais notauees que elle tinha, infestando o imperio Romano &#38; perseguindo sua catholica Igreja: primeiro que per elles castigasse Espanha os quis castigar na sua heresia,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As in that time God’s most notorious enemies were the Arabs, who infested the Roman empire and persecuted God’s Catholic Church, he also wished to punish them for their heresies first, before He used them to punish Spain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">acendendo antre elles hum fogo de competencia, sobre quem se assentaria na cadeira do pontificado de sua abominaçam, com este titulo de calyfa, que naquelle tempo era a mayor degnidade da sua secta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So he kindled the fire of competition over who would sit on the pontifical throne of their abominable heresy, that is who would bear the title of Caliph, which was the sect’s greatest dignitary title back then.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="7">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E depois de Arabia, Syria, &#38; parte da Persia, arderem com guerras de confusam aquem perualeceria neste estado, em que morreo grande numero delles,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And thus Arabia, Syria, and part of Persia burned in confusing wars over who was to prevail, which caused the death of many.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">tendo cada parentella enlegido calyfa antre sy:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wars resulted in each family group electing their own Caliph amongst themselves.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ieram alguns naquella parte interior de Arabia onde esta situa da a cidade Cufa, per concordia de sua cisma babilonica, enleger por calyfa a hum arabio chamado, C,afa:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Some of these came to the interior of Arabia, where the city called Kufa lies, and agreed to elect an Arab man called C,afa as to overcome their Babylonian schism.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dizendo que a elle pertencia aquelle Pontificado por ser o mais chegado parente de Mafamede: ca elle vinha per linha direita de Abaz seu tio, a linhagem do qual Abaz elles chamam Abazcion.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They said that the Pontificate belonged to C,afa because he was Mohammad’s closest relative: through his uncle Abaz, C,afa was a direct descendant from Mohammad’s line, a line which they called Abazcion.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="8">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E porque quando o aleuantaram por seu calyfa, foy com lhe darem juramento que auia de ir destruir o calyfa que emtam residia na cidade Damasco que era dalinhagem a que elles chamam Maraunion, em a qual auia muytos annos que andaua o calyfado per modo de tyrannia mais que per eleiçam, &#38; por isso era esta geraçam muy auorecida antre a mayor parte dos Arabios:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He was proclaimed the Caliph only after he had sworn that he would destroy the Caliph who then dwelled in the city of Damascus, who was from the so-called lineage of Maraunion, who had ruled that Caliphate [of Damascus] for many years by tyranny rather than election, and that is the reason why this generation was so covetous in comparison to the majority of Arabs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ordenou logo este nouo calyfa hum seu parente per nome Abedela benAlle, que com grande numero de gente de cauallo fosse sobre o calyfa de Damasco.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus, because those were the conditions of him being proclaimed Caliph of Kufa, the new Caliph sent a relative of his, called Abdullah bin Alle, to attack the Caliph of Damascus with a great army of mounted soldiers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="9">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O qual Abedela sendo com este exercito junto do rio Eufrates topou o mesmo calyfa que hya Buscar, que vinha de dar huma batalha a outro calyfa nouamente aleuantado nas partes da Mesopotamia:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Abdullah, who was with his army close to the Euphrates river, stumbled upon the Caliph he sought and who was returning from a skirmish with another Caliph who emerged somewhere in Mesopotamia:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">&#38; rompendo ambos seus exercitos, ouue antre elles huma muy crua batalha em que o calyfa de Damasco foy vencido.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and both armies collided, there was a very crude battle between them, which the Caliph of Damascus lost.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="10">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E temendo elle a furio deste seu imigo Abedela, quis se recolher na cidade Damasco de tantos tempos fora senhor: mas os moradores della lhe fecharão as portas sem o quererem receber, com que lhe conueo fugir pera a cidade do Cayro, onde achou pior gasalhado, dizendo todolos cidadões que deos os tinha liurado de hum tam mao homem como elle sempre fora.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Fearing his sworn enemy Abdullah’s fury, the Caliph of Damascus retreated into the city that he presided over as Caliph: but its inhabitants shut their doors on him as they did not want to host him there, after which he went to the city of Cairo, where he was even more poorly hosted, as every inhabitant of Cairo claimed that they were delivered from a very evil man as the Caliph of Damascus had been before.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="11">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Vendoso elle em todalas partes tam mal recibido, ja desemparado dos seus, como homem desesperado do adjutorio delles quis se passar aos Gregos:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Seeing that he was not welcomed anywhere, and having lost his supporters, he desperately resorted to the Greeks’ aid:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">&#38; indo com hum escrauo seu, foy ter a huma Ilha onde sendo conhecido o mataram, no qual acabaram todolos calyfas de Damasco,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and there he went with a slave of his, arriving in an Island where they knew of him, where he was killed, thus ending all Caliphs from Damascus;</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="12">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Abedela seu imigo tanto que venceo &#38; soube quam mal recibido hera dos proprios feus, sem o querer mais perseguir foy se dereitamente a Damasco:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">meanwhile, Abdullah, his enemy, as soon as he won the battle against him and because he knew that the Caliph of Damascus was not welcome among his people, he did not chase the Caliph of Damascus and went directly to Damascus himself:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="13">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">&#38; tomada pose da cidade, a primeira cousa que fez, foy mandar defenterrar o calyfa Yazit que era dos primeiros que ali foram daquella linhagem Maraunion, auendo ja muy tos annos que era falecido, os hosos do qual com hum aucto publico manduo queimar.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And with the city taken, the first thing he ordered was that the Caliph Yazit was to be exhumed so that his bones could be burned in a public act, Yazit who was one of the first of the Maraunion lineage, having died years before.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">orque sendo Docem neto de Mafamede seu legislador, filho de sua filha Aixa, &#38; de Alle seu sobrinho, direitamente en legido por calyfa como fora seu pay: elle. Yazat nam somente lhe nam quisera obedecer, mas ainda tene modo como Docem fosse morto,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And that was because years before Yazit had chosen not to obey Doxem and had ordered Doxem’s death, who was Mohammed’s grandson and the ruler of those lands, son of Mohammed’s daughter Aixa with Alle his nephew, and who was rightly elected Caliph as his father had been.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="14">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">tudo por elle Yazit se leuantar com o calyfado, o qual pesuyo tyrannicamente, E assi todolos de sua linhage per muytos tempos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All of that Yazit did so that he could rise in that Caliphate, which he ruled tyrannically, and so did every one of his descendants for centuries.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="15">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E nam contente este Abedela com tomar tal vingança deste Yazit, geralmente a toda sua parentela mandaua matar com mil generos de tormentos, &#38; lançar seus corpos no campo âs feras &#38; aues delle: dizendo serem todos efcomungados &#38; dignos de nam ter sepultura, pois eram do sangue da quelle pessimo homem que mandou derramar o do justo Docem, vngido naquella dignidade de calyfa per o testamento de seu auo Mafamede.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And Abdullah, unsatisfied with his revenge on Yazit, ordered that all of his relatives and extended family to be tortured to death, and throwing their bodies in the fields for his beasts and birds to eat: he also ordered that they be excommunicated and that they were not dignified enough to have a grave, as they had the same blood of the rascal who had spilled Doxem’s blood, whom Mohammed himself had anointed Caliph in his will.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="16">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Da furia &#38; fogo das quaes cruezas que este Abedela fazia, saltou huma faisca que veo abrasar toda Espanha, &#38; o caso procedeo per esta maneira.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From the same fury and fire that originated from Abdullah’s cruelties, there was a spark that came to burn all of Spain and it happened thus:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Antre alguns desta linhagem Marauniom que este capitam Abedela perseguia, auia hum hômem poderoso chamado AbedRamon filho de Mauhyam, &#38; neto de Doxon, &#38; bisneto de Abbedelmalc: o qual auo &#38; bisauo em tempo passado foram tambem calyfas daquella cidade Damasco.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">among those of the Maraunion lineage who Abdullah was persecuting, there was a powerful man named Abed Ramon, son of Mauhyam, and grandson of Doxon, and great grandson of Abdullmalec: whose grandfather and great-grandfather, back then, were also Caliphs in that city of Damascus.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="17">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E vendo elle a perseguiçam de sua linhagem &#38; as cruezas que Abedela nella fazia, temendo receber outros taes em sua pessoa: recolheo pera si os mais parentes que pode, com outra gente solta, cuja vida era andar em guerras &#38; roubos, &#38; feito hum grande excercito de gente por autorizar sua pessoa, meyo fogindo veo ter a estas partes do ponente.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As he was seeing how Abdullah persecuted his line and the cruelties Abdullah was carrying out, and as he feared that he would be subject to those, he gathered as many relatives as he could, with other wandering people whose lives were dedicated to wars and ransacking, and having gathered a great army to empower himself, and, while escaping Abdullah, he came to these lands to the West,</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="18">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Onde, assi por ser da linhagem dos calyfas de Damasco, como por ser homem valeroso &#38; caualeiro de sua pessoa foy muy bem recebido, &#38; concorreo a ella tanta gente arabia da que ja ca andaua nestas partes dos Algarues dalem mar, que vendose tam poderoso em gente &#38; opiniam de secta:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Where he was welcomed because he was brave, knightly and from the lineage of the Caliphs of Damascus and he gathered many people from Arabia who joined him, people who had already been living in these parts across the sea from Algarve (North Africa), and seeing that he was powerful because he had many followers and was well-perceived:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="19">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tomou ousadia a se intitular com nouo nome chamandose principe dos Crentes nesta palaura arabia Miralmuminim, a que nos coruptamente chamamos Miramulim, &#38; isto quasi em opprobio &#38; reprouaçam dos calyfas da linhagem de Abaz que nouamente foram leuantados na Arabia por cuja causa elle se desterrou daquellas partes de Damasco.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He dared name himself the prince of the Believers with the Arabic word Miralmuminim, which we erroneously say Miramulim, and he did this in spite of, and with the rejection by the Caliphs of the lineage of Abaz, who again raised their armies in Arabia and because of whom Abed Ramon had gone into exile away from Damascus.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="20">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E nam se contentando ainda com este nouo &#38; soberbo nome, fundou a cidade Marrocos pera cadeira de seu estado &#38; metropoli daquella regiam (posto que algumas cronicas dos arabios querem que a edificou Iosep filho Iestim, &#38; outros que outro principe, como veremos em a nossa geographia.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And not satisfied with his new and lofty name, he founded the city Morocco, making it the seat of his estate and metropolis of that region (despite some Arab chroniclers saying that the city of Morocco was founded by Joseph, son of Jestim, and other prices, as we will see in our Geography).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="21">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">A causa da fundaçam da qual cidade, dizem alguns delles que nam foy tanto por gloria que este AbedRamom teue da memoria do seu nome: quanto em reprouaçam doutra que ouuio dizar que fundaua o calyfa Bujafar irmão &#38; sucessor do calyfa Cafa, que foy causa de se elle vir a estas partes.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The reason why that city was founded, as some Arab historians claim, is not so much for the glory that Abed Ramon wanted for his name, but more as a rejection of another city he heard was founded by Caliph Bujafar, brother and successor of the Caliph Cafa, who was the original cause for Abed Ramon to come to these parts (Northern Africa).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="22">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">A qual cidade que este Bujafar fundou tambem, era pera cadeira onde auia sempre de residir o seu pontificado de calyfa: &#38; he aquella a que ora os mouros chamam Bagodad, situada na prouincia de Babilonia nas correntes do rio Eufrates.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The city that Bujafar founded was also intended to be the seat of his Pontifical Caliphate and it is the city that today the Moors call Baghdad, which lies in the Province of Babylon on the margins of the Euphrates.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="23">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"> E segundo escreuem os Parseos &#38; Arabeos no seu Larigh que alegamos, o qual temos em nosso poder em lingua Parsea: foy esta cidade Bagodad fundada per conselho de hum astrologo gentio per nome Nobach, &#38; tem por ascendente o signo Sagitario, &#38; acabouse em quatro annos, &#38; custou dezoito contos douro, da qual em a nossa geographia faremos mayor relaçam.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And as the Persians and Arabs write in their Larigh that we now mention, which we have in our possession in Persian language: that city Baghdad was founded on the counsel of a gentile astrologer whose name was Nobach and the city was founded under the sign of Sagittarius &#38; the founding of Bagdad took four years, and cost eighteen counts of gold, an account of which we will further expand in our geography.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="24">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pois estando este nouo Miralmuminim com potencia em estado &#38; numero de gente, feito outro Nabuchodonosor pera castigo do pouo de Espanha: totalmente seu filho Vlid que o sucedeo em nome, &#38; poder se fez senhor della, per Mussa, &#38; per outros seus capitães, em tempo del Rey dom Rodrigo, o derradeiro dos Godos.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus, since this new Miralmunimim had both the stately potency and many supporters, just like another Nebuchadnezzar for the plight of the people of Spain, his son Ulid who succeeded him was able to rule over Spain completely, with the aid of Mussa and other captains in his service, during the time of the king, Lord Roderick, the last of the Goths.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="25">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Mas aprouue a diuina misericordia que este açoute de sua justiça, tornasse logo atras daquelle impeto de vitorias, que per espaço de trinta meses teue: dando animo &#38; fauor aquelle bemauenturado Principe dom Pelayo, com que logo começou ganhar as terras que ja estauaom subditas ao ferro &#38; cruezas destes alarues.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But praised be divine mercy that this strike of punishment and justice that befell Spain would be followed by many victories, which happened over a period of thirty months: the divine mercy bestowed courage upon and favored that blessed Prince Lord Pelayo, who began to win back the lands that were subjected to the iron and cruelties of those brutes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="26">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E procedendo estas vitorias em recobrar Espanha per discurso de trezentos quorenta &#38; tantos annos: vieram ter a el Rey dom Affonso o sexto deste nome, dalcunha o brauo que tomou Toledo aos mouros.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">These victories that won Spain back occurred over three-hundred forty and some years: Alphonse VI, the Brave, whose name stemmed from having won Toledo back from the Moors.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="27">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O qual querendo satisfazer aos seruiços &#38; ajudas que lhe o conde dom Anrique nesta guerra dos mouros tinha feito &#38; dado, nam achou cousa mais digna de sua pessoa, nem de mayor galardam, que aceitallo por filho, dandolhe por molher a sua filha dona Tareija:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Alphonse VI, who wanted to reward the services the count Lord Henry had rendered him, and the aid he had given him, Alphonse VI found that accepting Henry as a son was the most worthy thing to do, the most worthy prize, so he gave his daughter Lady Tareija to Henry in marriage:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="28">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">&#38; em dote, todalas terras que naquelle tempo eram tomadas aos mouros nesta parte da Lusitania que ora he Reyno de Portugal, com todalas mais que elle podesse conquistar delles.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the dowry was all the lands that were hitherto taken by the Moors in this part of Lusitania, which is now the Kingdom of Portugal, and whichever other lands from such parts that he could win back from the Moors, which included some lands in Andalusia;</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Em que entrauaom algumas de Andaluzia, porque em todas estas elle &#38; seu filho el Rey dom Afonso Anriquez verteram seu sangue por as ganhar das mãos &#38; poder dos Mouros: (como se vera em a outra parte da nossa escriptura chamada Europa.)</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">there, Henry and his son the king, Lord Alphonse Henry, spilled their blood to recover the lands from the hands and the rule of the Moors: (as we will see in another work of ours called Europe).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="29">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O qual dote, &#38; herança, parece que foy dado com tal bençam per este catholico Rey dom Afonso: que todolos seus descendentes que a herdassem, sempre teuessem continua guerra com esta perfida gente dos Arabios.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Such dowry and inheritance was given with the blessing of the very Catholic king, Lord Alphonse (VI), with the condition that all his descendants who inherited the lands given as the dowry would always fight against the perfidious Arab peoples.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="30">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Porque começando deste tempo té o presente, que he discurso de quatrocentos &#38; tantos annos de idade deste Reyno de Portugal, depois que apartado da coroa de Espanha teue este nome: assi parmaneceo em continua guerra destes infieis, que com verdade se pode dizer por elle, ter vestido mais armas que pelotes.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And that is why, beginning then, up until now, a period that encompasses four-hundred and many years of this era, that the Kingdom of Portugal received its name, after being separated from the crown of Spain, and so it has remained in a perpetual state of war against the infidels, that we can say the kingdom of Portugal has worn armor more often than robes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="31">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Donde podemos afirmar que esta casa de coroa de Portugal, esta fundada sobre sangue de martyres, &#38; que martyres a dilatam, &#38; estendem per todo o vniuerso: se este nome podem merecer aquelles que militando pola fee offerecem suas vidas a Deos em sacrficio, &#38; dotam suas fazendas a sumotuosos templos que fundaram.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And we can also say that this house of the crown of Portugal is founded upon the blood of martyrs and that martyrs have expanded it throughout the whole universe, because martyr is the name that we give those who have willingly given their lives in sacrifice for their faith in God,  and those who found sumptuous temples in their lands.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="32">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Como vemos que fez el Rey dom Afonso Anriquez primeiro, fundador desta casa real, &#38; o conde dom Anrique seu padre &#38; toda a nobreza &#38; fidalguia que os seguia nesta confissam &#38; defensam da fee, da qual verdade sam testemunho muy dotados &#38; magnificos templos deste Reyno.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This is what we know the King Alphonse Henry the First did, founder of this royal house and the count Lord Henry his father also, and all the nobility and important people who followed them in their practice and defense of the faith, as we see the many magnificent and gifted temples that stand as proof of the truth of these events.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="33">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E passados os primeiros annos de infancia delle, que foy todo o tempo que esteue no berço em que naceo, limitado na costa do mar Oceano (porque o mais do sertam da terra, ficou na coroa de Castella, &#38; a ella lhe nam coube mais em sorte nesta nossa Europa:)</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And after the first years of the kingdom’s infancy had passed, which was the period when it lay in the cradle it was born, bordering the sea Ocean on the West (because the most interior part of the land remained with the crown of Castile and to which nothing else belonged in this Europe of ours):</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="34">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Todo o trabalho daquelles Principes que entam o gouernauam, foy alimpar a casa desta infiel gente dos Arabeos que lha tinham occupada do tempo da perdição de Espanha, té totalmente a poder de ferro os lançarem alem mar, com que se intitularam Reys de Portugal, &#38; do Algarue.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All the toils of those Princes who ruled over the kingdom of Portugal was to enlarge it at the expense of the Arab peoples who had occupied it during the times of punishment of Spain, until they completely cast them out overseas by their military power, when they became the Kings of Portugal and of Algarve.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="35">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E assi estaua limpa delles no tempo del Rey dom Ioam o primeiro, que desejando elle derramar seu sangue na guerra dos infieis, por auer a benção de seus auôos, esteue determinado de fazer guerra aos Mouros do Reyno de Gra[na]da: &#38; por algus inconuenientes de Castella, &#38; assi por mayor gloria sua, passou alem mar em as partes de Africa, onde tomou aquella Metropoly Cepta cidade tam cruel competidor de Espanha, como Cartago foy de Italia.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And thus the land was free from the Arabs in the time of the King, Lord John the First, who, wishing that he himself could spill his own blood in the war against the infidels, and since he had been blessed by his forefathers, was determined to wage war against the Moors of the Kingdom of Granada  and because of some inconveniences that Castile brought forth, as well as to attain even more glory for himself, he went overseas into parts of Africa, where he conquered that Metropolis Ceuta, as cruel a rival city to Spain as Carthage had been to Italy.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="36">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Da qual cidade se logo intitulou por senhor, como quem tomaua posse daquella parte de Africa, &#38; [d]eixaua porta aberta a seus filhos &#38; netos pera irem mais auante.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He named himself Lord of that city, an action whereby he also took over that part of Africa and left the door open for his sons and grandsons to go even further beyond.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="36">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O que elles muy bem compriram, porque nam somente tomaran cidades villas &#38; lugares, nos principaes portos, &#38; forças dos Reynos de Fez, &#38; Marrocos, restituindo a Igreja Romana a jurisdição que naquellas partes tinha perdida depois da perdiçam de Espanha, como obedientes filhos &#38; primeiros capitães polla fee nestas partes de Africa: mas ainda foram despregar aquella diuina &#38; real bandeira da milicia de Christo (que elles fundaram pera esta guerra dos infieis) nas partes Orientaes da Asia em meyo das infernaes mesquitas da Arabea, &#38; Persia, &#38; de totolos pagôdes da gentilidade da India daquem, &#38; dalem do Gange: partes onde (segundo escriptores Gregos &#38; latinos) excepto a illustre Semirames, Bacho, &#38; o grande Alexandre, ninguem ousou cometer.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which they did very well, as they were good sons and captains of God’s faith in these parts of Africa, they did well not only because they conquered the main port cities and places and forces of the kingdoms of Fez and Morocco, restoring the Catholic Church’s jurisdiction in that area, which she had lost after the punishment of Spain, but also because they went to the Oriental parts of Asia to fly the divine and royal flag of the Order of Christ (which they had founded to wage war against the infidels), plunging into the middle of the infernal mosques of Arabia, Persia, and all gentile temples of the people of India, before and beyond the Ganges: parts where, according to the Greek and Roman writers, nobody dared reach, except for the illustrious Semirames, Bacchus and the great Alexander.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="37">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">O que elles muy bem compriram, porque nam somente tomaran cidades villas &#38; lugares, nos principaes portos, &#38; forças dos Reynos de Fez, &#38; Marrocos, restituindo a Igreja Romana a jurisdição que naquellas partes tinha perdida depois da perdiçam de Espanha, como obedientes filhos &#38; primeiros capitães polla fee nestas partes de Africa: mas ainda foram despregar aquella diuina &#38; real bandeira da milicia de Christo (que elles fundaram pera esta guerra dos infieis) nas partes Orientaes da Asia em meyo das infernaes mesquitas da Arabea, &#38; Persia, &#38; de totolos pagôdes da gentilidade da India daquem, &#38; dalem do Gange: partes onde (segundo escriptores Gregos &#38; latinos) excepto a illustre Semirames, Bacho, &#38; o grande Alexandre, ninguem ousou cometer.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which they did very well, as they were good sons and captains of God’s faith in these parts of Africa, they did well not only because they conquered the main port cities and places and forces of the kingdoms of Fez and Morocco, restoring the Catholic Church’s jurisdiction in that area, which she had lost after the punishment of Spain, but also because they went to the Oriental parts of Asia to fly the divine and royal flag of the Order of Christ (which they had founded to wage war against the infidels), plunging into the middle of the infernal mosques of Arabia, Persia, and all gentile temples of the people of India, before and beyond the Ganges: parts where, according to the Greek and Roman writers, nobody dared reach, except for the illustrious Semirames, Bacchus and the great Alexander.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="38">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Com as quais vitorias que os Reys deste Reyno ouueram nestas tres partes da terra, Europa, Africa, &#38; Asia, ganhando Reynos &#38; estados, acrescentaram sua coroa com nouos, &#38; illustres titulos que lhe deram do que alguns Principes desta nossa Europa tem nos estados de que se intitulam, dos quaes esta em posse esta barbara gente de mouros sem os poderem vindicar per lei de armas.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With these victories that the kings of this Kingdom carried out in the three parts of the globe, Europe, Africa, and Asia, conquering Kingdoms and states, they have expanded their crown, receiving new and illustrious titles, which some other Princes in this Europe of ours bear, but whose territories are still in possession of the barbarous people of the Moors, which the other Princes cannot recover by waging war.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="39">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">E os Reyes deste Reyno, sendo senhores do Reyno de Ormuz, cujo estado tem boa parte &#38; amilhor da terra maritima da Arabia, &#38; da Persia, &#38; senhores do Reyno de Cambaya com lhe ter tomado o maritimo delle, &#38; senhores do Reyno de Goa, com as terras, &#38; ilhas a ella adjacentes, &#38; senhores da requissima Malaca situada na Aurea Chersoneso tam celebrada dos geographos, &#38; fenhores das ilhas Orientaes de Maluco, Banda, &#38;c. somente se intitulam por Reys de Portugal, &#38; dos Algarues daquem &#38; dalem mar, senhores de Guine, &#38; da conquista, nauegaçam, &#38; comercio, da Ethiopia, Arabia, Persia, &#38; India:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And though as the Kings of this Kingdom, they are the lords of the Kingdom of Ormuz, of which they possess most parts, and which has the best maritime land of Arabia and Persia, and as they are also lords of the Kingdom of Cambaya after having conquered its maritime access, and as they are also lords of the Kingdom of Goa, with its adjacent lands and islands, and as they are also lords of Malacca, which lies in the Golden Chersonese, a region so admired by ancient geographers, and as they are also lords of the Eastern Islands of Maluku and Banda, and they only name themselves Kings of Portugal, and European and Northern African Algarve, lords of Guine, and of the conquest, navigation, and commerce of Ethiopia, Arabia, Persia, and India;</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="40">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">como se estoutros Reynos &#38; senhorios nomeados, nam se gouernassem per suas leyes, &#38; ordenações, &#38; lhe nam pagassem tributos &#38; rendas, &#38; elles lhe name tiuessem o pescoço debaixo do escabello de seus pes.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">they name themselves such as if the other aforementioned kingdoms and lordships were not governed by Portuguese laws and ordinations, as if they did not pay taxes and send revenue to Portugal, and as if the Portuguese kings did not have the kingdoms’ necks under their little wooden bench where the Portuguese rest their feet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="41">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Mas como de cade huma destas partes em seu lugar mais copiosamente fazemos relação, ao presente ([d]eixadas ellas) pera se milhor entender o fundamento desta nossa Asia, conuem que saibamos como no titulo da Real coroa destes Reynos, se comprendem tres cousas distintas huma da outra: posto que entre si sejam tam correlatiuas, que huma nam pode ser sem adjutorio da outra, comunicandose pera sua conseruação.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As we will copiously account for each of these parts when time comes, we leave them aside for now, but to understand better the foundations of this Asia of ours, it is convenient that we know how the title of the Royal crown of these kingdoms [of Portugal and Algarve] there are three different things, one very distinct from the other, even though they are related to one another and one cannot exist without the aid of the other, as their preservations are linked.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="42">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">A primeira he conquista, a qual trata de milicia, a segunda nauegação, a que responde a geographia, &#38; a terceira comerçio que conuem a mercadaria:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The first one is the conquest, which relates to matters of militia, the second is navigation, which relates to geography and the third is commerce, which encompasses the goods.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="43">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">das quais partes querendo nos escreuer soccessiuamente como ellas se foram adquerindo &#38; ajuntando a coroa deste Reyno, em lugar &#38; tempo, por nam confundir os meritos de cade huma das matereas, com adjutorio diuino que pera isso imploramos, per este modo trataremos dellas.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">We wish to write about each of these parts, in their proper place and time, to account for how they were acquired in succession and added to the crown of this kingdom; we must not, however, mistake the merits of each of subject, so we beg for divine aid and we will divide the subject this way:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="44">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Quanto a parte da conquista que he propria da milicia, esta porque foy em todalas partes da terra, fazemos della quatro partes de escriptura: (posto que em seys em a nossa geographia diuidamos todo o vniuerso.)</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As for the part that concerns the subject of militia, since this happened in all parts of the Earth, we will thus divide it in four parts in this book (even though we divide the world in six parts in our Geography).</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>