<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Anthropomorphic description of the Americas</title>
				<author>Miguel Cabello Valboa></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Leonardo Velloso-Lyons</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Leonardo Velloso-Lyons</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Descripción del antropomórfica del continente americano</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Anthropomorphic description of the Americas</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Anthropomorphic description of the Americas" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Descripción del antropomórfica del continente americano</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Anthropomorphic description of the Americas</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>	
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Resta ahora que con la más claridad y brevedad que nos fuere posible, en tanto que la parte de el mundo que dijimos se acaba de henchir de gentes y darnos materia que tratar, digamos de la forma y postura en que el soberano criador la formó, a lo menos en la que nuestra nación la halló cuando pasó a ella.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Given that the part of the world already mentioned<note anchored="true"><p>Cabello Valboa uses this turn of phrase to refer to the Americas, as the <hi rend="italic">Miscelánea Antartica</hi>’s previous chapters, and the one from which this translation comes, were dedicated to laying out his thesis about the origin of the indigenous peoples of the Americas, i.e. that they descend from peoples from Asia, who migrated to the Americas.</p></note> is now full of people and provides us with our subject<note anchored="true"><p> I.e. the subject of this work. The use of the first person possessive here simply refers to the Cabello’s book, the <hi rend="italic">Miscelánea Antartica</hi>, more precisely the work’s main subject: the origin of the indigenous peoples of the Americas.</p></note>, it is now time to describe as clearly and briefly as possible the shape and form that God Almighty chose to give this continent—at least, the shape that our nation<note anchored="true"><p>By “our nation,” he probably means early modern Spain, which included the kingdoms of Castile, Leon, Aragon, Navarre, and Portugal (at the time that he finished writing the <hi rend="italic">MA</hi>), among others.</p></note> encountered when we first came here.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Y no halló artificio para expresar esto mejor que imaginarla un corpulento y robusto gigante acostado en el mundo sobre sus pechos, cuya disforme y mal peinada cabeza está en cincuenta y cinco grados de altura al Polo Antártico.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> mejor que imaginarla un corpulento y robusto gigante acostado en el mundo sobre sus pechos, cuya disforme y mal peinada cabeza está en cincuenta y cinco grados de altura al Polo Antártico.
							And He found no better artifice with which to express this continent than imagining it as a pudgy and robust giant, lying on his front upon the world, his disformed head with its poorly combed hair beginning at around fifty-five degrees latitude from the Antarctic Pole.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Y de esta cabeza, degollado el cuello por los cincuenta y dos y medio que es lo que llamamos estrecho de Magallanes, cuya longitud corre leste oeste.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And his head is severed from the neck at around fifty-two-and-a-half degrees latitude, where the Strait of Magellan runs longitudinally from East to West.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="2">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De este celebro, destroncado de su lugar, nace el grande y osudo espinazo, que con mal parejos ñudos va haciendo y formando la gran cordillera que el sagrado texto, según Montano, llama Sephar, y los nuestros los Andes.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">From his brain, severed from its rightful place, springs his great and bony spine with its uneven nodules making and shaping the great chain of mountains which the Sacred Text (according to Montano) calls Sephar<note anchored="true"><p>Here, Cabello Valboa references one of Iberia’s most prominent antiquarians and Bible scholars, Benito Arias Montano, one of the many scholars who attempted to find evidence that the Americas were known to Hebrews and Christians before the Spanish kingdoms discovered it in 1492.</p></note>, and which our people call the Andes.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">El brazo izquierdo de este monstruo, que le cae a la parte de el levante, lo tiene</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> cae a la parte de el levante, lo tiene
							The monster’s left arm is extended: it rests pointing towards the East, and within his</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">estendido, y en sus músculos y coyunturas escondidas infinitas naciones bárbaras.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">muscles and crevasses infinite barbarous nations hide.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Y son sus venas grandes y espaciosos ríos que desaguan en el gran mar Occéano.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And his veins are enormous and broad rivers that run into the great sea ocean.<note anchored="true"><p>“El mar Oceano,” as early modern Spanish and Portuguese speakers would have called it, means the Atlantic Ocean.</p></note></rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Todas las ijadas de este inmenso cuerpo que caen al lado izquierdo, está humidísimas y montosas, lavadas en el agua de el mar y río de la Plata, Paraguay y otros no menores lagos y desaguaderos que por aquella banda se hacen.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The entire flanks on the left side of this immense body are mountainous and extremely humid, washed by the ocean’s water and by the River Plate, the Paraguay River, and other equally large lakes and river mouths that run through that region.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sus gruesas costillas son las cordilleras que de el ñudoso espinazo de su cordillera nacen, entre las cuales se hacen hondos y húmedos valles, que con canales profundas llevan inumerable suma de agua a el Mar de el Norte.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His thick ribs are the mountain range that spring from his spine, full of mountainous nodes between which valleys, deep and humid, emerge, bringing an infinite amount of water through their deep canals to the Northern Sea.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Deja tender su pierna izquierda hacia el septentrión, y de su rodilla hace el cabo de Sant Agustín, que de aquesta tierra es la parte más cercana a la de Áphrica. </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His left leg hangs, pointing north, and his knee forms the Cape of St. Augustine, which is the part of these lands which is closest to Africa.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Recoge su espinilla y de su corva le sale el caudaloso río Marañón, no sin causa llamado Mar Dulce.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His lifted shin forms a curve from which springs the abundant Marañón River, which is rightly called “Freshwater Sea”.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Viene finalmente a rematar su pie en las asperezas de Caracas y sus vecinas sierras, quedándole en aquel vacío de la dobladura de su desmesurada pierna aquellos llanos de la Venezuela por donde se camina con el mismo tiento y gobierno que por la mar, a causa de su mucha grandeza.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His foot rests in the harsh lands of Caracas and its neighboring mountains. In that empty region where his oversized leg bends is where Venezuela’s prairies are located; there, walking proceeds at the same speed and accuracy as sailing the sea because the distances are so immense.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
				<p n="3">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Volviendo a tomar el hombro derecho deste corpulento gigante que le cae a la parte de el poniente, lo hallamos nevado y húmedo, interrumpido de muchas ensenadas y bahías que el mar hace en él; mas en comenzando a estender su brazo, el cual tiene menos apartado de sí que el izquierdo, se van mejorando sus cielos y suelos y abarca con sus molledos muchas naciones bárbaras y belicosas. </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Now, returning to this pudgy giant’s right shoulder, which falls onto the western side of his body, we find it covered in snow and water and interrupted by many inlets and bays created by the ocean. But as he begins to extend his arm, which he keeps closer to his body than the left one, the skies and earth start to look better, and he embraces many barbarous and bellicose nations with his biceps.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Comienzan luego sus estendidas ijadas, con una sequedad tan intensa que pocas y raras veces le alcanza un rocío y menuda stilcidia de el cielo, y lávalas el Mar de el sur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This is where his extensive flanks begin, where the land is so dry that few and rare are the times when we see a morning dew and the sky is frequently barren<note anchored="true"><p>I.e., it rarely rains in these regions.</p></note>; the South Sea washes these flanks.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Estiéndese con tan fogosa sequedad la distancia que dejamos señalada en el capítulo 15 de esta Segunda Parte, y la infinita multitud de gente que en esta parte habita pereciera de hambre, si el soberano proveedor no ordenara que de entre las costillas de el lado derecho de este monstruo, que son cordilleras desmembradas de el lomo, no desaguaran, haciendo grandes y fértiles valles, muy caudalosos ríos, que a sus tiempos conocidos traen y acarrean a estas tierras llanas y fogosas el agua que llueve en lo alto de la sierra. </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This burning and barren area extends over a great distance, as mentioned in Chapter 15 of this second part<note anchored="true"><p>The <hi rend="italic">MA</hi> has a lot of instances of self-reference, something not uncommon for early modern books of this magnitude and size. Chapter 15 is dedicated to explaining how the indigenous peoples—from whom all indigenous peoples of the Americas descended—arrived in the Americas. In this same chapter, Cabello Valboa also introduces a few comments about Andean geography, and how it differed from that of his own time.</p></note>, and the infinite multitudes of peoples living in these parts would perish from hunger if the Almighty Provider<note anchored="true"><p> I.e. God. Cabello Valboa was a Catholic priest, which probably explains why he finds many words to describe the Christian God without directly naming Him. This is one of such instances.</p></note> had not commanded that, between the ribs on this monster’s right side (which are the mountain ranges that originate in his loins), water should be brought by powerful rivers, generating great and fertile valleys; these rivers have been bringing and carrying the water that rains at the top of the mountains to these barren and burning lands since the beginning of time.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Y aquestos riegos hacen tan fértiles y abundantes estas tierras que no tienen ni le queda a lo demás de el mundo de que le pueden tener imbidia. </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And these flows make these lands so fertile and abundant that there is no other place in the rest of these world that these lands can envy.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">La pierna de esta monstruosa figura no va tan apartada como la oriental que antes dijimos, sino, corriendo de norte a sur, sigue el rumbo con que el brazo se comenzó a apartar de el hombro y se va estendiendo hasta tener por su espinilla las grandes cordilleras de Caramanta y Encerma, de donde torciendo, por no quebrarse en ninguno de los dos mares, se mete por entre ambos, tomando el nombre de Capira, en la tierra firme de Castilla de el Oro, dejando sus muslos, corvas y pantorrillas y más partes de su pierna, pobladas de grandísima suma de naciones diferentes en lenguas, trajes y adoraciones, aunque muy ricas de oro.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This monstrous figure’s leg is also not as far from his body as the previously discussed eastern one; it runs from North to South, following the path where his shoulder ends and his arm begins, extending until it reaches his shin—the great mountain ranges of Caramanta and Encerma—and there it twists so that it will not break into either of the seas; squeezing between the two, it takes on the name “Capira” and turns into the solid ground of Castilla del Oro. His muscles, curves, and calves, and other parts of his leg, are populated with a very great number of nations—nations which differ in language, clothing, and forms of worship, although all are rich in gold.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Lo alto de sus lomos se ciñen no con cualquiera cinta, sino con la tórrida, por donde siempre el sol camina.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The highest part of his loins is girded, not with any regular belt, but with the torrid zone<note anchored="true"><p>I.e. the Equator. He means the region between the tropics of Cancer and Capricorn. Early moderns often referred to it as “the torrid zone.”</p></note> where the Sun always treads its path.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Su osudo espinazo de la nuca, desencasado por aquel estrecho, va corriendo de el Polo Antártico hacia el Ártico, haciendo grandes y encumbradas sierras de nieve y volcanes </lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His bony spine, severed from his head by the aforementioned strait, runs all the way from the Antarctic Pole to the Arctic, forming great, towering, snow-capped </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">de fuego dando, con todo eso, lugar a que infinitas naciones vivan sana y opulentamente entre aquellas asperezas.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">mountains and fiery volcanos, providing a rich and healthy life for the infinite nations that live in those harsh lands.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Córrele la una y otra costa, como dicho queda, siguiendo el mismo rumbo de sur a norte, y la costa meridional dista de su altura de la cordillera por las partes más lejanas casi quinientas leguas, y por la que menos, más de ciento, y la costa y ribera del mar por la banda de el occidente, por la parte que más lejana la tiene, serán sesenta leguas, y treinta por donde más se le acerca, donde se hacen aquellos llanos y secos arenales de que ya habemos tratado, semejantes a los de Libia, aunque no tan olvidados de el rocío de el cielo, puesto que jamás en ellos llueve, como queda dicho.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As already stated, both coasts run the same course from South to North, and the southern coast is five hundred leagues away from the tall mountain range that runs in parallel; whereas where they are closest, coast and mountain range are only one hundred leagues apart<note anchored="true"><p>For this and the following comment on distances, it is hard to make sense of Cabello Valboa’s original language. There seems to be an opposition between two coasts, which would have the reader believe that he is writing about the western (Pacific) and the eastern (Atlantic) coasts of South America. However, as the whole passage concerns the Andes (the mountain range that he references), the “southern” coast could refer to the southern portion of the western (Pacific) coast—modern day Chile—and the “western” coast could refer to the northern portion of the western (Pacific) coast—modern day Peru and Ecuador. Modern editors of the work have tended to leave this confusing passage uncommented.</p></note>. As for the sea shore on the western side, the part that is furthest away from the mountain range is sixty leagues, and thirty where they are the closest, where those plain and dry deserts, which we discussed, are formed, similar to those in Libya except not so forsaken by the sky’s dew, although it never rains, as already stated.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mas ansí como en el Egipto fertilizan las tierras la crecientes que por el Nilo bajan de la Ethiopía, en estos llanos arenales, ansí mismo, fertilizan las tierras de sus valles las crecientes de los ríos que bajan de los Andes o cordilleras serranas.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Just as in Egypt, where rivers which originate in Ethiopia flow into the Nile and fertilize the lands through which they run, so these deserts are also fertilized by the rivers that descend from the Andes or the other mountain ranges. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
