<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>A Monstrous Courtship</title>
				<author>Hakim Irānshāh ebn-e Abi-l-Khayr</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Sam Lasman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Sam Lasman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>Likely completed between 1092 and 1108 CE, the Bahmannāma (“Book of Bahman”) is the work of a poet so obscure that even his name is not certain. Though there is a general consensus around the form Irānshāh ebn-e Abi-l-Khayr, the first element is spelled “Irānshān” or even “Inshān” in some manuscripts. Dedications in the text to the Seljuq sultans Nāser ad-Din Mahmud ebn-e Malekshāh and Ghiyās ad-Din Mohammad ebn-e Malekshāh position him within the Seljuq Empire around the turn of the 12th century CE.</p>
				<p>Irānshāh is credited with another epic work, the Kushnāma (“Book of Kush”). Both of the poems offer revisionist takes on the New Persian epic tradition established by the monumental Shāhnāma (“Book of Kings,” 1010 CE) of Abolqāsem Ferdowsi. This Book drew upon Persian legend, Zoroastrian religious tradition, and Arabic historiography to craft an immense saga of Iran’s pre-Islamic past, from the first king Gayomart down to the Muslim conquests of the 7th century CE. Subsequent epic poets adopted the Shāhnāma’s meter and diction, often situating their narratives in gaps within the earlier poem’s millennia-long scope—a practice literalized by later scribes, who often incorporated segments of these poems seamlessly into Shāhnāma manuscripts.</p> 
				<p>In the Bahmannāma, Irānshāh centers not the usual epic heroes but rather a villain, the tyrannical King Bahman. Known for his bloody vengeance against the family of the Sistāni champion Rostam, Bahman is an overbearing, homicidal tyrant. Frequently defeated in battle, he is ultimately devoured by a serpentine monster, an azhdahā, making him the only epic character who fails to overcome such a beast.</p> 
				<p>Before this shocking finale, however, the poem features another encounter with an azhdahā. In this excerpt, the hero Borzin-Āzar (“Exalted Flame,” usually just called Borzin), son of Farāmarz (“Beyond-the-Border”), and grandson of Rostam, takes a break from his struggle against Bahman. Together with his companions, Marzbān (“Margrave”) and Tokhāra (“The Tokharian”), he sets out on a hunting expedition. Along the way, they encounter a lion-hunting youth who directs them to a large nomadic encampment with abundant livestock. The lord of the herds is Burāsp, who in the course of a lavish welcome feast reveals that the lion-hunting youth is his daughter. This warrior maiden will only marry the man who can overcome her father’s champion wrestler, a Black African man (zangi), and then defeat her in a joust. Borzin accomplishes these feats, but before the wedding, Burāsp reveals the reason behind this warlike courtship. Every year, he is forced to deliver his daughter up to a sexually rapacious cloud; if he fails, his livestock will be slaughtered. Horrified, Borzin witnesses this ritual. He then pursues the cloud back to its mountain lair, where it reveals itself as a monstrous beast. Borzin kills it, and the excerpt ends with a celebratory feast at the court of Burāsp’s brother, the king of Pārs.</p>
				<p>Violence and eroticism entwine throughout this passage. One key word is azhdahā, a chimeric reptilian beast with anthropomorphic qualities, translated here as “dragon.” This first appears in this edition’s line 111, as a metaphor for the warrior princess; then, in 204, it describes Borzin as he overcomes her. These figurative usages are juxtaposed against the literal monster which terrorizes the young woman and her kingdom, itself killed by one final azhdahā—Borzin’s sword.</p>
				<p>Irānshāh’s poetry invests in depictions of alterity that are both denigrated and desired. The African wrestler is a key figure in this project. Denied dialogue or even a name, his portrayal is a stark example of the anti-Blackness prevalent in Persian epic literature. He exists only to be overcome, even if the text here tacitly endorses Borzin’s chivalrous smackdown over Tokhāra’s outspoken bigotry. Yet verbal echoes link all of these figures—Borzin, the princess, the wrestler, and the monster. All are enmeshed in economies of violence that complicate simplistic narratives of culture heroes triumphing over the forces of chaos.</p>
				<p>Neither of Irānshāh’s epics have been translated into English or other European languages, and scholarly discussion of them remains scant.</p>
				<p>The text transcribed here is not medieval; rather, it is a lithograph produced in Mumbai in 1907. This is one of at least two lithographed poems—the other being a Farāmarznāma, narrating the exploits of Borzin’s father—produced under the direction of Rostam Pur-e Bahrām Sorush-e Tāfti. Sorush-e Tāfti was an Indian Parsi who traveled throughout India and Iran in search of antique manuscripts relating to the Sistāni heroes. According to Rahim ‘Afifi, editor of the only scholarly edition of the Bahmannāmeh, the lithograph is primarily based on an otherwise unidentified manuscript from 1667. At least four other manuscripts are known, the earliest dated to 1397-98 CE.</p>
				<p>Hanaway, W. L. “Bahman-Nāma.” Encyclopædia Iranica, vol. 2, no. 5, 2011, pp. 499-500. Brief scholarly outline of the epic.</p>
				<p>Kuehn, Sara. The Dragon in Medieval East Christian and Islamic Art. Brill, 2011. Thorough discussion of the pre-modern Islamicate dragon, from an art-historical perspective.</p>
				<p>van Zutphen, Marjolijn. Farāmarz, the Sistāni Hero: Texts and Traditions of the Farāmarznāme and the Persian Epic Cycle. Brill, 2014. Extensive survey of the Persian epic tradition after the Shāhnāma.</p>
				<p>Sorush-e Tāfti, Rostam Pur-e Bahrām, ed. Bahmannāmeh. Matba’i-Fayzrasān, 1325 [1907]. Lithograph copy of the source.</p>
				<p>Irānshāh ebn-e Abi-l-Khayr. Bahmannāmeh. Edited by Rahim ‘Afifi. Enteshārāt-e ‘Elmi va Farhangi, 1380 [2001-2002]. Published edition of the text.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Trancription based on the lithograph compiled by Rostam Pur Bahrām Sorush Tafti. Bambaʼī: Matbaʻ-i Faiz Rasān, 1325 [1908].</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">قطعه&#x200c;ای از بهمن&#x200c;نامه&#x200c;ی ایرانشاه بن ابی الخیر</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">A Monstrous Courtship</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"A Monstrous Courtship" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>I have followed the lithograph wherever possible, only amending or supplying lines from ‘Afifi’s edition when the lithograph’s version is clearly garbled, or important passages are missing. These lines are marked with an asterisk [*] and underlined. No attempt has been made to preserve the original’s rhyme scheme (masnavi: AA, BB, CC, …xx) or meter (motaqāreb: ˘- - / ˘ - - / ˘ - - / ˘ - ). I have generally opted for a more naturalistic style over literal renditions. Certain pronouns have been replaced with proper names to aid clarity. Culturally specific terms (gholām, azhdahā, div, zangi, etc.) have been rendered into rough English equivalents (“youth,” “dragon,” “demon, “African,” etc.), though I acknowledge this approach sacrifices important nuances for readability.</p>
        			<p>Thank you to Alexandra Hoffmann,  Franklin Lewis, and Mary Thaler for numerous helpful suggestions and amendations.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title in original language, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title in English, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1-">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">قطعه&#x200c;ای از بهمن&#x200c;نامه&#x200c;ی ایرانشاه بن ابی الخیر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Excerpt from the <hi rend="italic">Bahmannāmeh</hi> of Irānshāh ebn-e Abi-l-Khayr</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برفتند ازینسان سه روز و سه شب&#65372;شکم گرسنه ناچریده به لب </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They went on like this, three days and three nights, bellies hungry, lips famished.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تن از ناچریدن چو شاخ نوان&#65372;شده زیرشان بارگی ناتوان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Their famished bodies became like quaking branches, their steeds weak beneath them. </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3" type="stanza">
				<l n="2+">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">داستان برزین آزر با غلام و شیر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">The Tale of Borzin-Āzar, the Youth, and the Lion</hi></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">روز چهارم گه نیمروز&#65372;غلامی همی رفت بس دلفروز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fourth day, at noontime, a youth went by, very pleasing to the heart,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نشسته بر اسب عقیلی نژاد&#65372;به دیدار کوه و به رفتار باد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Seated on a horse of exalted pedigree, looking like a mountain, moving like wind,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">رخی همچو خورشید فرمانروا&#65372;تنی همچو برقی میان هوا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Face like the sovereign sun, body like lightning amid the air,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی پیرهن پرنیان در برش&#65372;کلاهی ز مشک سیه بر سرش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A silken shirt over the chest, a musk-black hat over the head—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">گشاده گلی چو گل نارون&#65372;ز خون تیره گشته برو پیرهن</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">An opened flower, like an elm flower, shirt stained dark with blood.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">گرفته یکی شیر جنگی به بند&#65372;فکنده مر او را به گردون کمند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With a warlike lion taken in snares, a lasso thrown around its throat.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به یاران چنین گفت برزین گو&#65372;که با این شگفتست بسیار نو</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The hero Borzin said this to his companions: “This is a wonder, unprecedented…</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببینید کاین کودک شیر خوار&#65372;چگونه گرفتست آن شیر خوار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">See how this lion-eating child captured that wretched lion.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگه رسیدند نزد غلام&#65372;بپرسید برزین و کردش سلام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right away they drew near to the youth. Borzin asked and gave his greeting,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت از آن پس که ای شیر زوش&#65372;به گفتار من پهن بگشای گوش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Said then, “Mighty lion! Open your ears wide to my speech.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدان کاندرین مرز بیگانه ایم&#65372;اگر چند هر یک ز یک خانه ایم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Know that we’re strangers in these borderlands, though each of us is from the same house.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سه روز و سه شب گشت تا نان و آب&#65372;نخورديم و از ما رمیده ست خواب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It’s been three days and three nights since we’ve had food or drink, and sleep has fled from us.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">اگر میزبانی کنی در خورست&#65372;که آزادمردی هم از گوهر ست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It would be fitting if you hosted us, since nobility also comes from quality.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">پریچهره پاسخ چنین داد باز&#65372;که گر کار آسان نگیری دراز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fairy-faced youth gave this answer back: “If you don’t want to make an easy task tough,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بیایید کز گوشت این شیر جنگ&#65372;شما را کبابی دهم بی درنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Come, and from the flesh of this battling lion, I’ll make you kebabs right away.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">مرا خوردن اینست بیگاه و گاه&#65372;ندانم جز از بیشه و شیر راه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This is my food, both night and day; I know no way but woods and lions.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شکم چون تهی شد بر آید به جوش&#65372;به هر چیز کردن توانی خموش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the belly becomes empty, it begins to churn; then, it might be silenced by anything.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدین خوردنی گر ندارید خوی&#65372;شما را ازین بهتر است آرزوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But if you don’t have the stomach for such food, there’s better hope for you yet:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به صحرا بدان بیشه اندر شوید&#65372;چو لختی از آن سر فروتر شوید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From these woods, enter the wasteland. When you’ve gone a little further that way,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در و دشت و کوه و بیابان همه&#65372;نه بینید جایی تهی از رمه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In all the vale and plain and mountain and desert, you won’t see a spot empty of herds</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">از اسبان تازی هیونان بار&#65372;ز گاوان گردون هزاران هزار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Of Arabian horses, baggage camels, thousands upon thousands of Tauruses,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هم از مادیانها  که بر شب یله&#65372;هم از گوسفندان فراوان گله</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Also of mares that are loosed at night, also of sheep in abundant flocks.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکایک میان رمه بگذرید&#65372;یکی دشت پیش اندرون بسپرید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One after the other, pass among the herds, until you arrive in a further plain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بران دشت یابید خیمه هزار&#65372;زده بر کنار یکی جویبار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On that plain, you’ll find a thousand tents pitched beside a stream,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همه دیبه&#x200c;یی سرخ زرد و بنفش&#65372;زده بر در خیمه ها بر درفش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All with crimson, yellow, and violet brocade set as flags by the tent doors.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کجا خیمه&#x200c;یی سرخ اندر میان&#65372; سرش ماه زر دامنش پرنیان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Where there’s a crimson tent in the midst, a golden moon on its crest, its skirts of silk,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در آن خیمه آرام و خواب منست&#65372;خداوند آن خانه باب منست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In that tent is my rest and relaxation; the lord of that house is my father.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز من پیش او آشنایی دهید&#65372;به جان از خورش روشنایی دهید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Give him my regards, brighten your souls with food.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بباشید یکچند مهمان ما&#65372;فروزان شود کاخ و ایوان ما</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’ll be our guests for a while. Our palace and vaulted hall<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Throughout this tale, the poet uses the architectural vocabulary of a settled court to describe the nomadic domain of Burāsb.</p></note>will become radiant.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بخندید برزین و گفت ای دلیر&#65372;به یزدان که هرگز نخوردیم شیر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin laughed, and said, “Brave one! By God, we’ve never eaten lion!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وز آنجا سوی بیشه بشتافتند&#65372;جهانی پر از چارپا یافتند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And from there they dashed towards the wood. They found the earth covered in livestock,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی کودک اندر میان گله&#65372;گله بر در و دشت گروه یله</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A child in the midst of the flocks, flocks on the vales and plains, wandering in groups—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">زده بر سر چوب  تکیه چنان&#65372;کجا باشد آیین و رسم شبان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Pitched on top a pole, a sort of refuge, as is the custom and tradition of herdsmen there.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت پرمایه برزین تویی&#65372;ز خون فرامرز پر کین تو یی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The herdboy said, “You’re the wise Borzin! You’re of the vengeful Farāmarz’s blood!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برو کآمد اکنون گه کام تو&#65372;به خورشید تابان رسد نام تو</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Go on, for now the time of your desires has come; your fame has reached the blazing sun.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به کاری که داری به پیش اندرون&#65372;ترا بخت باشد بران رهنمون</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For the task that you have up ahead, fortune will be yours, by this prediction!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد همی گفت کاین فالگوی&#65372;ز برزین چه آگاهی آمد به روی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The commander kept saying, “How did this fortune-teller come to know of Borzin?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">از آن چارپا سر به سر در گذشت&#65372; به بالا بر آمد از آن پهن دشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He passed by all that livestock, and came up from that wide plain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نگه کرد دشتی پر از خیمه دید&#65372;همه سرخ و زرد و بنفش و سفید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He looked, saw a plain full of tents, all crimson and yellow and violet and white,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز دیبای رومی یکایک زده&#65372; نگارش سراسر به زر آزده</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Each one fashioned of Byzantine<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Rumi, “Roman,” a generic term for the West; in Irānshāh’s day, it referred particularly to the Byzantine Empire.</p></note> brocade, sewn all over with golden figures;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نهادند زی خیمه ای سرخ روی&#65372;زبان از شگفتی پر از گفتگوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They turned towards a nearby crimson tent, the wonder of gossiping tongues,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز دیبای رومی یکی بارگاه&#65372;نشسته یکی پیر در بارگاه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A court of Byzantine brocade, an old man seated in the court,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">غلامان زرین کمر صف زده&#65372;کلاه و کمرها به زر  آزده</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Golden-belted youths set in ranks, hats and belts stitched with gold.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برو آفرین کرد برزین و گفت&#65372;که با جان تو آفرین باد جفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin praised him, and said, “May praise be mated to your soul!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="47">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکایک بپرسیدشان مرزبان&#65372;سخن کرد گویا به شیرین زبان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Marzbān asked them one by one, spoke his speech with a sweet tongue:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="48">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو مهمانت آید سخن خوبگوی&#65372;ترش کم کن از بینوایی تو روی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“When your guest comes, speaking eloquent speech, don’t knit your brows over your poverty.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="49">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نکو گفت دستور با شاه فش&#65372;چه نیکوست از میزبان خوی خوش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The councilor spoke fairly to the kingly one: “How sweet is a host’s good disposition!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="50">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">مر آن پیر را بود بوراسب نام&#65372;از آن چارپا روز و شب شادکام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That old man’s name was Burāsb; his livestock made him blissful day and night.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="51">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز برزین بپرسید کای نامدار&#65372;تو چون اوفتادی بدین ره گذار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He asked Borzin, “Fame-bearer, why did you set out on this journey?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="52">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کی و کجا رفت خواهی بگوی&#65372;ز ما آرزو هر چه خواهی بجوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When and where do you wish to go? Speak! Seek from us whatever wish you desire.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="53">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو پهلوان گفت کای نیک خوی&#65372;مرا نیست جز دیدنت آرزوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The champion said to him, “Fair-natured man, I have no wish but to see you.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="54">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی رفت خواهیم جایی دگر&#65372;بدین کشور افتاد ما را گذر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">We still seek to go elsewhere—our passage has led through this country.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="55">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدین بارگه میهمان آمدیم&#65372;خریدار رویت به جان آمدیم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">We’ve come as guests to this court; we’ve come to purchase your honor with our souls.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="56">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بفرمود بوراسب اندر زمان&#65372;به خوالیگرش تا بیاورد نان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb commanded his cook to bring food right away:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="57">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز بریان و ماهی و مرغ و بره&#65372;ز هرگونه ای خوردنیها سره</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Fried meats and fish and poultry and lamb, every sort of pleasing food.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="58">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بخوردند و زان تازه تر شد روان&#65372;در آورد نیرو به تن پهلوان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They ate, and it refreshed their spirits; it brought back strength to the champion’s body.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="59">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بر آراستندش یکی خوابگاه&#65372;روانش بر آسود از رنج راه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A resting place was decked out for him; his spirit settled down from the sufferings of the road.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="60">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دگر روز بوراسب خوانی نهاد&#65372;که هرگز کس آن را ندارد به یاد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The next day, Burāsb set out a banquet, unlike any that anyone could remember.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="61">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز هر خیمه ای نامداری بخواند&#65372;بدان ساخته خوانشان بر نشاند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He summoned a famous lord from every tent; with such preparations, set out a banquet for them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="62">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بخوردند از آن خوان بپرداختند&#65372;یکی بزمگاه همی ساختند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They ate, partook in that banquet with gusto; they were fashioning a feasting place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="63">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">زمین بستد از باده ی ناب نور&#65372;هوا پر شد از بوی مشک و بخور</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The earth was drenched in pure-bright wine, the air filled with the scents of musk and incense,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="64">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فلک دود بست از بخار کباب&#65372;به جرعه زمین مست گشت از شراب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The heavens smoke-choked with kebab vapors. The earth grew drunk with gouts of wine.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="65">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز بوی گل و نرگس و یاسمین&#65372;زمین شد به سان بهشت برین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From the scent of rose, daffodils, and jasmine, the earth became like lofty paradise.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="66">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همه ساز آن بارگه سیم ناب&#65372;همه دل بر آواز چنگ و رباب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All that court’s gear was pure silver, all hearts set on the songs of harp and rebab.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="67">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو از باده ی زرد همچون بهی&#65372;سر سرکشان شد ز دانش تهی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When yellow wine, just like beauty, emptied the haughty lords’ heads of wisdom,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="68">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هوا پرده بر داشت از روی شرم&#65372;بلندی گرفت آن سخنهای نرم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The breeze lifted a veil from the face of shame. Those soft words took flight.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="69">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سرافراز برزین به بوراسب گفت&#65372;که اکنون سخنها نباید نهفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The proud Borzin said to Burāsb, “Now there’s no need to conceal speech.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="70">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی تا بدیدم بدانم ترا&#65372;به نام و نژادت چه خوانم ترا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I must know who you are, your name and your lineage; what should I call you?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="71">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سزد گر بگویی که این جای چیست&#65372;همین چارپای دلارای کیست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It’s fitting if you say what this place is, and whose is this lovely livestock?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="72">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">که را باشد این کشور و جویبار&#65372;چنین لشکری همچو باغ بهار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Whose might this land and stream be, this warband like a spring garden?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="73">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنین پاسخش داد کای سرفراز&#65372;کنم آشکارا به پیش تو راز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The other answered him, “Proud man, I will reveal this secret to you:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="74">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنان دان که این مرز جای منست&#65372;همه دشت پر چارپای منست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Know that this borderland is my place. All the plain is full of my livestock.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="75">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">مر این جوی را زنده رودست نام&#65372;من از دیدنش سال و مه شاد کام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The name of this stream is the Zandeh-rud.<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Literally, “Life-Giving River,” this flows from the Zagros Mountains through the city of Esfahān, though in recent years its flow has become drastically reduced through drought and mismanagement.</p></note> Seeing it, I am blissful every month and year.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="76">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">گیا چون بر آید ز روی زمین&#65372;بیایم من از پارس ایدر چنین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When greenery comes up from the earth’s face, I come from Pārs to this very place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="77">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدین مرغزار آورم چارپای&#65372;چو فربه شود باز گردم به جای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To this prairie, I bring the livestock; when they become fat, I go back.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="78">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شه پارس باشد یکی نامور&#65372;برادر مرا و ز پشت پدر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The king of Pārs is a famous man, my brother, descended from my father.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="79">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سرافراز یزدان نام ویست&#65372;جهان سر به سر زیر کام ویست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Proud Yazdād is his name. From end to end, the world is subject to his desire.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="80">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به گاه شمردن دو ره سی هزار&#65372;فزون آیدش لشکر نامدار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the mustering place, more than sixty thousand of his famed warband come to him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="81">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">میان من و اوست این چارپای&#65372;همه گدایی مرا زین به پای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">These livestock are shared between me and him; all of my dominion is based on this.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="82">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">غم آنست کز بهمن اسفندیار&#65372;به تنگی گذارد همی روزگار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The tragedy is that thanks to Bahman son of Esfandiyār, he passes his days in anxiety.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="83">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی خواهد از کشورش شاه باژ&#65372;ندانم که گردون چه دارد به راز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Bahman keeps seeking royal tribute from his land; I don’t know what secrets the heavens keep.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="84">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شب و روز در پیش یزدان به پای&#65372;همی گوید ای دادر پاک رای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Night and day before God on his feet, Yazdād keeps saying, ‘Oh Just One of pure judgment,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="85">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بده برزین ازان بدکنش&#65372;مگردان ز کینه مر او را منش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Deliver Borzin from that evildoer; do not turn his spirit back from vengeance.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="86">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تبه کن تو بر دست این جان اوی&#65372;منه بر جهان پیش فرمان اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">By Borzin’s hands, destroy Bahman’s life; do not deliver the world into his control.’<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Oppressed by Bahman, Yazdād prays for the king’s rival, Borzin.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="87">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کنون آگهی آمد این چند روز&#65372;ز برزین کجا بخت او گشت کوز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Now news has come these past few days of Borzin, how his luck went crooked.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="88">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تبه گشت بر دست آن دیوزاد&#65372;که نام نژادش به گیتی مباد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He was destroyed by that demon-spawn’s hand (may that lineage’s name vanish from the earth!)</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="89">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دل ما بلرزید از آن درد و غم&#65372;وزین آگهی جان ما شد دژم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Our hearts trembled from that pain and sorrow, and from that news our souls grew depressed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="90">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دگر باره شنیدم از رهنمای&#65372;که آن پهلوان زنده مانده به جای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Later, we heard from a courier that the champion remained alive, somewhere.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="91">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کز بهمن آمد سپاه&#65372;سپاهی که بر باد بر بست راه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin told him, "An army came from Bahman, an army that blocked the passage of the wind.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="92">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز برزین آزر شکسته شدند&#65372;بسی کشته و زار و خسته شدند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They were shattered by Borzin-Āzar; many were killed or hurt or wounded.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="93">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو بشنید بوراسب از آن شاد شد&#65372;وزان غم روان وی آزاد شد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Burāsb heard this, he became glad, and his spirit became freed from that sorrow.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="94">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو آفرین کرد و گفت ای جوان&#65372;مرا از غم آزاد کردی روان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He praised him, and said, “Young man, you’ve freed my spirit from sorrow.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="95">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز غمها روان تو آزاد باد&#65372;دل نیک بختان تو شاد باد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">May your spirit be free from sorrow. May your fair-fortuned heart be glad!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="96">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کاین خیمه ها سر به سر&#65372;که را باشد ای مهتر نامور</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “These tents altogether—whose are they, famous nobleman?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="97">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ندانیم کس را بدین پایگاه&#65372;ندارد چنین دستگه هیچ شاه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">We don’t know anyone in this encampment; no king has such a court!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="98">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بخندید بوراسب گفت ای پسر&#65372;که را باشد این ساز و آیین و کر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb laughed and said, “Son, whose is this gear, these customs and might?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="99">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">مر این سر کشان را که بینی همی&#65372;به دل مهرشان بر گزینی همی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They belong to these proud lords you keep seeing; you’d always pick out love in their hearts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="100">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نه خویشند ما را و نه لشکری&#65372;همه با دل خویش درد آوری</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They aren’t mine, they aren’t my warband—all bring the pain of their own hearts!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="101">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هزارند فرزند شاهان چین&#65372;ز روم و ز چین و ز ایران زمین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They’re a thousand kings’ sons from China; from Byzantium, China, and the land of Iran.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="102">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"> همه یک به یک در پی کام دل&#65372;وزین کام دل باز مانده خجل</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Each of them searching for his heart’s desire, and by this heart’s desire still confounded.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="103">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدین راه گر دیده ای کودکی&#65372;گرفته ز شیران جنگی یکی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the road here, if you saw a child who’d captured one of those warlike lions,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="104">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنان دان که او مر مرا دختر است&#65372;که هنگام کینه یکی لشکر است</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Know this: she is my daughter, who in times of violence is worth a whole warband.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="105">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سر سال شاهان روی زمین&#65372;بیایند خواهندش از من چنین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At the year’s start, the kings of the earth will come seeking her from me in this way.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="106">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هرآنکس که خواهد ز من دخترم&#65372;چنان دان که از رای او نگذرم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Anyone who wishes for my daughter from me, know this: I will not overrule her judgment.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="107">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دو پیمان نهم پیش او اندرون&#65372;که این  هر دو نزدیک باشد به خون</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I will set forth for him two pledges regarding this, and both of these are linked to blood:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="108">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی آنک با او نبرد آورد&#65372;سر و خود او زیر گرد آورد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One is that he must fight against her, and bring her head and helm down into the dirt.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="109">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دو دیگر که دارم سیاهی درشت&#65372;زند بر زمینش به هنگام پشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The second is that I have a gigantic Black man; throw him on his back upon the earth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="110">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هر آنکس که آرد به جا این دو کار&#65372;دلش شادمان گردد از روزگار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Whoever accomplishes these two things, then and there, fate will turn his heart to gladness.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="111">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">درین بود کان اژدهای دلیر&#65372;ز پشته در آمد گرفته دو شیر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Just then that brave dragon came down from the hills, having captured two lions.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="112">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دویدند پیش پرستندگان&#65372;ازو بستدند آن ددان بندگان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Servants came running forward; they took those bound beasts from her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="113">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بیامد پریچهره پیش پدر&#65372;زمین را ببوسید و آمد به در</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fairy-faced girl came before her father, kissed the earth and came through the door.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="114">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دلیران یکایک فرو ماندند&#65372;برو نام یزدان همی خواندند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All the brave lords humbled themselves; they kept praising her in God’s name,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="115">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز بالا و دیدار و رفتار اوی&#65372;وزان زورمندی و کردار اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Her stature, her appearance, and her conduct, her mightiness and deeds.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="116">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت برزین که ما روز و شب&#65372;ز مردی و نیرو گشاییم لب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin kept saying, “Day and night, we will open our lips for her manliness and strength.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="117">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شکارش به کردار بانو گشسب&#65372;چنین شیر دل کی نشیند بر اسب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Her quarry is like Bānu Goshasp’s, that lion-heart, when she rides upon her horse,<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Bānu Goshasp is a famed warrior woman, daughter of Rostam (and therefore Borzin’s aunt). In addition to appearing in the <hi rend="italic">Bahmannāma</hi> and other poems, she stars as the hero of her own brief epic, the <hi rend="italic">Bānugoshāspnāma.</hi></p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="118">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">که بندد به یک ره دو شیر ژیان&#65372;ز گردان ایران و تورانیان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Who binds in one course two savage lions from among the heroes of Iran and Turān.”<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Iran’s traditional rivals, representing the peoples of the Central Asian steppes; from at least the Shāhnāma onward, associated with the Turks and with <hi rend="italic">Chin</hi> (China).</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="119">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنین گفت بوراسب کای شیر مرد&#65372;که آمد کنون روزگار نبرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb said this: “Lion man! The time of battle is coming now.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="120">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سر سال نو را سه روز است گفت&#65372;شود هر کس امروز جویای جفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He said, “The new year starts in three days; that day, everyone starts searching for a mate.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="121">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت برزین که ما این سه روز&#65372;بباشم نزد تو ای دلفروز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “For these three days, I will stay close to you, heart-pleaser.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="122">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببینیم تا آن گل نارون&#65372;هنر چون نماید درین انجمن</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">We will see how that elm blossom demonstrates her skill at this gathering.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="123">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببودند با رامش و نای ورود&#65372;زبانها پر از پهلوانی سرود</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They engaged in pleasure and flute-playing, their tongues brimming with heroic songs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="124">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سر سال خوان نو آیین نهاد&#65372;در رامش و شادکامی گشاد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For New Year, a new-fashioned banquet was set; the gate of pleasure and delight was opened.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="125">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو در دست شادی در غم ببست&#65372;گشادند بر باده ی لعل دست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the hand of joy shut the gate of grief, they opened their hands to ruby wine.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="126">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دگر روز بوراسب بنهاد تخت&#65372;به دشت اندرون زیر شاخ درخت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The next day, Burāsb set out a throne upon the plain, beneath a tree branch.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="127">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نهاده برو دستهای مهی&#65372;بگسترده دیبای شاهنشهی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Noble thrones were set out before him, imperial brocade was spread out.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="128">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نشستند بر تخت پرمایگان&#65372;چو برزین و دیگر گرانمایگان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wise sat upon those thrones, like Borzin, and others of great worth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="129">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">منا دیگری در میان بانگ کرد&#65372;که ای نامداران و مردان مرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Another cried out amid the crowd, “Famed ones! Men among men!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="130">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدانید که امروز سال نوست&#65372;گه رامش و جشن کیخسروست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Know that today is the New Year; it’s the time of pleasure, the festival of Kay Khosrow.<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Kay Khosrow was a just and much-loved king, who reigned before Bahman’s great-grandfather Lohrasp came to the throne.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="131">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به میدان شوید و بجویید کام&#65372;میان دلیران بر آرید نام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Enter the arena and seek your desire! Exalt your name among the brave.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="132">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سر نامداران بر آمد ز خواب&#65372;گرفته یکایک به میدان شتاب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The heads of the famed lords lifted from sleep; each one came rushing to the arena.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="133">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو شد توده میدان از آن سروران&#65372;سپاهی بیامد چو کوه گران</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the arena became a mass of those chieftains, the army came like a massive mountain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l n="133a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">داستان زنگی و جنگ کردن او</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">The Tale of the African and His Battling</hi></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="5" type="stanza">
				<l n="134">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به روغن بمالیده سر تا به پای&#65372;چو دیوی رمیده ز نام خدای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Rubbed with oil from head to foot, like a demon fleeing from the name of God,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="135">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برهنه سراپای و اندام اوی&#65372;به کشتی به گیتی شده نام اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His body naked from head to foot, famed throughout the world for wrestling—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="136">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو گفتی همی کینه ورزد همی&#65372;زمین زیر پایش بلرزد همی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’d say he always trained himself in violence; the earth trembled beneath his feet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="137">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دو چشمش به کردار دو طاس خون&#65372;بر و یال همچون که بیستون</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His eyes were like two bowls of blood, his head and shoulders like Mount Bisotun.<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>A peak in the Zagros Mountains, famed for the ancient reliefs carved on it.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="138">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به میدان در آمد دمان و دنان&#65372;دل هرکس از هیبت او رمان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He entered the arena, hissing and strutting, everyone’s heart fleeing for fear of him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="139">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگاه بوراسب آواز داد&#65372;که ای نامداران فرخ نژاد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Just then Burāsb shouted out, “Famous lords of glorious lineage!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="140">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به میدان شوید از پی کام و نام&#65372;که این نام نیکو رساند به کام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Enter the arena seeking desire and fame, for sweet fame comes through desire.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="141">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هر آنکو به کشتی کند دست پیش&#65372;بلای سیه باز دارد ز خویش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Whoever sets his hands to wrestling, and keeps from himself a black calamity—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="142">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همان دخترم را به گاه نبرد&#65372;ز پشت ستور اندر آرد به گرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then at the time of battle, casts that daughter of mine from her mount’s back into the dirt.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="143">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگه بدو بخشمش ناگزیر&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*نه کابین بخواهم نه پیمان شیر</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right then, I’ll grant her to him with no evasion; I’ll ask for no dowry, no lion’s pledge.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="144">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز قهرش بجنبید دلها ز جای&#65372;خرد پیش مهر اندر آورد پای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His command made hearts spring from their place; wisdom lagged behind love.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="145">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی جامه بر کند و از جای جست&#65372;بیامد به هم باز زد هر دو دست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One stripped off his robe and leaped from his place; he came to grips, struck with both hands.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="146">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سیه چون چنان دید شد پر ز کین&#65372;میان دو ابرو در آورد چین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the Black man saw this, he became full of violence. A furrow appeared between his brows.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="147">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بغرید ماننده&#x200c;ی پیل مست&#65372;میان دو پایش برون کرد دست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He roared like an elephant in musth. He stuck his arm out between the other’s legs,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="148">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در آورد و زد بر زمینش درشت&#65372;سر مهره&#x200c;ی وی برون شد ز پشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Threw him and slammed him on the ground; the ends of his vertebrae stuck out from his back.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="149">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی دیگر آمد بر شرزه زنگ&#65372;به کشتی ندادش زمانی درنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Another one came against the fierce African; he didn’t give him a moment’s respite in wrestling.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="150">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بیامد یکی نامدار از میان&#65372;ز تخم بزرگان ایرانیان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A famed lord came out from the crowd, from the seed of the Iranian nobility.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="151">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی مشت زد بر میانش سیاه&#65372;به زخمی مر آن نامور شد تباه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Black man smashed a fist against his middle; the famed lord was destroyed by that injury.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="152">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنین تا از آن انجمن مرد بیست&#65372;بیفگند هر کس همی خون گریست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So it was until he’d overthrown twenty men from the assembly; each of them kept crying blood.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="153">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز خشمش تخاره بر آمد ز جای&#65372;چو آتش به کشتی وی کرد رای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Enraged, Tokhāra sprang from his place. Firelike, he set his mind on wrestling.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="154">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت بوراسب کای شیر مرد&#65372;به گرد بلا تا توانی مگرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb said to him, “Lion-man! Don’t orbit around calamity, if you can help it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="155">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو مهمان مایی بدین روزگار&#65372;ترا با نبرد دلیران چه کار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">These days, you’re our guest; what business do you have, battling with brave men?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="156">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نباید که زنگی ترا بشکند&#65372;تن نامدارت به خاک افکند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It wouldn’t be right for the African to break you, to hurl your famed body in the dust.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="157">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تخاره بدو گفت شاید رواست&#65372;هوا بر دل هر کسی پادشاست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Tokhāra said to him, “Maybe that’s right, but passion rules over everyone’s heart.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="158">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو نزدیک زنگی رسید آن دلیر&#65372;بغرید ماننده&#x200c;ی نره شیر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When that brave man came near the African, he roared like a male lion;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="159">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">زبان را به دشنام بگشاد و گفت&#65372;که ای زشت بد گوهر دیو جفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He loosened his tongue with curses, and said, “Ugly man of bad substance, demons’ mate,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="160">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدین نامداران گشادی دو دست&#65372;هنر بین هم اکنون تو از پیل مست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’ve unleashed your hands on these famed lords; see now the skills of an elephant in musth!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="161">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بر آشفت زنگی ز دشنام اوی&#65372;وزان ناسزا گفتن و کام اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The African grew enraged from his curses, and from his slanderous speech and will;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="162">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به پاسخ نیفزودنی گرم و سرد&#65372;برو همچو دیو دژ آهنگ کرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In answer, without adding to the drama, he acted on him like a demon from the Iron Fortress.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="163">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"> ز کینه بدو اندر آمد درشت&#65372;بر افروخت یال و بر آورد پشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He fell upon him violently, enraged; his great frame bristled, his back stretched.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="164">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بزد بر تهیگاه بشکست خرد&#65372;تخاره بیفتاد و گویی بمرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He struck him in the flank, shattered him utterly. Tokhāra fell—you’d say he died!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="165">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><hi rend="underline">*ز خاکش تنی چند بر داشتند</hi>&#65372;به پرده درون خوار بگذاشتند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Some lifted the body up from the dust. They brought him, pitiful, into a tent.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="166">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بخندید برزین ز کردار اوی&#65372;وزان تیزی خام گفتار اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin laughed at his deeds, and at his sharp, raw speech.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="167">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دژم شد ز خندیدنش مرزبان&#65372;بدو گفت کای شیردل پهلوان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Marzbān grew enraged at his laugher, and said to him, “Lion-hearted champion,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="168">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سزد گر تو نیز آزمایش کنی&#65372;به نیرو هنرها نمایش کنی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It would be fitting for you to endeavor also, to forcefully display your skills.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="169">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بود کاین سیه را در آری ز پای&#65372;برین ماه پیکر شوی کدخدای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Should you throw this Black man off his feet, you’ll become lord of that moon-bodied girl.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="170">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">که تو مایه از تخمه&#x200c;ی نیرمی&#65372;نبیره جهان پهلوان رستمی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For the seed of Nariman’s your origin; you’re grandson of the World-Champion,<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>Jahān-pahlavān, an epithet regularly granted to Rostam as the preeminent epic hero.</p></note> Rostam.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="171">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ترا هست کشتی سرشت و نهاد&#65372;کنون داد باید بدین رزم داد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Wrestling’s part of your nature and disposition! Now you must bring a just end to this combat.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="6" type="stanza">
				<l n="171a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کشتی گرفتن برزین با غلام زنگی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">Borzin’s Wrestling with the African Youth</hi></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="7" type="stanza">
				<l n="172">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بر آشفت برزین کزینسان شنید&#65372;همانگاه جامه ز تن بر کشید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin grew enraged when he heard this. Right away he stripped the robe from his body.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="173">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چه خواهی همی کرد بوراسب گفت&#65372;که با جان پاکت خرد باد جفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“What are you trying to do?” Burāsb asked. “May wisdom be mated with your pure soul!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="174">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی با سیه گفت کشتی کنم&#65372;برو بر یکی پیشدستی کنم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Just once,” Borzin said, “I’ll wrestle with the Black man. Just once, I’ll outmaneuver him.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="175">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کای مایه&#x200c;ی دین و داد&#65372;نگر تا ازین گفته نیاری تو یاد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb said, “Essence of faith and justice, mind that you don’t have cause to rue this speech.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="176">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو بیگانه یی نه بدین آمدی&#65372;نه از بهر پیکار و کین آمدی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’re a stranger here. Don’t come into this! Don’t come for fighting and vengeance!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="177">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به ویژه که دیدی هنرهای او&#65372;ندارد کسی بر زمین پای او</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Especially since you’ve seen his skills—no one on earth has a stance like his!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="178">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ازان نامداران سه تن را بکشت&#65372;تن بیست را بر زمین نهد درشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He’s killed three of those famed lords, slammed the bodies of twenty violently against the earth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="179">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چرا کرد باید به دریا شناه&#65372;به ویژه کسی کاو نداند شناه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Why should anyone dare to swim the sea, especially someone who doesn’t know how to swim?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="180">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">خرد بر گمار ارتوانی به دل&#65372;که پیشین بود کاروان گاه گل</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Appoint wisdom to your heart, if you can; for ahead lies the caravansarai of clay.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="181">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کای  مایه‌‌&#x200c;ی مردمی&#65372;دلم شد ز پیکار زنگی غمی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “Essence of manliness, my heart has grown sad from the African’s fighting.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="182">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی آزمایش کنم با سیاه&#65372;مگر بخت بگشایدم بسته راه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I’ll try myself once against the Black man. If fortune’s mine, I might force the blocked path.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="183">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد چو جامه ز سر بر کشید&#65372;ز پرده درون دختر او را بدید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the commander pulled his robe over his head, the girl saw him from inside her tent:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="184">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدان ناز پرورده اندام اوی&#65372;چنان کش خرامیدن و گام اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His well-nourished body, that fair striding and step of his.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="185">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز مهرش به جان تاب آتش رسید&#65372;دلش پرده ی شرم را بر درید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Love for him brought a blazing fire to her heart. Her heart tore the shroud of shame.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="186">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دلش گشت چون دیده&#x200c;ی دردمند&#65372;تن زورمندش تباه و نژند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Her heart became like a stricken eye; her mighty body became ruined and undone.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="187">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت با خویشتن کدخدای&#65372;سیه را یکی سست شد دست و پای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">She kept saying to herself, “Lord, the Black man’s hands and feet have become a bit weak.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="188">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">مگر گردد او شوی و سالار من&#65372;به گیتی نشاید جز او یار من</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Perhaps the other will be my husband and master. In this world, only he will be my companion.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="189">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در اندیشه بود آن پریچهره ماه&#65372;که برزین در آمد به تنگ سیاه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That fairy-faced moon was in a state of anxiety when Borzin went up against the Black man. </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="190">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بغرید و چون رعد زد هر دو دست&#65372;به گردش بگردید چون پیل مست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He roared, and like thunder struck with his two hands; he circled him like an elephant in musth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="191">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بترسید زنگی ازان شاخ و یال&#65372;ز سستی شدش پای همچون دوال</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The African feared his limbs and frame. Weakness made his legs like leather strips.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="192">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بزد بر دهانش یکی پشت دست&#65372;دو دندان پیشین او را شکست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin backhanded him across the mouth; he broke his two front teeth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="193">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برون کرد دستش میان دو پای&#65372;هنر کرد و بر کند او را ز جای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He stuck his hand between the other’s legs, showed his skill, and uprooted him from his place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="194">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به گردن بر آورد و زد بر زمین&#65372;نشست از برش همچو شیر عرین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He hoisted him by the neck and hurled him onto the earth, sat on his chest like a lion in its lair.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="195">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برو هر کسی آفرین خواند نو&#65372;وزان انجمن بانگ بر خواست غو</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Upon him, everyone called out praises anew. Shouting whoops rose up from that assembly.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="196">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو بر داشتند آن سیه را ز خاک&#65372;برو پشت و پهلو همه   چاک چاک</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When they lifted that Black man up from the dust, his back and sides were completely shattered.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="197">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت بوراسب کای نامدار&#65372;نبردیست مانده ز پیش تو کار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb said to Borzin, “Famous man, there remains ahead of you one battle to wage.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="198">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو هر دو به دستت بر آید همی&#65372;بهانه به گیتی سر آید همی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When you have both of them in hand, the conditions will be fulfilled in this world.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="199">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">پراکنده گشت آن بزرگ انجمن&#65372;وزانجا به سوی خیمه شد پیلتن</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That great assembly scattered. The mammoth hero went from there towards his tent.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="200">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به شادی و رامش گشادند دست&#65372;همه شب شدند از می لعل مست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They opened their hands to joy and pleasure. All night, they became drunk on ruby wine.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="8" type="stanza">
				<l n="200a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کشتی گرفتن دختر با برزین و انداختن برزین او را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">The Girl’s Struggle with Borzin and Borzin’s Overthrowing Her</hi></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="9" type="stanza">
				<l n="201">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو طاوس زنگی ز گه بر فروخت&#65372;بر و یال زاغ سیه را بسوخت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the African peacock blazed up from its place, it burned the crows’ wings and feathers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="202">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به میدان شد آن دختر خوبچهر&#65372;سری پر ز کینه دلی پر ز مهر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That fair-faced girl entered the arena, head full of violence and heart full of love.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="203">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به اسب عقیلی به سان عقاب&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*تن از باد و پای از درنگ و شتاب</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On a pedigreed horse, like an eagle, body made of wind, feet quick to halt and rush.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="204">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد برابر شدش در زمان&#65372;به سان یکی اژدهای دمان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right then, the commander came against her like a hissing dragon.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="205">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بر آویختند آن سواران جنگ&#65372;نظاره بران دشت شیر و پلنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Those battle-knights came to grips, lions and leopards their audience on that plain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="206">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو شد حمله اندر میانشان بسی&#65372;نشد چیره بر هم نبردش کسی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the first attack was done between them, neither one was victorious in battle over the other.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="207">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد بر آشفت بر روزگار&#65372;چو باد اندر آمد ز فرجام کار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The commander became enraged against fate; he charged in like the wind to conclude the affair.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="208">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی نیزه زد بر میانش ز کین&#65372;ز زینش بر آورد و زد بر زمین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He struck a lance violently against her belly, threw her from her saddle, and she struck the earth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="209">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز برزین دل سرکشان شد دژم&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*شد امید هر کس ازان کام کم</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin frustrated the hearts of the haughty; everyone else’s hopes for that desire grew scant.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="210">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو از خاک بر خاست آن دل گسل&#65372;ز پرده برون شد ز میدان خجل</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When that heart-tearer rose up from the dust, she went in shame from the arena to her tent.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="211">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به برزین چنین گفت بوراسب راد&#65372;که از رزم کشتی بدادی تو داد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The noble Burāsb said this to Borzin: “You put a just end to this battle and wrestling.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="212">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کنون دختر من ترا است و بس&#65372;نخواهد رسیدن بدو دست کس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Now my daughter is yours, that’s it. No one else’s hand will touch her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="213">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ولیکن زمان ده مرا چند روز&#65372;که گردد به کام تو گیتی فروز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But give me some time, a few days, that the world may become bright by your will.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="214">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو فربه شود چارپای و گله&#65372;کنم در در و دشت یکسر یله</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the livestock and flocks become fat, I will herd them all together in the vale and plain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="215">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">از ایدر کشم آنگهی سوی پارس&#65372;بدین از تو دارم فراوان سپاس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From here, I will drive then towards Pārs. For this, I’ll be abundantly thankful to you.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="216">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت برزین که فرمانبرم&#65372;ز رای و ز گفتار تو نگذرم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “I’m at your service. I won’t transgress your judgment or words.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="217">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببودند یکچند شادان به دشت&#65372;به رامش شب و روزشان در گذشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They were happy for some time in the plain. Their days and nights passed in pleasure.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="218">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بسازید سوری بدان مرز و بوم&#65372;که هرگز نبود اندر آیین روم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb set a feast in that border region, such as there never was in Byzantine custom.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="219">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی روز بوراسب هنگام بار&#65372;دژم بود دلی خسته روزگار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One day at court, Burāsb seemed depressed, his heart wounded by fate.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="220">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد به دیدار او شد به گاه&#65372;دژم دید هر چند کردش نگاه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The commander, went to the throne to see him; saw him depressed whenever he glanced at him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="221">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بر اندوه گواهی دهد روی زرد&#65372;چو زردی نماید همی رنگ مرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A sallow face gives evidence of sorrow, when a man’s color always appears sallow. </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="222">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بجوشد ز غم زهره&#x200c;ی آدمی&#65372;ازیرا بود زرد روی غمی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A person’s bile churns from sadness; from this comes a sallow face and sadness.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="223">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو شادی که افزون کند خون چو مل&#65372;ازیرا شود روی همرنگ گل</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Similarly, happiness increases the wine-like blood; this makes the face the color of roses.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="224">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد بدو گفت کای سرفراز&#65372;چه بودت که اندیشه کردی دراز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The commander said to him, “Proud man, what’s going on, that you lengthen your cares?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="225">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دلت را نگویی که کردست تنگ&#65372;که از من بپوشی همی بی درنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You won’t speak of what constricts your heart; you conceal it from me ceaselessly.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="226">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کای مایه&#x200c;ی روزگار&#65372;مپرس این که بر من درازست کار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Burāsb said to him, “Essence of fate, don’t ask me this, for my woes have become interminable.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="227">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی کار پیش آمدستم شگفت&#65372;که با هر کسی باز نتوانش گفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Something has happened to me, a wonder that cannot be repeated to anyone.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="228">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دو سالست تا این گیاخوار من&#65372;تباهی فزوده است در کار من</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For two years, thanks to these grazers of mine, my affairs have turned to measureless ruin.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="229">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو آید بهاران و اردیبهشت&#65372;همه دشت گردد چو خرم بهشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the springs come, and Ordibehesht,<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p> The second month of the Iranian calendar, corresponding to late April and early May.</p></note>all the plain appears like a blossoming paradise.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="230">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">جهانی به رامش گشایند دست&#65372;مرا با غم و درد باید نشست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All people open their hands to pleasure, while I must sit in grief and anguish.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="231">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بباید مرا دختر آراستن&#65372;به کردار سروی به پیراستن</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">My daughter must be adorned, ornamented like a cypress tree</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="232">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز پیرایه&#x200c;ای  بر تنش زیوری&#65372;به سر بر نهادن ز زر افسری</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With finery: gems on her body, and a golden tiara set on her head.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="233">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برو سوختن مشک چندین به دشت&#65372;که پیرامن وی نشاید گذشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Some musk is burned over her, upon the plain, so that no one might get near her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="234">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فرستاد باید به جای بلند&#65372;نشاندن بر آنجا یکی مستمند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">She must be sent to a high place and set in that spot for a while, miserable.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="235">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی پاره ابر اندر آید ز کوه&#65372;که از دیدنش دیو گردد ستوه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A scrap of cloud descends from the mountain—seeing it, a demon would be terrified—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="236">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">خروشان و آتش ز پیشش جهان&#65372;گهی تیره زد گاه روشن جهان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Roaring, with fire darting before it. Then darkness strikes the world’s bright places.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="237">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بگیردش و گرد اندر آید چو دود&#65372;شود دختر من سیاه و کبود</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It takes her and comes swirling like smoke; my daughter becomes black and ashen.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="237a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><hi rend="underline">*زمانی بباشد شود ناپدید</hi>&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*به گیتی کسی این شگفتی ندید</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[For a while, she remains invisible; no one in the world has seen such a wonder.]<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>This and subsequent bracketed lines do not appear in the lithograph.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="238">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز آن پس گه گردد ز دختر جدا&#65372;ره کوه گیرد هم اندر هوا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then, when it separates from the girl, it takes its way back to the mountain through the air.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="239">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بماند مر آن دخترم مستمند&#65372;دو هفته به خانه تباه و نژند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That daughter of mine remains miserable for two weeks at home, ruined and distraught.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="239a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">زیانش ندیدند از آن سرکشان&#65372;ز مهر خداییش بر وی نشان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[Her injury: after that, the proud princes did not see any sign of her maidenhead upon her.]”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="240">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت کای کار دیده هژبر&#65372;گر او را نبخشی  بر آن تیره ابر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “Experienced lion, what if you didn’t give her to that dark cloud?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="241">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بگو تا زیانی چه آرد ترا&#65372;چه پتیاره پیش آورد مر ترا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Speak of the injury that is yours—what does the monster bring upon you?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="242">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنین داد پاسخ که یکسال پیش&#65372;زحمیت ندادم بدو دخت خویش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He answered, “One year ago, in my pride I did not give it my daughter. </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="243">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز کوه بلند اندر آتش فروخت&#65372;همه چارپایم سراسر بسوخت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From within the high mountain, fire flared, and burned all my livestock completely.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="244">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">من از هول آن روز ترسیده&#x200c;ام&#65372;کزان روز پتیاره را دیده&#x200c;ام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I am afraid of the terror of that day, for that day I saw the monster.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="245">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببینی تو فردا چو آگه شوی&#65372;گر از خویشتن بر سر ره شوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’ll see tomorrow, for you’ll witness it, if you take yourself along that path.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="246">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد ز گفتار او شد دژم&#65372;فرو ماند و دیگر نزد هیچ دم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His words made the commander furious. He felt downcast, and didn’t breathe another breath.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="247">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همه شب همی بود اندیشناک&#65372;جهان را چو بزدود خورشید پاک</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">All night, he was beset continually by worry. When the pure sun scrubbed clean the world,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="248">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگه بپوشید خفتان جنگ&#65372;دلیران او بر کشیدند تنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right then he put on his battle-coat. His brave followers drew close around him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="249">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بیامد به دشت اندرون ایستاد&#65372;همی کرد بوراسب گفتار یاد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He went to the plain and stood within it, and kept remembering Burāsb’s words.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="250">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت با مرزبان و تخار&#65372;که این بس شگفت آمد از روزگار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He kept saying to Marzbān and Tokhār, “This is truly a wonder come from fate.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="251">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگاه دختر بیامد به دشت&#65372;چو سرو خرامان برو بر گذشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Right then the girl came to the plain. Like a striding cypress, she passed by him,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="252">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سر افکنده در پیش و گشته دژم&#65372;چو نازنده سروی که گردد به خم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Head bowed forward; she’d become depressed, like a proud cypress that’s become bent.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="253">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">پر از زیورش گردن و دست پای&#65372;پر از گوهرش حلقه مشک سای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Her neck and arms and legs covered in gems, her musk-spreading earrings covered in jewels,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="254">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فکنده بسی تاب در مشک ناب&#65372;ز چادر دمان بوی مشک و گلاب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Abundant curls drenched in pure musk, scents of musk and rosewater exhaling from her veil.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="255">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بسی خادمان سیه پیش و پس&#65372;پرستنده با وی ز هر گونه کس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Many Black servants before and behind her, all sorts of people attending upon her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="256">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بماند آن پریچهره بر پهن دشت&#65372;پرستنده یک بارگی باز گشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That fairy-faced girl remained in the broad plain. The attendants all at once drew back from her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="257">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی تیره ابری هم اندر زمان&#65372;به زیر آمد از کوه و از آسمان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In that very instant, a dark cloud came down from the mountain and from the heavens.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="258">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">جهان قیرگون شد از آن تیره ابر&#65372;خروشان جوشان و چو جنگی هژبر</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The world became pitch-black from that dark cloud, which roared and frothed like a warlike lion.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="259">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">گرفته جهان آتش و دود ازو&#65372;همی هر زمان آتش افزود ازو</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The world took on its fire and smoke. Always the flames kept spreading from it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="260">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">کشان دامنش بر زمین پر ز چین&#65372;چو دودی که خیزد ز روی زمین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Trailing its twisted robes along the ground, like smoke rising from the face of the earth,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="261">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">خروشان ز کوه اندر آمد به دشت&#65372;زمانی به پیرامن وی گذشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Roaring, it descended from the mountain to the plain. For a moment it passed around her.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="262">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><hi rend="underline">*به گرد اندر آمدش مانند دود</hi>&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*کزو سیمتن هیچ پیدا نبود</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[It swept all around her like smoke, so that nothing could be seen of her silver body.]</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="263">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فقان کرد و بیداد بسیار کرد&#65372;زمانی همی بود با رنج و درد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It bellowed, and committed great wrongs; for a time everything was suffering and pain</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="264">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دگر باره شد بر میان هوا&#65372;بپوشید خورشید فرمانروا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then again it lifted up into the midst of the air, and covered up the sovereign sun.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="265">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سپهبد همی تاخت زیر اندرش&#65372;تخاره بدو مرزبان همبرش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The commander galloped on, directly beneath it, Tokhāra with him, Marzbān right by him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="266">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببرید ازان دشت فرسنگ پنج&#65372;بران کوه رفتند با درد و رنج</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They cut across five parasangs of that plain; they went to that mountain of pain and suffering.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="267">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز کوه اندر آمد به شیب دره&#65372;همی راند برزین گو یکسره</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From the mountain, they came into a steep canyon. The hero Borzin kept driving directly on.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="268">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز پس چون نگه کرد کس را ندید&#65372;گران شد عنان و فرو آرمید</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then when he looked around, he didn’t see anyone. His reins grew heavy, and he grew still.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="269">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنین گفت برزین بدان هر دو کس&#65372;که از ره چرا باز ماندید پس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin called to the two of them, “Why do you stay back along the path?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="270">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تخاره بدو گفت ای نیک یار&#65372;گذشتن مجالست ازین کوهسار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Tokhāra said to him, “Fair companion, it’s possible to pass into this highland,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="271">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">نکرده ست بازی به جان هوشمند&#65372;نه کس بر تن خویش جوید گزند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But a wise man doesn’t gamble away his soul! No one seeks injuries upon his own body!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="272">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو بیهوده در کوه تازی&#65372;همی چه خواهی ازین اسب تازی همی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You, galloping foolishly into the mountain, what do you want from your Arabian horse?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="273">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">من این ابر تیره ندانم که چیست&#65372;در اندیشه زو در گمانم که کیست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I don’t know what this dark cloud is. It worries me! I have no idea who it is.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="274">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو فرمان کن و باز گرد و مپای&#65372;بدین باز گشتن بهش بر فزای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Give the order! Turn back, and don’t delay. By returning, show greater wisdom.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="275">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بدو گفت برزین که تو جای دار&#65372;که من رفت خواهم بدین کوهسار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin said to him, “You hold this ground, for I will go into this highland.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="276">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ببینم که این دیو پتیاره کیست&#65372;چو کار آمد از پیش من چاره چیست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I will see who this monstrous demon is. When a mission comes to me, what else can I do?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="277">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شما هر دو ایدر بدارید پای&#65372;که گر زنده مانم خود آیم به جای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Both of you, hold firm here, for if I remain alive, I myself will return to this place,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="278">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وگر مرگ پیش آیدم ناگاهان&#65372;مرا زندگانی سر آرد جهان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And if death comes suddenly upon me, this world will have brought my lifetime to an end.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="279">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">درین کوه فردا بجویید اسب&#65372;فرستید نزدیک بانو گشسب</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Tomorrow, search for my horse in this mountain; send it on to Bānu Goshasp.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="280">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بگفت این و آن هر دو بگریستند&#65372;دو روز اندر آن غم همی  زیستند</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He said this, and those two both cried; they lived for two days in such grief.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="10" type="stanza">
				<l n="280a">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">رفتن برزین آزر به جنگ  اژدها</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">Borzin-Āzar Goes to Battle the Dragon</hi></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="11" type="stanza">
				<l n="281">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو برزین فرو رفت از آن برز کوه&#65372;تکاور شد ز کوه خارا ستوه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Borzin went down from that mountaintop, that flint-pillared mountain made him bold.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="282">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی رفت تا شب در آن غارها&#65372;فکنده سپر دید خروارها</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He kept riding until night through those caverns; he saw heaps of shields scattered about.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="283">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سراسر دره دید سرخ و سیاه&#65372;همی کرد برزین بدان بر نگاه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He saw the vale completely red and black. Borzin kept gazing at it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="284">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت کاندر چنین جای تنگ&#65372;دو لشکر همانا که کرده ست جنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He kept saying, “In this narrow place, it seems two armies have done battle.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="285">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در آن ریگها چون نگه کرد ژرف&#65372;همانا چنان اژدها بود جرف</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When he looked deep into that rubble, it seemed to be that dragon’s castings.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="286">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به گاه بهاران تنش ریخته&#65372;ز هر سو به خاک اندر آمیخته</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the springtime, its body sloughed off, mixed with the dust in all directions.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="287">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بترسید برزین از آن هول جای&#65372;همی بود تنها و در پیش پای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Borzin grew scared of that terror-place. He was still alone, his foot set forward.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="288">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">درین بود کز کوه ژرف اژدها&#65372;بغرید کرد آتش از دم رها</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment from the mountain depths, the dragon roared and shot fire from its breath.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="289">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هوا تیره گون گشت از کام او&#65372;زمین رفت در زیر اندام او</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Its maw darkened the air. The earth vanished beneath its bulk,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="290">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دهانش به مانند غاری فراخ&#65372;چو الماس بر سر مر او را دو شاخ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Its mouth like a gaping cavern, two horns like diamonds on its head,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="291">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دو چشمش به کردار دو طاس خون&#65372;سرش همچنان چون که بیستون</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Its two eyes like two bowls of blood, its head exactly like Mount Bisotun.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="292">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ز سر تا به دم بود صد گز فزون&#65372;دل شیر ار دیدن او زبون</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From head to tail, it was more than a hundred yards. The lion’s heart would weaken, seeing it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="293">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چون برزین چنان دید یک نعره کرد&#65372;چنان چون دلیران به گاه نبرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Borzin saw it, he let out a cry, just as brave warriors do on the day of battle.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="294">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو آواز  برزینش آمد به گوش&#65372;به مغز اندرش تیزتر گشت هوش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Borzin’s voice reached its ears, its mind grew harsher within its brain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="295">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">در آمد روان از سر کوهسار&#65372;کمان را بمالید مرد سوار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It came rushing down from the highland heights. The cavalier grasped his bow.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="296">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بپیوست بر شصت تیر خدنگ&#65372;چو دید اژدها اندر آمد به تنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He hooked the poplar arrow above his thumb-ring, when he saw that dragon draw near.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="297">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو با چرخ سوفار شدست بار&#65372;بجست اژدها را دو دیده سوار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the nock was set firm on the arc, the cavalier sought the dragon’s two eyes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="298">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو بگشاد شصت آن یل نامدار&#65372;به چشمش زد آن تیر الماس دار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When that famous hero slipped his thumb-ring, that diamond-bearing arrow struck its eye.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="299">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو انداخت بر دیده آمدش راست&#65372;ز درد اژدها خویش را کرد راست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When he shot, it landed right in its eye; from pain, the dragon straightened itself out.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="300">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">خدنگ دگر باره پیوند کرد&#65372;چنان جانور را چنین بند کرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He nocked another poplar-shaft, in order to subdue that creature.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="301">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">زدش بر دگر دیده و کرد کور&#65372;همی زان روز خمش ز تن رفت زور</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He struck it in the other eye and made it blind. From the pain in its eyes, strength left its body.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="302">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی اژدها بر کشید از نیام&#65372;که تازی همی خواند او را حسام</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He drew another dragon from his sheathe, what the Arabs usually call a “scimitar”—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="302b">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بغرید ماننده پیل مست&#65372;به یک زخم از تن سرش کرد پست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[...]<note anchored="true" type="critical"><p>This line (“He roared like an elephant in musth; with one blow, he made its head droop from its body”) seems extraneous; it appears to narrate the same action as the subsequent line while breaking the syntactic connection to the “scimitar.”</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="303">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">خورش دادش از خون و خونخوار رفت&#65372;همانگه سرش را ز تن بر گرفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He fed it with blood and it became bloodthirsty. With one blow, he struck its head from its body.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
 				<l n="304">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فرود آمد و چشمه‌ی آب جست&#65372;به آب اندر آمد سر و تن بشست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He dismounted and sought a spring of water. He came into the water, washed his head and body,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="305">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وز آنجا بیامد به جای نماز&#65372;همی گفت کای پاک دانای راز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And from there came to a praying place. He kept saying, “Pure Knower of Secrets,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="306">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو دادی مر این بنده را دسترس&#65372;تو باشی به هر جای فریاد رس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To this slave you gave assistance. In every place, you rush to the cries of the distressed.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="307">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وز آنجا سر اژدها بر گرفت&#65372;به نزدیک یاران ره اندر گرفت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And from there he took up the dragon’s head, and took the path towards his companions.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="308">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بینداخت سر پیش آن سرکشان&#65372;که سر باشد از تن به هر جا نشان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He threw the head down before those haughty lords, for everywhere the head signifies the body.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="309">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تخاره چو آن دید و دندان اوی&#65372;بسی آفرین کرد بر جان اوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Tokhāra saw that, and its teeth, he heaped plenty of praise upon his soul.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="310">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت مردی همین است و بس&#65372;ندیدیم از اینسان دلیری ز کس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He kept saying, “This is manliness, that’s it! We’ve never seen bravery like this from anyone!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="311">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چو نزدیک بوراسب رفتند باز&#65372;بینداخت سر پیش آن سر فراز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When they went back to Burāsb, he threw the head down before that proud lord.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="312">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بترسید سخت آن یل از اژدها&#65372;<hi rend="underline">*بشد از دلش هوش گفتی رها</hi></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That hero feared the dragon terribly; you’d say consciousness fled from his heart.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="313">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بمالید بر خاک پیشش جبین&#65372;بسی خواند بر جان او آفرین</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He rubbed his forehead in the dust before him, and heaped plenty of praise upon his soul.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="314">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همی گفت از این سان هنر کس نکرد&#65372;که کردی تو امروز ای شیر مرد</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He kept saying, “No one has shown such skill as you’ve done today, lion-man!</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="315">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">همانگه از تخمه&#x200c;ی نیرمی&#65372;که با زور سام و دل رستمی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Surely you’re of Nariman’s seed, since you have Sām’s strength and Rostam’s heart.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="316">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به مژده سواری سوی شاه پارس&#65372;بیامد نزدیک نیکی شناس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A horseman came bearing the good news to the King of Pārs, to that one versed in goodness:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="317">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">که از دشمن ما بر آمد هلاک&#65372;به دست سواری هنرمند پاک</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Destruction has come upon our enemy, at the hands of a skillful, pure cavalier,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="318">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">که رویش ز خورشید تابانتر است&#65372;خردش از هنرها فراوانتر است</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Whose face is more radiant than the sun, whose wisdom is even more abundant than his skills.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="319">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">پس از مژده اینک بیاییم زود&#65372;بگوییم یکایک ترا هر چه بود</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Following this good news. We’ll come quickly; we’ll tell you of everything, as it happened.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="320">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سه روز اندر آن دشت کرد او درنگ&#65372;گله نزد خویش اندر آورد تنگ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Three days he tarried in that plain, brought the herds close in around him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="321">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چهارم روزگاه بر خاست نای&#65372;به اسب اندر آورد بوراسب پای</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the fourth day, flutes sounded. Burāsb mounted up on his horse.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="322">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سوی پارس رفتند یکسر به هم&#65372;ز دل دور کرده همه رنج و غم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Towards Pārs they went all together, casting suffering and grief far from their hearts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="323">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">برادر پذیره شدش با سپاه&#65372;سپاهی که گردش رسیدی به ماه</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His brother greeted him with his army, an army whose mustering had taken a month.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="324">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">به شهر اندر آورد و بردش به کاخ&#65372;به باغ دلارای و جای فراخ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He escorted them through the city to the palace, to a heart-pleasing garden and an open place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="325">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">شب آمد بگفت آن همه سر گذشت&#65372;ز برزین و کشتی زنگی و دشت</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Night came. Burāsb told all that had happened, Borzin and the African’s wrestling and the plain,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="326">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وز آن ابر کان اژدها گشته بود&#65372;که برزین یل کشت او را چو دود</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And that cloud that turned into that dragon, which the hero Borzin killed like mere vapor.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="327">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">از آن شادمان شد دل شاه پارس&#65372;همی داشت زیشان فراوان سپاس</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The King of Pārs’s heart grew glad from that; he gave abundant thanks to them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
 				<l n="328">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">سرافراز بوراسب و یزداد باز&#65372;یکی هفته کردند در شهر ساز</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The proud Burāsb and the falcon Yazdād made a week-long feast in that city.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="329">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فراوان بکشتند اسب و گله&#65372;بسی گاو و آن گوسفندان یله</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They killed many horses and herds, many cows and those sheep from the flocks.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="330">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">یکی سور کردند آن سرکشان&#65372;که هرگز ندارد کس آزانشان</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Those proud lords made a banquet, for never has anyone had wealth like them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>				
				<l n="331">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">هوا یکسر از مشک بد پر ز بوی&#65372;نشایست مردم گذشتن به کوی</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The air was completely full of the scent of musk; people couldn’t pass through the alleyways.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="332">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">جوانان و پیران همه شاد و مست&#65372;گرفته همه دسته&#x200c;ی گل به دست</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Young and old, all glad and drunk, all taking bouquets of flowers in hand.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="333">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">چنان بود بازار و کوی از نثار&#65372;که زر و درم گشت چون خاک خوار</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Such wealth was scattered in markets and alleys, that gold and dirhams became despised as dust.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="334">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تو گفتی که چرخ بلند از برش&#65372;ستاره فشاند همی بر سرش</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You’d say that high heaven rained stars from its breast down upon his head.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>