<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title><!--Title in English--></title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Introduction by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The Millstatt Plaint of Sin, written in middle of the twelfth century perhaps in the South West of Germany, is a substantial poem addressed to God in the voice of a sinner. The poem is conventionally counted as part of a small sub-genre of Early Middle High German religious poetry known as the ‘Sündenklage’, or ‘plaint of sin’. These poems – there is also the Vorau Plaint of Sin and the more simplistic Uppsala Plaint of Sin – all have at their heart a confession of sinfulness and a prayer to God for mercy, and are thought to have taken their inspiration from the more pragmatic text-type of the German confession (Beichte). These confessions, generalized first-person confessions in prose, are transmitted widely from the ninth century and had a variety of liturgical and devotional functions. The manuscript of the Millstatt Plaint of Sin is heavily damaged, but it is nonetheless possible to get a good sense of the poem and its themes. It is not simply a confession of sins, but rather offers a conceptualization of the world, as well as the place of man and his sins within it. By framing the confessional act with sections praising God and his creation and structuring sins around the inappropriate use of individual body parts, the Millstatt Plaint of Sin explains that God is in everything and that all created things are a way of seeing God; hence sinning is perceived as an almost illogical malfunctioning of creation. Although ostensibly quite straightforward, the poem tackles – in a rewarding and indeed quite challenging way – a number of contemporary issues that will be of interest to readers: the relationship between body and soul; bodily fragmentation; and the nature and construction of selfhood.</p>
				<p>The Millstatt Plaint of Sin is transmitted in full in Klagenfurt Landesarchiv Cod. GV 6/19, a major anthology of ‘Early Middle High German’ verse texts. It was made around 1200, or slightly later, in Bavaria or Austria, and contains the Old German Genesis, Exodus, and Physiologus, accompanied by illustrations, followed by five short religious poems, of which the Millstatt Plaint of Sin is the third. We do not know for whom it was made – perhaps for nobility or for a female religious community. The part of the manuscript containing our poem is heavily damaged and so the poem itself is often difficult to reconstruct. Some insight into the missing sections is however offered by two other manuscript witnesses that contain fragmented versions of the same poem: 1) Munich BSB Cgm 5249/60a, four parchment fragments of Honorius’ Elucidarium from the late twelfth century, with a German text written below in a smaller hand (although perhaps the same hand) that correlates – albeit with considerably deviation – to around 100 lines of the Millstatt Plaint of Sin; 2) Zurich Zentralbibliothek Cod. Rh. 77, a ninth- or tenth-century Latin manuscript with various twelfth-century additions, including a fragment of a German poem often known as the Rheinau Paul. This poem correlates fairly closely to parts of the end of the Millstatt Plaint of Sin, although it is by no means identical.</p>
				<p><!--Further Reading--></p>
				<p><!--Further Reading--></p>
				<p><!--Further Reading--></p>
				<p><!--Further Reading--></p>
				<p><!--Further Reading--></p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"<!--Title in English-->" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p><!--Add in "About this edition" here.--></p>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>Previous editors of the Millstatt Plaint of Sin have made attempts to reconstruct the damaged poem using a mix of the so-called Rheinau Paul and educated guesswork. I have largely avoided the latter, although not because I think earlier attempts were not plausible: both Roediger and Maurer make thoughtful, intelligent suggestions. Roediger often underestimates the size of the gaps, however, and Maurer’s edition, although largely more plausible, is marred by his insistence on a long-line strophic form, for which there is little evidence. I have only completed half-finished words when their full form is entirely obvious. I have, however, completed some lines using the Munich and (particularly) the Zurich manuscripts above – these instances are noted in the notes. I have avoided any linguistic normalization, though; my aim in ‘completing’ these lines is to give the reader a (plausible) sense of the content, not to recreate a damaged poem. In any case, the verses in the Munich and Zurich manuscripts do show considerable differentiation to those in the Klagenfurt manuscript, so my additions should not be thought of as anything other than possibilities.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">
							<note anchored="true"><p></p></note> 
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="6"><!--Lines are continuously numbered through the song so check that they are correct-->
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
