<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Legend of the Miracles of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Emily Ziffer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Emily Ziffer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The “Legend of the Miracles of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon” is a 15th-century text relating a series of ten miracles performed by the Vladimir Mother of God icon in the late 12th century. Widely regarded as one of the most sacred icons in Russian history, the Vladimir Mother of God, painted with tempera on wood in the 12th century, depicts the Virgin Mary embracing Christ the child cheek to cheek. Dressed in gold, Christ gazes up at his mother adoringly. This tender pose is emblematic of a genre of icons called an “Icon of Loving Tenderness,”— or umilenie in Russian — and is meant to remind the viewer of the love uniting Mary and Christ. </p>
				<p>The Vladimir Mother of God Icon was brought to Kiev from Byzantium in 1131-32 and remained there until 1155, when Prince Andrei Bogoliubsky decided to move the icon to his new capital city of Vladimir in the Rostov-Suzdal principality in northeastern Rus (approximately 120 miles northeast of Moscow). Prince Andrei honored the icon by decorating it with a silver riza — a metal covering meant to protect icons from damage— bejeweled with precious metals and stones. He then built the Dormition Cathedral in 1158 in the icon’s honor and placed it inside, where the icon served thereafter as the symbolic religious protector and benefactor of Vladimir. </p>
				<p>It is likely that Prince Andrei himself was involved in creating the initial cycle of legends in order to legitimize Vladimir as the new political and spiritual capital of Rus. This is especially plausible considering that Andrei is a witness to many of the miracles described in the “Legend,” one of which includes details about the birth of his own child. The “Legend” begins by comparing the Mother of God icon to the sun, stating that both have the ability to traverse and warm the entire universe, a message that suggests Prince Andrei’s ambitions to unite several principalities of northern Rus under his rule. This underlying political agenda is prevalent in the geographical scope of the “Legend,” which suggests Prince Andrei’s spreading glory since the miracles do not only occur in Prince Andrei’s capital city of Vladimir and its surrounding environs, but also in more distant cities such as Murom, Tver, and Pereiaslavl.</p>
				<p>In many 16th-century manuscripts, the miracles are preceded by the “Legend of the Victory over the Volga Bulgars” of 1164, the story of how Prince Andrei defeated the Volga Bulgars with the help of a miracle by the Mother of God icon, which Andrei carried throughout the campaign in the vanguard of the army. In contrast, the “Legend of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon” depicts the everyday realities of 12th-century Rus, using colloquial language and expressive dialogue. These are not miracles relating military victories, but instead empathetic vignettes of women suffering from complicated pregnancies, a teenage boy with a mysterious eye disease, and people grappling with blindness and heart disease. In each case, the intervention of the Mother of God icon cures the afflicted, bringing peace and stability to the people of Vladimir and beyond.</p>
				<p>The Vladimir Mother of God icon continued to serve as a symbol of Russian imperial and national destiny throughout Russia’s history. The Ermolin Chronicle of the 1470s attributes the Grand Prince Vasily I’s victory over the Mongol ruler Tamerlane in 1395 to the icon’s intervention. The Romanovs kept the icon in the Kremlin as a symbol of Russia’s link to the historical center of Christianity in Byzantium. Tsar Nicholas II and his family traveled to the Moscow Kremlin when the Germans invaded Russia in 1914, where they kissed the icon and asked it to protect Russia from harm. Legend has it that when German forces were approaching Moscow during World War II, Stalin ordered the icon to be put on a plane and flown around the capital city. And finally, during the 1993 Russian constitutional crisis, the icon was removed from its current home in the State Tretyakov gallery and brought to the Epiphany Cathedral at Elokohovo, where the icon was asked to prevent civil war. By reading the “Legends of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon,” we can understand the origins of this powerful national symbol, which has come to signify Russia’s complex relationship between political power and Orthodox Christianity.</p>
				<p>The first cycle of legends regarding the Vladimir Mother of God icon was composed between 1163 and the late 1180s. According to scholars, these dates are indicated in a note in a later version of the legends, written in a menology— an ecclesiastical calendar containing biographies of Saints— by the Miliutin brothers in the 17th century. The first historical work that linked disparate legends regarding the miracles performed by the Mother of God into one cohesive narrative is the Book of Royal Degrees compiled in the circle of the Metropolitan Makarii of Moscow in the 1550s and 1560s. However, many earlier sources mention the icon’s history and the miracles caused by the icon’s direct intervention. For example, the Laurentian Chronicle compiled in the late 14th century tells of how the Mother of God icon was delivered from Constantinople to Kiev, while the 15th-century Ermonlin Chronicle describes the Virgin’s intercession in the battle against Tamerlane in 1395. The edition of the text of the “Legend” used for this translation comes from a late 15th-century manuscript, #637 from the Egorov Collection at the Russian State Library in Moscow (Collection 98). Egor Egorovich Egorov (1862–1917) was a Moscow merchant born into a family of Old Believers (a group of Eastern Orthodox Christians who maintain the practices of the Russian Orthodox Church as they were before the reforms of 1652 – 1666) who collected medieval manuscripts and art. </p>
				<p>Alfeyev, Hilarion. 3: Orthodox Christianity Volume III : The Architecture, Icons, and Music of the Orthodox. Yonkers, St. Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2014.</p>
				<p>Guide to orthodox icons; see especially Chapter 8 (pp. 185–210), which is devoted to Russian icons.</p>
				<p>Bakatkina, Maria. “Hands off that Scared Image!” The Vladimir Icon and its Power. MA thesis. University of Virginia, 2017. https://libraetd.lib.virginia.edu/downloads/9306sz41b?filename=1_Bakatkina_Maria_2017_MA.pdf</p>
				<p>Comprehensive history of the Vladimir Icon and its significance in both medieva literature and visual art.</p>
				<p>Hurwitz, Ellen S. Prince Andrej Bogoljubskij: The Man and the Myth. Firenze, Licosa Editrice, 1980.</p>
				<p>Biography on Prince Andrei Bogoliubsky for additional context on his life and rule. </p>
				<p>Miller, David B. “Legends of the Icon of Our Lady of Vladimir: A Study of the Development of Muscovite National Consciousness.” Speculum, vol. 43, no. 4, 1968, pp. 657–670. JSTOR, www.jstor.org/stable/2855325. </p>
				<p>A study of the political significance of the Legends of the Icon of Our Lady of Vladimir.</p>
				<p>Tarasov, O. I︠U︡, and R. R Milner-Gulland. Icon and Devotion: Sacred Spaces In Imperial Russia. London: Reaktion Books, 2002.</p>
				<p>Extensive study of the significance of icons in Russian culture. </p>

			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>MS 637, Egorov Collection(98), Russian Library</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">"Ꙗко бо слн҃це створи бъ҃"</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Legend of the Miracles of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"The Legend of the Miracles of the Vladimir Mother of God Icon" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>This transcription retains the punctuation and graphic form of the original text, as well as superscript letters and abbreviations indicated by a titlo. Proper nouns have been left as they appear in the original and not been translated to their anglicized equivalent. For example, I have chosen to use the names “Priest Mikula” and “Priest Nikola” instead of anglicizing them to Nicholas. In several instances, brackets are used to indicate places where I have made small additions to the text for the sake of clarity. In such cases, an explanatory note has been added. </p>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ꙗко бо слн҃це створи бъ҃ . не на единоⷨ (// 389r) мѣстѣ постави. егда свѣтить ѡбиходѧ всю вселеню лчами ѡсвѣщаеть. тако же и сии ѡбразъ прес҃тыꙗ влчⷣ҇ца нашеꙗ бц҃а прнⷭ҇одв҃ы мр҃иꙗ. не на единоⷨ мѣстѣ чюдеса . и дары исцелениа истачаеть. но ѡ҆бьходѧщи всѧ страны и мира просвѣщаеть. и ѿ недгь различьныⷯ избавлѧе.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When God created the sun, he did not put it in one place. It shines during its rotations and illuminates the entire Universe with its rays. In the same way, this image of our Most Holy Lady the Mother of God Virgin Mary does not exude miracles and gifts of healing in one place, but, traveling across all countries of the world, illuminates and relieves various ailments. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Кн҃зю ⷤ҇ ⷷандрѣю хотѧщю кн҃жити на роⷭ  ⷪвьскᲂую землю. и нача бесѣдовати ѡ иконахъ. повѣдаша ем икон. вышѣгорода въ женьскоⷨ манастыри. пртⷭ҇ыꙗ влчⷣ҇ица нашеа бц҃а. ꙗко .г҃. жⷣы стпила с мѣста.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Prince Andrei wanted to reign in the land of Rostov, he began to ask about icons. They told him of the icon in Vyshegorod, in the nunnery of Our Most Holy Lady Mother of God, which had moved from its place by itself three times.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а҃ е внидоша въ црк҃вь. и видѣша ю средѣ цр҃кви ѡ҆собѣ стоꙗщю . и поставиша ю на иномъ мѣстѣ . в҃ е видиша ю ѡбратившюсѧ къ ѡлтареви лицемь . и ркоша ꙗко въ ѡлтари хощеть стоꙗти . поставиша ю за трѧпезою . г҃ е видѣша ю кромѣ трѧпезы ѡсобѣ стоꙗщю . и иныⷯ чюдесъ множество.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">First, when they went into the church, they saw it standing separately in the middle of the church, and they put it in a different place. The second time they saw the icon with her face turned towards the altar, and they said that she wanted to stand in the altar. They placed her behind the communion table. The third time they saw her standing apart from the communion table. And there were a great deal of other miracles. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">4. се слы (// 389v) шавъ, кн҃зь радъ  бы. и приде въ црк҃овь. и начать смотрити по иконамь. си же икона. ꙗко прешла бѣ всѣхъ ѡ҆бразовъ. видѣвъ ю припаде на земли. молѧсѧ и гл҃ѧ.  ѡ҆ прⷭ҇таꙗ бц҃е. мт҃и ха  ба҃ нашего. аще хощеши ми заступница быти. на ростовьскю землю. посѣтити новопросвѣщены люди. да въ твоеи всѧ си воли бдᲂуть. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hearing of this, the prince was pleased, and went to the church and started to look at the icons. Seeing this icon, which surpassed all images, he fell to the ground, praying and saying: “Oh Holy Mother of Our Lord Christ, if you want to be my patroness in the land of Rostov, visit the newly enlightened people there so that they will abide by your will.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">5. и тогда вземь икон поѣха на ростовьскю землю. поимъ и крилось со собою бдщю же ем птемь. поꙗ собѣ проводника. и приѣха к рѣцѣ воззѣ. и видѣвъ ю наводнившюсѧ нже ю. посла члк҃а въ рѣк пытать брод. и ꙗко вниде в рѣк на кони. и погрѧзе во дно. кн҃зь же начать молитисѧ ко иконѣ  прⷭ҇тыꙗ влчⷣца нашеа бц҃а и прⷭ҇нодв҃ци мр҃ии. ꙗко повиненъ есмь смр҃ти его. гжⷭ҇е аще не ты избавиши. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And so, having taken the icon, he set off for the land of Rostov, bringing the clergy with him too. For the road he took a guide, and came to the Vazuza river and, seeing that it had overflowed, he sent a man to look for a ford in the river. And when the man rode into the river on his horse, he sank to the bottom. The prince then began to pray before the holy icon of Our Lady Holy Mother of God and Virgin Mary: “I will be guilty in his death, my lady, unless you save him.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">6. и се быⷭ҇ намного молѧщюсѧ ем. абие изи (//390r) де среди рѣкѣ на кони. и батогъ в роцѣ. и приѣха на брегъ. кн҃зь же радъ быⷭ҇ видѣвыи. и ѡ҆даривъ ѿпꙋсти восвоꙗси. се же быⷭ҇ первое чюдо пртⷭ҇ѣи бц҃и.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he prayed so ardently that it came to pass that the man emerged in the middle of the river on his horse with a knout and rode to the shore. The prince rejoiced upon seeing him and, giving him a gift, sent him home. This was the first miracle of the Holy Mother of God. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">7. Чюⷣ в҃. Кн҃зю же сшю на рогожьски ⷯ поле ⷯ. се же миклинаꙗ попадьꙗ ѣха на колѣхъ съ снохою своею. бывшима же има на истоцѣ. и соидоста с колъ. бѣ бо попадьꙗ миклинаꙗ нетнѧ. ꙗко хотѣша минти конь. и нападе бѣсъ на конь. и зби повозника съ себе. и ног емᲂу изломи. и порази попадью миклин передними ногами. и завертѣшасѧ ем копыта в корътлѣ. и се на многъ чаⷭ҇ ꙗдѧшеть ю.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Second Miracle. When the prince was in the Rogozhskie Fields, the wife of priest Mikula was riding in a cart with her daughter-in-law. Once they arrived at the spring, they got off the cart. And the wife of Mikula was pregnant. They wanted to pass the horse, but a demon possessed the horse, and it threw off its driver and broke his leg. And it hit the wife of Mikula with its front legs, and its hooves got tangled in her clothing, and it bit her for a long time. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">8. мнѣша бо ю мрт҃в сщю. и възвѣстиша поп микли. ꙗко попадьꙗ твоꙗ мрт҃ва есть. ѡ҆нь же възрѣвъ на икон прⷭ҇тыꙗ бц҃а. и ре гжⷭ҇е прчтⷭ҇аꙗ влчⷣце. аще ты не избавиши еꙗ ѿ смр҃и. се ᲂуже мрт҃ва есть. конь же истеръ нозѣ ис ко (//390v) рьтлѧ. и бѣжа в лѣсь. и завивъсѧ и ста. въспросиша ю. ѡ҆ ꙗденьи конѧ. и ре ꙗко сдрава есмь. млт҃вами пртⷭ҇ыꙗ бц҃а. жал ми ᲂувисла же ѿлогъ еже изьѣде конь.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They even thought she had died and told the priest Mikula: “Your wife is dead.” Turning to the icon of the Holy Mother of God, he said, “Most Pure Lady, if you do not save her from death, she will be dead.” And the horse pulled his hooves out of her clothing and ran into the forest and stood there, having gotten confused. They asked her about the horse’s bite and she said, “I am alive and well because of the prayers of the Holy Mother of God, I am sorry only about the fringe on my clothing, which the horse chewed.” </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">9. приѣха вⸯволодимирь бл҃городныи кн҃зь андрѣи. и созда црк҃вь во имѧ прест҃ыꙗ бц҃а ᲂукрасивъ ю всѧкимъ бл҃гочⷭ҇тиемь. и постави в неи чюдотворню икон пртⷭ҇ѣи влчⷣци нашеи бц҃и.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Upon arrival in Vladimir, the noble Prince Andrei established a church in honor of the Holy Mother of God, decorating it with due honor. And he put the miraculous icon of the Mother of God inside. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">10. Чюдо третьее. По преходи же нѣколика времени члк҃ъ нѣкто болѣ ѡ҆гненою болезнию. в тои же болѣзни ѡ҆нѣми. и рка ем ᲂусше. въстав же ѿ болезни. начать помавати ркою здравою. мнѧхть бо ꙗко хочеть ко ст҃м николѣ. бѣ бо близь т ст҃ыи никола црк҃вь. и привезоша ко стм҃ николи. и помаваше мимо црк҃вь и не размѣша ѡ҆нь же самъ правѧше собѣ въ граⷣ къ ст҃ѣи бц҃и. и приде въ цр҃квь ст҃ыꙗ бц҃а на завътренюю. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Third Miracle. After some time, a certain man became sick with a fever. Because of his illness, he became mute and his hand withered. Once he got better, he started to make signs with his healthy hand. And they thought that he wanted to go to St. Nicholas, since the church of St. Nicholas was close by. And they brought him to St. Nicholas. And he waved them past the church and they did not understand. He himself led the horses to the city towards the church of the Holy Mother of God. And he arrived at the church of the Holy Mother of God by the matins.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">11. и ставъ въ црк҃ви ст҃ыа (//391r) бц҃а противъ ѡ҆лтарѧ. и на конець завътренни паде. и мнѣша ꙗко лихою болестью палъсѧ есть. извлекоша и въ притворъ. и т лежащю ем до ѡ҆бѣдни и въставъ начать сказывати. како видѣ ст҃ю бц҃ю. идᲂущю къ собѣ со мѣста. и ре видихъ ю близъ себе. и падохъ. и пакы не видѣхъ а бѣ бо не знакомитъ члк҃ъ тои. и начаша литргию ст҃ю  пѣти. ѡ҆н же вниде въ црк҃вь.  и нача молитисѧ ко иконѣ пртⷭ҇ыиѧ бц҃а. и ꙗко хотѣ целовати икон прест҃ѣи гжⷭ҇и влчⷣици нашеи бц҃и. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he stood in the church of the Holy Mother of God opposite the alter and at the end of the matins he fell. And they thought that he had fallen from a severe illness and took him out to the narthex, and he lay there until the liturgy service. When he recovered, he began to tell them that he had seen the Holy Mother of God walking towards him from her place, and he said, “I saw her close to me and fell and I didn’t see her again.” And this man was not noble. And the holy liturgy began. And he went into the church and began to pray to the icon of the Holy Mother of God and wanted to kiss the icon of the Most Holy Lady our Mother of God.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">12. и стѧжа ко иконѣ ркᲂу болнᲂую. гжⷭ҇а же бц҃а ст҃аꙗ ркою своею ꙗты и за рк его. кн҃зю сщю андрѣю. и попᲂу нестерᲂу, и множьствᲂу людемь видѧщⷨи въ црк҃ви. се же бысть ѿ начала и до конца литᲂургїа. нестеръ же попъ съзва клиросъ. и повелѣ облачитисѧ в ризы имъ. вземше же кртⷭ҇ы обоидоша трижⷣы црк҃вь. он же сѣдѧше въ црк҃ви простъ. попъ же сътвори празнⷣикъ. позва к себѣ кнѧзѧ и боꙗре. и и (//391v) сцѣлившаго. ѡдаривше и пᲂустиша. и быⷭ҇ радость велика въ градѣ володимерѣ того дн҃и. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he reached his sick hand to the icon. And the Holy Mother of God took his hand with her own. And Price Andrei and Priest Nestor and many people who were in the church saw this. And this  continued from the beginning to the end of the liturgy. Priest Nestor called the clergy and ordered them to dress in their vestments. They took their crosses and walked around the church three times. And he sat in the church alone. The priest served the holiday liturgy,  invited the prince and boyars, and they presented the healed man with gifts and let him go home. And there was great joy that day in the city of Vladimir. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">13. Чюдо д҃. По нѣколицⷯѣ же временехъ. пришⷣеш празнⷣикᲂу гжинᲂу дн҃и кн҃зь же андрѣи на канонѣ стоꙗше въ цр҃квѣ. пѣньꙗ ликы сътворѧꙗ. а срцⷣмь болѧше бѣ бо кнѧгини его болѧши дѣтиною болѣзнию. два дн҃и напрасно болѧщи. ꙗко по канонѣ бы. ѡмывше водою иконᲂу прест҃ыꙗ бц҃а. посла къ кнѧгинѣ. она же вкᲂуси воды тоꙗ. и роди дѣтѧ зрⷣаво, и сама бысть зрⷣава томъ часѣ. мл҃твами ст҃ыа бц҃а.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Fourth Miracle. After some time, when the feast of the Dormition of the Mother of God arrived, Prince Andrei stood at the church service singing hymns, but his heart was heavy, for the princess had labor complications: she had been in labor for two days without result. After the service, he washed the icon of the Mother of God with water and sent the water to the princess. And she drank that water and gave birth to a healthy child, and she immediately became healthy herself due to the prayers of the Holy Mother of God.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">14.  Чюдо е҃. Нѣчїи дїаволимъ наᲂученїеⷨ. створше чародѣиства въ ѧицѣ. и ѡтроча взеⷨ изъѣде. и быⷭ҇ емᲂу изметъ золъ на очеси его. изиде ꙗко ѡблакъ изъ ока его. и леже емᲂу на лици. и гл҃ахᲂуть же ꙗко ᲂумре ѡтроча. ови гл҃хᲂу ꙗко ѡ҆ко не бᲂуде. и омывше водою иконᲂу  пртѣи бц҃и. принесоша ем ꙗко же помазаша и водою. и провалисѧ изиде ѿ него болѣзнь. и бысть зрⷣавъ. и око его цѣло бысть.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Fifth Miracle. A certain person, at the instigation of the devil, performed magic with an egg. And a boy took the egg and ate it. And an evil blemish appeared on his eyes: it came out of his eye like a cloud and leaked out onto his face. And they said that the boy would die. Others said that he would lose his eye. And they performed the ritual of washing the icon of the Holy Mother of God and brought that water to the boy and anointed him with it. And the illness left him and he became healthy, and his eye was whole. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">15.  Чюⷣ ѕ҃ (//392r) Болѧшеть нѣкаꙗ жена в мᲂуромѣ. срчною болѣзнїю. и слышавши ѿ иконы ст҃ѣи бц҃и. бываемаꙗ чюдеса. и посла въ володимиръ кᲂузнь свою. къ ст҃ѣи бц҃и въ клиросъ. и воды взѧти ѿ ст҃ыа бц҃а иконы. и ꙗко принесоша вод въкᲂусивши и быⷭ҇ зрⷣава.  и нача нечюти срчⷣьныꙗ болѣзни.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Sixth Miracle. A certain woman in Murom had heart disease and, having heard that the Holy Mother of God performs miracles, she sent her icon frame to the clergy in Vladimir to the Holy Mother of God in order to get water from the icon of the Holy Mother of God. And when the water was brought to her, she drank it and became healthy, and stopped suffering from heart disease. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">16. Чюдо з҃. В рᲂуско переꙗславлѣ. въ славѧтинѣ манастыри. жидиславлѧ дщи їменемъ марїа. пострижесѧ за добродѣтелное еа житїе. даша еи игᲂуменьство. въ своего еи дѣда манастыри. и разболѣвшⷭ҇и очною болѣзнїю. и ѡслѣпе. и присла попа къ братᲂу своемᲂу  борис. борисъ же въпроси и ѡ сестрѣ своеи. и онъ рече разболѣвшисѧ ѡчною болѣзнїю и ослѣпе. и тако водѧть ю се треее лѣ. борисъ же призвавъ попа именеⷨ лазарѧ. молї и да ми принесеши водᲂу. омывь иконᲂу ст҃ыа бц҃а и попъ шеⷣ и принесе водᲂу. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Seventh Miracle. In the Rus town of Pereiaslavl in the Slaviatin monastery, the daughter of  Zhidiaslav, Maria, became a nun. In recognition of her virtuous life she was made the abbess of her grandfather’s monastery. And she became  sick with an eye disease and went blind, and she sent a priest to her brother Boris. And Boris asked him about his sister. And the priest said: “She has an eye disease and has gone blind, and for three summers she has used a guide.” Boris then called for a priest named Lazar and asked him to bring water that had been washed from the icon of the Holy Virgin. And the priest went and brought the water. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">17.   борисъ же вод тᲂу ст҃ю вливъ в вощаницю. и запечатавъ. посла и в рᲂускыи переꙗславль к сестрѣ своеи. попъ же приѣхавъ по (//392v) вѣдаше еи бывамаꙗ  чюдеса. ѿ ст҃ыа иконы водою. ѡна же радовашесѧ дшею. и рече попови. кое ми принесеши воды тоꙗ. попъ же повѣда еи ᲂу себе вод. ѡна же вкᲂуси воды тоꙗ, и очи помаза. томъ часѣ прозрѣ. ꙗко неболѣвши ѡчима. се же быⷭ҇ ст҃ѣи бц҃и велїе чюдо володимерьскои.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Boris then poured that holy water into a wax vessel and, having sealed it, sent it to his sister in Rus Pereiaslavl. Having arrived, the priest told her about the miracles that had happened from the holy icon’s water. She became delighted in her soul and said to the priest: “When will you bring me this water?” The priest said that he had the water. And she drank the water and anointed her eyes, and immediately was able to see as if her eyes had never been unwell. Such was the great miracle of the Vladimir Holy Mother of God icon. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">18.  Чюдо и҃. Се же быⷭ҇ ново чюдо. ст҃ѣи бц҃и ѡ женѣ именемь еᲂуфимїи. болѣвши еи срчⷣьною болѣзнїю, з҃ . лѣ. и ѿ многъ искавши еи исцѣленїа. и не обрѣте. и призва попа лазарѧ. и ре ч имъ бы помощи болѣзни сеи. попъ ре, аще тѧ не избавить ст҃аꙗ бц҃а. то не избдешь болѣзни сеѧ. она же слышавши ѿ него. бываемаꙗ чюдеса водою. ѿ иконы пртⷭ҇ыа бц҃а. и посла ᲂусирѧзи же и рѧсы златыѧ. къ ст҃ѣи бц҃и вⸯволодимиръ. с попомъ гл҃ѧ. да ми принесеть пртⷭ҇ыа воды тоа. того дн҃и исцѣли ѿ болѣзни. начать ꙗсти и пити въ сладость.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Eighth Miracle. This was a new miracle of the Holy Mother of God regarding a woman named Euphemia. She had been sick with heart disease for seven years and sought a cure from many people but did not find one. And she summoned the priest Lazar and said: “What would help cure this disease?” The priest said: “If the Holy Mother of God will not heal you, then you will not get rid of the disease.” After hearing from him of the miracles performed by the water of the Holy Mother of God icon, she sent the priest to the Holy Mother of God in Vladimir with her earrings and golden head pendants, asking to bring her the holy water. And when he brought her the water and she drank it, she was cured of her disease that same day, and she began to eat and drink with joy. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">19.  Чюдо ѳ҃. А се быⷭ҇ въ тфѣри. нѣкаа жена болѧшеть дѣтятеⷨ три дн҃и. и приѣха попъ лазарь. и навита ᲂу ниⷯ. (//393r) она же въспроси попа о зрⷣавьи. онъ же ре зрⷣавы есме нъ не велми. боꙗрыни наша в концинѣ есть. се же гл҃ющима прїиде вѣсть ѿ неѧ. ѡ҆ ѡ҆ц҃а поидита. и ре има при срамѣ есть. понеже смертна есмь. попъ же лазарь  ре еи. аще не обѣщаешисѧ ст҃ѣи бц҃и володимерьскои. ї не избᲂудеши. она же обѣщасѧ. и рече попомъ. идите ѿсюд . повелѣ дати има ꙗсти и пити. прїиде же вѣсть ѿ неѧ. ꙗкѡ ᲂуже родила бѣ сн҃а, и сама зрⷣава. и посла златыа косы. и ᲂусерѧзи свои къ иконѣ ст҃ыа бц҃а в володимиръ. имиже ѡ҆бѣщаласѧ бѣ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Ninth Miracle. And this happened in Tver. A certain woman was in labor for three days. And the Priest Lazar [and another priest] came and stayed with them. She asked about their health. He said: “We are well, but not very, since our mistress is close to death.” While they were talking, there came a request from her: “Holy fathers, come to me.” And she said to them: “I am not ashamed because I am close to death.” And Priest Lazar then said to her: “If you do not make a vow to the Holy Vladimir Mother of God, then you will not be cured.” And she made a vow and said to the priests: “Leave this place.” She ordered to give them food and drink. And news came from her that she had already given birth to a son and was herself in health. And, as she had promised, she sent her golden jewelry and earrings to the icon of the Holy Mother of God in Vladimir.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">20.  Чюⷣ  і҃. Кнѧзь бл҃горⷣныи андрѣи. съзаⷣ златаꙗ врата. къ празнⷣик  ст҃ыꙗ бц҃а. гл҃ѧ къ боꙗромъ. егⷣа снидᲂутсѧ лю󰀣е на празнⷣикъ. и врата ᲂузрѧ. бывшᲂу же празнⷣикᲂу. и снидесѧ нароⷣ къ вратомъ. бѣ бо еще не сᲂуха извисть въ вратѣⷯ. абїе же вънезапᲂу истръгшисѧ ѿ стѣнъ врата. и падоша на люди. и покрыша ві҃ мᲂужа. се же слышавъ кнѧзь андрѣи. (//393v) начать съ възⷣыхание молитисѧ. къ иконѣ пртѣи бц҃и. гжⷭ҇е прчтⷭ҇аа влчⷣце. аще сиⷯ ты не избавиши, азъ бо грѣшныи повиненъ быхъ см҃рти сихъ. и посла боѧрина своего. дати все на потребᲂу мрт҃вымь. он же приѣхавъ. и вьзѧша врата. и видиша всⷯѣ сᲂущиⷯ пѡⷣ враты живыⷯ и зрⷣавыхъ. и се слышавъ кн҃зь андрѣи раⷣ бысть. и се чюдо видѣвше народѣ чюдишасѧ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Tenth Miracle. The noble Prince Andrei built the golden gates for the feast of the Holy Mother of God and said to the boyars: “When people come to the feast they will see the gates.” When the feast day arrived and the people came to the gates, the lime in the gate had not yet dried. And suddenly the gate fell off the walls and onto the people, crushing twelve of them. When Prince Andrei heard of this, he began to pray and lament in front of the icon of the Holy Mother of God: “Most Pure Virgin Mother, if you do not save them, then I, a sinner, will be guilty of their deaths.” And he sent his boyar to provide all that was necessary to bury the dead. When the boyar arrived and the gate was lifted, the people underneath it were all alive and healthy. And hearing this, Prince Andrei was glad. And, seeing the miracle, the people marveled. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>