<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI 
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Muspilli</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription based on</resp>
					<name>Schlosser, Horst Dieter.<hi rend="italic">Althochdeutsche Literatur. Mit altniederdeutschen Textbeispielen. Auswahl mit Übertragungen und Kommentar</hi>, Berlin: Erich Schmidt Verlag 2004, pp. 82–86.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Introduction by</resp>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>				
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
				<p>Muspilli is an incomplete verse narrative (103 lines) written in Old High German. The manuscript containing the poem, which was produced in Bavaria (southern Germany) in the 9th century CE, contains neither the beginning nor the end of the poem. The reason for its incompleteness is probably due to its having been written in the margins of another text: a Latin theological work composed by Adalram (d. 836), bishop of Salzburg, for the young Louis the German (ca. 810–876). It appears Muspilli was added to the manuscript later by a different scribe, but little can be deduced about who produced the text or why. It is conjectured that the beginning and end have been lost because they would have been written on the outermost pages of the manuscript, which often incur the most damage over time.</p>

				<p>One of the most debated questions about Muspilli is its name. The original manuscript does not include a title, and the name Muspilli was assigned by the poem's first editor, Johann Andreas Schmeller. The name comes from the Old High German word muspille, meaning the destruction of the world by fire, which occurs in line 57 of the poem. This is the only known occurrence of this word. Scholars have since tried to give it various names which better suit the purpose of the poem, but none of these has stuck.</p>

				<p>Muspilli mainly deals with two main ideas: the fate of human souls after death and the Final Judgement. The first part of the poem describes how two groups of angels will fight over one soul to see whether it belongs in Heaven or Hell. The second part of the poem provides two narratives: Elijah and the Antichrist fight each other, the former as the champion of God and the latter as the champion of the Devil. In this duel, the Antichrist will be defeated and Elijah will be wounded and his blood will burn the whole world. Then the text describes how, in the Final Judgement, angels and demons will testify to the actions of humans on earth, and those actions will be scrutinized. At the end of the poem, the Holy Cross is brought forth and Christ reveals the wounds that he suffered for the sake of humankind.</p>

				<p>One of the most discussed aspects of this poem are its sources. Although explicitly Christian elements are abundant, scholars have argued that Muspilli is deeply infused with pre-Christian culture and draws much of its material from Norse mythology. Although the names mentioned in the poem are all Christian figures, some scholars argue that they are essentially the Christian representation of Norse gods. </p>

				<p>Muspilli is considered to be one of the most significant pieces of Old High German literature because of its vivid depiction of Christian themes in the vernacular language. Through this poem, modern readers can gain a better insight into the spiritual life and broader culture of ninth-century Germans.</p>

				<p>Murdoch, Brian. “The Carolingian Period and the Early Middle Ages (750–1100).” The Cambridge History of German Literature, edited by Helen Watanabe-O'Kelly, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1997, pp. 1–39.
				
				An overview of German literature from 750-1100 CE which includes discussion of Muspilli (on pp. 24).</p>

				<p>Wells, Christopher. "The Shorter German Verse Text." German Literature of the Early Middle Ages, edited by Brian Murdoch, Rochester, N.Y: Camden House, 2004, 157-199.
				
				An overview of Old High German verse texts, including a comparison between the Wessobrunn Prayer, Muspilli, and Lay of Ludwig (all published in the Global Medieval Sourcebook).</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Muspilli</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Muspilli</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Muspilli" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
 			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Muspilli</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Muspilli</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg>
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">...sin tac piqueme, daz er touuan scal.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">...his day comes, when he has to die.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuanta sar so sih diu sela in den sind arhevit</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Immediately afterwards, when the soul starts its journey</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti si den lihhamun likkan lazzit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and leaves the body behind,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">so quimit ein heri fona himilzungalon,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">then a host comes from the heaven’s firmament</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz andar fona pehhe: dar pagant siu umpi.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And another from hell: then they will fight for her [i. e. the soul].</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sorgen mac diu sela, unzi diu suona arget,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The soul has to worry until the judgement is made,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">za uuederemo herie si gihalot uuerde.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As to which host she is brought.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuanta ipu sia daz Satanazses kisindi kiuuinnit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For if Satan’s retainers win her,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz leitit sia sar dar iru leid uuirdit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They promptly lead her [the soul] to a place where pain awaits her,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">in fuir enti in finstri: daz ist rehto uirinlih ding.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Into fire and darkness: that is a truly horrible verdict.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Upi sia auar kihalont die, die dar fona himile quemant,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But if she is taken by those who come from heaven</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti si dero engilo eigan uuirdit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And is claimed by the angels,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">die pringent sia sar uf in himilo rihi:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They promptly bring her up into the heavenly kingdom</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dar ist lip ano tod, lioht ano finstri,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Where there is life without death, light without darkness,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">selida ano sorgun: dar nist neoman siuh.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A refuge without worry: there nobody suffers sickness.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne der man in pardisu pu kiuuinnit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For if a person wins a place in paradise,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">hus in himile, dar quimit imo hilfa kinuok.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A house in heaven, he will find a lot of support there.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pidiu ist durft mihhil</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus the need is great</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">allero manno uuelihemo, daz in es sin muot kispane,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">for everybody, that his [spirit/heart]
						<note anchored="true">
								<p>The correct translation of “muot” is controversial. A large camp of scholars translate it as “spirit” ( “der Geist” in modern German), although others translate it as "heart".</p>
							</note>is moved</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz er kotes uuillun kerno tuo</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">to gladly do God’s will</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti hella fuir harto uuise,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And firmly avoid hellfire,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pehhes pina. dar piutit Satanaz altist</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hell’s pain: there, the ancient Satan waits</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">heizzan lauc. so mac huckan za diu,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With hot fire. Therefore he, who knows himself</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">sorgen drato, der sih suntigen uueiz.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">to be sinful, shall think about this with great worry.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uue demo in uinstri scal sino uirina stuen,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Woe to him who has to atone for his sins in darkness</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">prinnan in pehhe: daz ist rehto paluuic dink,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and burn in hell. It is a truly horrible judgement,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz der man haret ze gote enti imo hilfa ni quimit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When somebody calls upon God and receives no help.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuanit sih kinada diu uuenaga sela.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wretched soul hopes for mercy,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ni ist in kihuctin himiliskin gote,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But she is not remembered by the heavenly God,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuanta hiar in uuerolti aftar ni uuerkota.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">because she has not proven herself worthy here in the world.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So denne der mahtigo khuninc daz mahal kipannit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the powerful King proclaims the day of judgement</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dara scal queman queman chunno kilihaz.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Every kin must come there.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne ni kitar parno nohhein den pan furisizzan,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">No child of man can dare to reject this command,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">nio allero manno uuelih ze demo mahale sculi.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[assuming] that not everybody had to attend this judgement.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dar scal er uora demo rihhe az rahhu stantan,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">There he shall give account to the Almighty
							<note anchored="true">
								<p>“rahha stantan” is a legal technical term meaning “to give an account for something.”. The expression is still used in modern German as “Rechenschaft stehen”.</p>
							</note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pi daz er in uuerolti kiuuerkot hapeta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">for what he has done in this world.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz hortih rahhon dia uueroltrehuuison,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I have heard the wise men of the world tell</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz sculi der antichristo mil Eliase pagan.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That the antichrist shall fight against Elijah.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">der uuarch ist kiuuafanit, denne uuirdit untar in uuic arhapan.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fiend is armed, and then the fight between them will start.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">khenfun sint so kreftic, diu kosa ist so mihhil:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fighters are so powerful, the cause is so crucial:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Elias stritit pi den ewiigon lip,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Elijah fights for eternal life,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuili din rehtkernon daz rihhi kistarkan.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He wants to secure the realm for the righteous</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pidiu scal imo helfan der himiles kiuualtit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He who rules in heaven shall help him with this.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">der antichristo stet pi demo altfiante,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The antichrist stands with the ancient foe,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">stet pi Satanase, der inan uarsenkan scal.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Stands with Satan, who wants to destroy him [Elijah]:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pidiu scal er in deru uuicsteti uuunt pivallan</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But he [the antichrist] will fall wounded on this battlefield,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="47">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti in demo sinde sigalos uuerdan.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And in this way be without victory.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="48">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Doh uuanit des uilo gotmanno,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Yet many men of God believe</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="49">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz Elias in demo uuige aruuartit uuerde.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That Elijah will be wounded in the battle.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="50">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">so daz Eliases pluot in erda kitriufit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So when Elijah’s blood drips on the earth,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="51">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">so inprinnant die perga, poum ni kistentit</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The mountains catch fire and no single tree on earth</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="52">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enihc in erdu, aha artruknent,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">remains standing, all waters dry up,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="53">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">muor uarsuuilhit sih, suilizot lougiu der himil,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The moor swallows itself, the heaven perishes in flames,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="54">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">mano uallit, prinnit mittilagart,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The moon falls, Middle Earth burns.
						<note anchored="true" type="critical">
								<p>“mittilagart” could also be translated as “Midgard”, (although the phrase "middle earth" is now well known to readers of Tolkein) which was the name of the human realm in Norse and Germanic myth. It is an interesting example of the mixing of pagan cosmological models with Christian apocalyptic narrative.</p>
							</note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="55">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">sten ni kistentit eikin in erdu, uerit denne tuatago in lant,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Stones do not stand fast by their owners on earth, and then judgement day comes upon the land,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="56">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uerit mit diu uuiru uiriho uuison.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Comes with fire to afflict the people:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="57">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dar ni mac denne mak helfan uora demo muspille.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">No kinsman can help the other in the face of the Muspilli.<note anchored="true" type="critical">
								<p>The exact translation and etymology of “muspille” is unclear. Later Nordic sources suggest that it roughly means “destruction of the world by fire”.</p>
							</note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="58">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne daz preita uuasal allaz uarprennit</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the whole circle of the world burns,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="59">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti uuir enti luft iz allaz arfurpit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and a storm of fire and air annihilates everything,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="60">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuar ist denne diu marha, dar man dar eo mit sinen magon piehc?</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Where is then the homeland, for which one before had fought together with one’s kinsmen?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="61">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Diu marha ist farprunnan, diu sela stet piduungan,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The homeland is burned, the soul stands defeated,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="62">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ni uueiz mit uuiu puaze: sar verit si za uuize.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Not knowing how to atone: soon she will face punishment.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="63">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pidiu ist demo manne so guot, denner ze demo mahale quimit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore it is good for a man, when he comes to the tribunal,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="64">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz er rahono uueliha rehto arteile.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To have always delivered rightful judgements.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="65">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Denne ni darf er sorgen, denne er ze deru suonu quimit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then he needs not to worry when he faces this trial.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="66">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ni uueiz der uuenago man uuielihan uuartil er habet,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A weak person does not know what sentence awaits him,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="67">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denner mit den miaton marrit daz rehta,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">when he breaks the law with bribery,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="68">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz der tiuual dar pi kitarnit stentit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And that the devil hides close to him,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="69">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">der hapet in ruouu rahono uueliha,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and quietly takes into account every evil deed</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="70">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz der man er enti sid upiles kifrumita,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">that this person has done and will do,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="71">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz er iz allaz kisaget, denne er ze deru suono quimit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In order to report it all when he [the man] faces the trial.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="72">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ni scolta manno nohhein miatun intfahan.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore, nobody should ever accept bribes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="73">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So daz himilisca horn kilutit uuirdit</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the heavenly horn is blown</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="74">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti sih der suanari ana den sind arheuit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the judge, who shall judge the dead</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="75">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">der da suannan scal toten enti lepenten,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and the living, will start his journey,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="76">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne heuit sih mit imo herio meista.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">the largest host will rise together with him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="77">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz ist allaz so pald, daz imo nioman kipagan ni mak.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This [host] is so brave that no one can stand up against it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="78">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Denne uerit er ze deru mahalsteti, deru dar kimarchot ist,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then he will go to the judgement place, which is staked out,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="79">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dar uuirdit diu suona, dia man dar io sageta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That is where the trial will take place as it has been proclaimed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="80">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Denne uarant engila uper dio marha,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Angels will then travel over the land,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="81">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuechant deota, uuissant ze dinge.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">wake the dead, call them to the judgement.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="82">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne scal manno gilih fona deru moltu arsten,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then everybody will resurrect from the dust,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="83">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Lossan si ar dero leuuo vazzon, scal imo auar sin lip piqueman,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Release himself from the burden of the grave: he shall regain his body,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="84">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz er sin reht allaz kirahhn muozzi</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So that he can fairly answer for everything</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="85">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti imo after sinen tatin arteilit uuerde.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And be judged for his deeds.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="86">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Denne der gisizzit, der dâr suonnan scal</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then he sits down, the one who shall try in court</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="87">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti arteillan scal toten enti quekkhen,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And pass judgement over the dead and the living;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="88">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne stet dar umpi engilo menigi,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The host of angels surrounds him,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="89">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">guotero gomono: gart ist so mihhil,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and [many] good men: The place [of judgement] is large,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="90">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dara quimit ze deu rihtungu so uilo, dia dar ar resti arstent</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And so many who have arisen from their rest come to the trial.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="91">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">so dar manno nohhein uuiht pimidan ni mak,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Nobody can hide anything there,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="92">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dar scal denne hant sprehhan, houpit sagen,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Or else the hand will speak, the head will talk,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="93">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">allero lido uuelihc unzi in den luzigun uinger,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Every limb down to the smallest finger,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="94">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuaz er untar mannun mordes kifrumita.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">What murder it has committed amongst men.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="95">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dar ni ist eo so listic man, der dar iouuiht arliugan megi,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore nobody is cunning enough to be able to tell a lie there</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="96">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">daz er kitarnan megi tato dehheina,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Or to hide any deed:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="97">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">niz al fora demo khuninge kichundit uuerde,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It will still be revealed in front of the king</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="98">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uzzan er iz mit alamusanu furimegi</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">unless he can compensate for it with alms [he has given],</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="99">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">enti mit fastun dio uirina kipuazti.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And has atoned for the crimes with fasting.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="100">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Denne der paldet, der gipuazzit hapet, denner ze deru suonu quimit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore he, who has atoned, needs not to worry when he comes to this judgement.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="101">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">uuirdit denne furi kitragan daz frono chruci,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then the noble cross will be carried forward,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="102">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">dar der heligo Christ ana arhangan uuard,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Upon which the holy Christ was crucified,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="103">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">denne augit er dio masun, dio er in deru menniski anfenc,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he will show the wounds that he received as a man,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="104">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">duruh desse mancunnes minna f[ardoleta]...</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That he had obtained for his love of mankind.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
