<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Origin of the Pastoral Care</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Alexandra Reider</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Alexandra Reider</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>This short preface to Pope Gregory the Great’s Regula Pastoralis (Pastoral Rule or Pastoral Care) offers an unusual account of the genesis of that text, composed—so the preface says—during travel that Gregory undertook through Gaul in an attempt to avoid becoming pope. By contrast, the standard narrative of the Pastoral Care’s origin sees it completed presumably in Rome, not long after Gregory’s papal inauguration, and sent off thence to John, bishop of Ravenna. (History supports the second version of events: Gregory was first in Constantinople, then Rome, prior to assuming the papacy.) Gregory’s initial reluctance to become pope is a constant in both origin stories, however, even if he is more active in his escapism in the preface presented here. The tally noted in the preface extends Gregory’s time in office by four months. He was pope from September 3, 590 to March 12, 604: thirteen years, six months (not ten months), and nine days. The etymology of Gregory’s name is sound. The preface also alludes to a second alternate history of the Pastoral Care, one that is introduced in a more displaced way: “And others think that…” This origin story is vague with its mentions of an “emperor of the Goths” and a “demented leader of the Romans,” but these could be references to Justin II, Emperor of the Byzantine Empire (r. 565-74), and Leovigild, the Visigothic king with whom he contended. (Justin II notably suffered from mental illness.) This would place the text’s purported composition sometime between 565 and 574; for context, Gregory entered monastic life in 574.</p>
				<p>To the best of my knowledge, this text has not been previously edited or translated. I have found it in two English manuscripts that were produced centuries apart and that bear no direct relation to one another: Oxford, St. John’s College, MS 28 (s. x med. and x3/4 or x/xi; the Pastoral Care is in the slightly later part), fol. 6v and Oxford, Merton College, MS 16, (s. xiv ex., xv1), fol. 139va. The text must certainly exist in more manuscript witnesses of the Pastoral Care, from a range of times and—one assumes, given the text’s continental origin—of places.</p>
				<p>Godden, Malcolm. “Prologues and Epilogues in the Old English Pastoral Care, and Their Carolingian Models.” Journal of English and Germanic Philology, vol. 110, no. 4, 2011, pp. 441-73.</p>
				<p>St. Gregory the Great. The Book of Pastoral Rule. Translated by George Demacopoulos. St. Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2007.</p>
				<p>Neil, Bronwen and Matthew Dal Santo, editors. A Companion to Gregory the Great. Brill, 2013.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Oxford, St John’s College, MS 28, fol. 6v</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">De origine Regulae pastoralis</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">On the Origin of the Pastoral Care</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"On the Origin of the Pastoral Care" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>All abbreviations in the manuscript witness have been expanded and the title "On the Origin of the Pastoral Care" has been added by the translator.</p>
        			<p>I have transcribed this text diplomatically from St. John’s College, MS 28 and double-checked it against Merton College, MS 16. The two witnesses follow each other word-for-word except for two presumed misspellings: MS 16 reads tritor for nutritor and plicipatum for principatum. The only other differences are the spelling, punctuation and abbreviations used: a remarkable fixity, in view of the centuries between the two known versions. On my decision to translate brigalis as “Bruges”: brigalis is described as a city in gallia belgica (“Belgian Gaul”), and Bruges was indeed settled by the late sixth century, so it would have been an option to a fleeing Gregory. But I have not found brigalis as an attested Latin term for “Bruges” (or indeed for anywhere else in Belgian Gaul). Brigalis, then, is either evidence of a further place-name for Bruges or a name of a different city.</p>
        			<p>I would like to thank the Lynne Grundy Memorial Trust for funding my travel within the UK to examine the Oxford manuscripts named here and the Scriptorium Working Group at Yale University for discussing this fascinating little text with me, as well as the team behind the Global Medieval Sourcebook.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Gregorius urbis romę æpiscopus hunc librum pastoralis curę scripsit pro excusatione episcoporum eo quod pelagius illius nutritor et romanę æcclesię princeps eum rogabat.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Gregory, bishop of the city of Rome, wrote this book of pastoral care for the benefit of bishops because Pelagius, his mentor and head of the Roman church,</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"> ut post se episcopi locum tenuisset.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">asked that he take the place of bishop after him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">et in gallia lugdunensi conscripsit huius libri incepta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And in Lyonnais Gaul he composed the beginnings of this book</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">et in gallia belgica consummata est id est in ciuitate que dicitur brigalis</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and in Belgian Gaul it was completed, that is, in the city that is called Bruges,</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">quia gregorius principatum uitare uolens in occidentales plagas gallorum fugerat.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">because Gregory, wanting to avoid leadership, had fled to the western regions of Gaul.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">et alii putant quia imperatoris de gothis vel insani regis romanorum tempore hic liber conscriptus est in quo narrat gregorius opus esse difficile principatum æcclesię;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And others think that this book, in which Gregory recounts that leadership of the Church is difficult work, was begun at the time of the emperor of the Goths or of the demented leader of the Romans.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sanctus gregorius. annis. xiii. et. mensibus. x. et diebus. ix. rexit æcclesiam;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">St. Gregory ruled the Church for thirteen years and ten months and nine days.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Gregorius grece uigil latine.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Gregorius” in Greek means vigil [“alert”] in Latin,</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">et a uerbo gregorio. iii. coniugationes. quia inuenitur gregorite id est uigilate.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and from the word “Gregorius” come three etymological connections because “gregorite” – that is, vigilate [“you (pl.) watch”] – is found.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
