<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Concerning the Wicked Woman</title>
				<author>Petrus Pictor</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Astrid Khoo</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Astrid Khoo</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Irene Han</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>Petrus Pictor, a canon (resident clergyman) at Saint-Omer in northern France, composed De Muliere Mala (“The Wicked Woman”) in the late eleventh or early twelfth century. In his poem, Pictor first cites a litany of historical and biblical examples on the evil of womankind before detailing the fatal vengeance of a rebuffed mother-seducer who falsely accuses her own son of rape. De Muliere Mala thus participates in a long tradition of misogynistic Christian writing as embodied by Tertullian, a pioneering theologian from the second and third centuries AD, who interpreted Eve’s fall from grace as a warning that women are “the Devil’s gateway” (De Habitu Mulierum 1.1). Nevertheless, it is far more than a mere moralising text, for its explicit treatment of incestuous lust looks to Classical models: Pictor accords a literary status to his verses by referencing ancient erotic writers such as Ovid (43BC-17/18AD) and Apuleius (c. 124-170 AD). The rhetoric of the poem is reinforced by its aggressive anaphoras (repeated phrases at the beginnings of certain lines) and pounding polysyndetons (lists of words linked only by conjunctions, typically “and...and”), which simultaneously drive home the notion that all women are malicious and evoke the eponymous Wicked Woman’s uncontrollable frenzy. Owing to these complex layers, this rarely-studied poem has the potential to please a diverse crowd. It is especially interesting to consider its portrayal of sexual aggression in the light of current debates on this topic, and to question its support of gender essentialism, that is, the notion that all women share the same malevolent characteristics. The poem is, moreover, an enjoyable read as it constitutes a thrilling psychological portrait on the extremities to which lust and pride can lead.</p>
				<p>The De Muliere Mala was first compiled in the Liber Floridus, an 1120 encyclopedia containing what Lambert, a later canon of Saint Omer, considered to be the most important knowledge in his possession. The “autograph copy,” written in Lambert’s own hand, is currently stored in the Ghent University Library as MS 92. The manuscript includes other Pictor poems, for example a satire on money narrated by the personified Denarius (“Dollar”). The fact that Pictor’s work was deliberately excerpted for inclusion in this collection, alongside more well-known texts such as Isidore’s Etymologiae, indicates that contemporaries appreciated its literary and moral value. While there are no exact duplicates, dozens of partial copies survive, including the twelfth-century French manuscript upon which this edition is based. Their proliferation suggests that Petrus Pictor, and by extension the De Muliere Mala, were frequently read in medieval European monasteries.</p>
				<p>Carver, Robert H. F. “Apuleius in the High Middle Ages.” The Protean Ass: The Metamorphoses of Apuleius from Antiquity to the Renaissance. Oxford UP, 2007, pp. 61-107. Elaborates on how Pictor borrowed specific elements of his De Muliere Mala from Apuleius’ descriptions of lustful women.</p>
				<p>Derolez, Albert. The Making and Meaning of the Liber Floridus: A Study of the Original Manuscript. Ghent, University Library, MS 92. Brepols, 2015. A comprehensive introduction to the manuscript in which Pictor’s poems were first transmitted.</p>
				<p>Muir Tyler, Elizabeth. “Reading through the Conquest.” England in Europe: English Royal Women and Literary Patronage, c. 1000-1150. U of Toronto P, 2017, pp. 260-301. Describes the link between Pictor’s life experiences (e.g. his travels outside Flanders) and his poetic style, while also highlighting key contemporaries.</p>
				<p>Van Acker, Lieven, editor. Petri Pictoris Carmina. Nec Non Petri de Sancto Audemaro Librum de Coloribus Faciendis. CCCM 25. Brepols, 1972, pp. 103-116. Most recent Latin edition of Pictor’s complete works, including the De Muliere Mala.</p>
				<p>Wieser, Marie T. “Zu Petrus Pictors misogynem Carmen 14.” Wiener Studien, vol. 115, 2002, pp. 315-20. The best introduction to this text is in German. This article discusses the structure and misogynistic themes of the De Muliere Mala, and demonstrates that Pictor borrowed heavily from Roman declamation.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<P></P>			
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">De Muliere Mala</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Concerning the Wicked Woman</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"On the Wicked Woman" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">De Muliere Mala</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Concerning the Wicked Woman</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
					<l n="1">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quisquis male mulieris artes malas scire queris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">May you, who seek to know the wicked tricks of Woman,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="2">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que subscripsi coacerua, lege disce, mente serua.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Read, learn, and keep in mind the the verses written below.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="3">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si uis tandem felix esse, haec ut legas est necesse.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, if you wish to be happy, it is necessary that you read these words.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="4">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic addisces, hic uidebis, quid dimittes, quid tenebis.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Here you will learn and see what you will dismiss and what you will remember.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="5">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic Caribdis atque Sille patent antra, Syrtes mille,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Here lie open the caves of Scylla and Charybdis, along with a thousand Sirtes:
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The Gulf of Sirte, infamous for its hazardous sandbanks, is located on the northern coast of Libya.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="6">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic describo Cyrcen lenam, absorbentemque balenam.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Here I describe whorish Circe and the all-consuming whale.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This is perhaps a reference to Jonah 1.17.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="7">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que ne formides in mari, naui uectus salutari,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So that you will not fear these threats at sea, while you sail in a salutary ship,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="8">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Deum ama, fuge scortum. Castitatis tene portum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You should love God, flee harlotry, and seek the port of chastity.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="9">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Uersus et euersus in me, dum fabrico uersus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">While I compose my verses, I twist and turn within my mind.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="10">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non ualeo fari, non scribere, non meditari,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I can barely speak, write, and think:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="11">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ut fatear uerum, que sit feritas mulierum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">How can I ever tell the entire truth about the savagery of women?</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="12">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed licet ad uotum nequeam describere totum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nevertheless, although I cannot describe it all, as I wish to,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="13">
						<app loc="l13">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quicquid de Scilla feritatis habundat in illa,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l14">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I shall speak a little – if the Muses come to my aid –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="14">
						<app loc="l14">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dicam pauca tamen, si det michi musa iuuamen.</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l13">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">About that Scyllan beastliness that abounds in Woman.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>
										 There are two Scyllas mentioned in the poem – the aquatic monster Scylla (Hom. <hi rend="italic">Od.</hi> 12.111-150) and Scylla, princess of Megara (Ov. <hi rend="italic">Met.</hi> 8.6-151). In this case, the term <hi rend="italic">‘feritatis’</hi> (‘[of] beastliness’) evokes the former rather than the latter.
									</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="15">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Prestat in orbe feris cunctis feritas mulieris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The savagery of Woman exceeds that of all the beasts in the world;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="16">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tygri predoni prestat, rapidoque leoni;</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It puts to shame the preying tiger and swift-footed lion.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>
										 ‘Puts to shame’ is an idiomatic translation of <hi rend="italic">‘prestat’</hi> and its dative object; more literally, ‘The savagery of Woman exceeds that of the preying tiger and the swift-footed lion’.
									</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="17">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Uincitur istarum feritas, rabiesque ferarum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">On the one hand, the savagery of these creatures and the madness of all other beasts can be conquered,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="18">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Haeque
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>As is expected with medieval manuscripts, the ‘ae’ digraph is confused with the letter ‘e’ throughout. I have preserved the [mis]spellings of the manuscript. In this case ‘ae’ is used correctly, but often it is not (cf. line 78).</p>
								</note>
							 pati discunt homines illosque tremiscunt.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As they learn to bear the yoke and tremble at men.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="19">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina uero feris truculencior una seueris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">On the other hand, Woman alone is more ferocious than the fiercest beasts:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="20">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Numquam pacatur, nulla racione domatur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She is never appeased, and can in no way be tamed.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="21">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non homini cedit, non sponte fauet nec obedit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She does not yield to Man, nor favour him, nor obey him.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="22">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non ad iter recti ualet ullo uerbere flecti.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She cannot be led to the right path with beatings;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="23">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo uexata magis fuerit mala femina plagis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In fact, the more a wicked woman is harried by blows,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="24">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tanto maiorem studet exercere furorem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The greater fury she strives to exhibit.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="25">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nec mala desistit fieri, stimuloque resistit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Moreover, she does not cease becoming evil, but instead resists the spur.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="26">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quisquis Samsonem considerat et Salomonem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Whoever considers the cases of Samson and Solomon,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="27">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et reliquos multos mulieris amore sopitos</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the many others brought to eternal rest by love of a woman,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="28">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Discet et intendet, mirabitur et reprehendet</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Will learn, notice, criticise and marvel at</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="29">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Exemplis ueris portenta male mulieris.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The real-life precursors of my ‘wicked woman’.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="30">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina flamma furens, sed flammis acrius urens</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman, flaming mad, is singed all the more sharply by her own flames.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="31">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Totum concussit mundum, succendit, et ussit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She shakes up the whole world, lights it on fire, and burns it down.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="32">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hec est cunctorum caput, et scintilla malorum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She is the beginning and spark of all evils,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="33">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Orbis que metas semper facit inrequietas.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For she troubles the ends of the earth for eternity.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="34">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">O mala scintilla: quisquis succenditur illa,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">O wicked spark: whoever is set alight by Woman</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="35">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ille nec indigne misero consumitur igne,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">is deservedly consumed by a wretched fire,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="36">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nec nisi diuina ualet extingui medicina.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">which cannot be extinguished unless by some divine remedy.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="37">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Haec hominem primum de celso trusit in imum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It was Woman who first cast Man down from up high,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="38">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Intulit et penam mundo, mortisque catenam.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">bringing punishment and the chain of death to the world.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="39">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sponsum, serpentem, uitam, genus, Omnipotentem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She betrayed her husband, welcomed the serpent, spurned life,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="40">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Prodidit, admisit, spreuit, uiciauit, omisit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">injured mankind, and lost the All-Powerful.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>In the original Latin, this sentence is constructed using two asyndetic verses: ‘Her husband, the serpent, life, mankind, and the All-Powerful / she betrayed, welcomed, spurned, injured, and lost.’</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="41">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et quis eam laudet? Quicquid male cogitat audet,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And who shall praise her? She dares to perform whatever evil she thinks up,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="42">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et cupit expleri rem, qua rea possit haberi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">and yearns to commit some act, so that she will be perceived as guilty.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="43">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nil fugit incestum, cupit omne quod est inhonestum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In addition, she shuns nothing which is taboo, but wants everything which is dishonourable.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="44">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quicquid agit secum, fas siue nefas, putat equum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She considers all her plans to be just, whether they be right or wrong.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="45">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina terrarum confusio, mors animarum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman is the disorder of lands and the death of souls:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="46">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ut mundo late resonet scelerum nouitate,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">she is heard far and wide throughout the world due to the strangeness of her sins.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="47">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nil dubium dubitat, nichil euitabile uitat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She does not doubt that which is doubtful, nor avoid that which is avoidable,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="48">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nil intemptatum sinit, it scelus omne patratum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">but leaves nothing untried, and commits every sin,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="49">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ad causas quasque confundens fasque nefasque.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">confusing right and wrong for her own purposes.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="50">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo magis obscenum scelus est, magis huic fit amenum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The more obscene a crime is, the more pleasant it seems to her;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="51">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo magis horrendum, magis hoc putat esse colendum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">the more terrible a sin, the greater the glory she places upon it.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="52">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Imperium, sensum, uires, fastidia, censum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She obtains power, weakens perception, diminishes strength,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="53">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Optinet, emollit, minuit, generat, male tollit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">creates annoyance, and exhausts wealth.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The original Latin is constructed in the same way as the note suggested on line 40.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="54">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina tormentum iuuenum, mortis monimentum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, Woman is a torment for young men and a reminder of death:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="55">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mortem Samsoni dedit, interitum Salomoni.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">she brought about Samson’s demise and Solomon’s end.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="56">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina priuauit pietatis robore Dauid,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She also deprived David of the strength of his piety,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="57">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quando per inuidiam iugulari fecit Uriam</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">when he ordered Uriah’s murder out of lustful envy.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to 2 Samuel 11:5-27. David places Uriah at the front lines of a dangerous battle so as to eliminate him, as he was enamoured with Uriah’s wife, Bathsheba.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="58">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Coniuge pro pulchra multi subiere sepulcra.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Many have gone to their graves due to their beautiful wives.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="59">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina plena malis, faera, pessima, demonialis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman is full of evils, wild, demonic, the worst of all creatures.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="60">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Priuauit uita Naboth, pro uitae cupita:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She took away Naboth’s life to obtain his vineyard;
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p> This refers to 1 Kings 21:2-15. Jezebel has Naboth killed so that her husband, King Ahab, can have Naboth’s vineyard.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="61">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Causa necis subitae sunt res plerumque cupite.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">she murders on sudden impulses, and especially out of greed.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="62">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina mors mundi, mala femina fabula mundi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, Woman is the death of the world, and a wicked woman is its scandal.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="63">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Exicium, reges, insontes, federa, leges,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She brings destruction, murders kings, slaughters innocents,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="64">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Attulit, orbauit, strauit, soluit, uiolauit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">unbinds treaties, and violates laws.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The original Latin is constructed in the same way as the note suggested on line 40.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="65">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Illa Ioseph iustum Veneris non ignibus ustum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She saw to it that Joseph, who remained unburnt by the fires of Venus,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="66">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Carcere dampnari fecit ferroque ligari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">was condemned to prison and bound in iron chains.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="67">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hec etiam plena rabie truculenta leena</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Similarly, that aggressive whore,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The aggresive whore refers to Salome</p>
								</note>
							 filled with madness,
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="68">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Rex ferus artaret uinclis, gladioque necaret,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">persuaded the savage king to bind in chains</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="69">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fecit ut athletam Domini magnumque prophetam</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">and kill the champion of the Lord, that great prophet:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="70">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et tulit in disco caput illius, unde tremisco.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">then she carried his head on a platter. How I tremble at this!
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The original Latin literally means ‘at which I tremble’.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="71">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fabula Grecorum de libris promit eorum</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The books of the Greeks tell of</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="72">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quomodo regina Cretensis, lege ferina,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">How the Cretan queen,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Pasiphaë.</p>
								</note>
							 following the customs of beasts,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="73">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Carnis ob ardorem nimium, mentisque furorem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Driven by mental madness and an excess of carnal lust,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="74">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Taurum decipit niueum, coituque recepit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Deceived a snow-white bull and copulated with him,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="75">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et peperit natum, taurumque uirumque c[r]eatum:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Eventually giving birth to a son who was half man and half bull.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="76">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Turpi nempe nota res est, per secula nota.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This foul deed, which has been passed down through the centuries, is certainly infamous.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="77">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quis non horrescat, quis non horrenda pauescat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After all, who does not shrink in horror, and fear this repulsive act?</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="78">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dum contra legem nature, faemina regem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That a woman, against the law of nature, should spurn a king</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="79">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Regem formosum, prudentem, deliciosum</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">– And no mere king, but handsome, prudent, and pleasant –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="80">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Despicit, atque fere succumbit plus muliere?</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Only to have sex with a wild beast!</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="81">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina, res fragilis, precio conducta monilis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman, a fragile creature, bribed with the price of a necklace,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="82">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">In populo Danaum, male prodidit Amphiaraum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Betrayed Amphiaraus to the Greek people.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Eriphyle, Amphiaraus’ wife, persuaded him to join a fatal raid. See Ps.-Apollodorus <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca</hi> 3.8.2.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="83">
						<app loc="l83">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sic quoque priuignum uita non funere dignum,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l85">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus also did Phaedra betray Hippolytus, whom she desired unjustly,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="84">
						<app loc="l84">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Usque renitentem patriumque cubile uerentem,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l83">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And who was worthy of life and not of death,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="85">
						<app loc="l85">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Prodidit Ypolitum, contra ius Phedra cupitum.</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l84">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">All because he showed reverence for his father’s bed by resisting her advances.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Cf., among others, Euripides’ <hi rend="italic">Hippolytus</hi>.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="86">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Naso suis libris inscribit quomodo Biblis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Similarly, Naso writes in his books about how Biblis</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="87">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Igne sit illicito male saucia fratre cupito.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Was badly burnt by an illicit flame while she lusted after her brother.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Ov. <hi rend="italic">Met.</hi> 9.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="88">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fraude quidem mira Cynare coiit sua Myrra,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Deceived in an astounding manner, Cinyras slept with his daughter,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="89">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Inque loco [matris] concepit semine [patris].
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>BnF Ms. Lat. 16699, f. 176v reads: ‘Inque loco patris concepit semine matris.’ However this is illogical and likely the result of scribal error. My reading is supported by the critical edition, Van Acker, L. (ed.) (1972). <hi rend="italic">Petri Pictoris Carmina. Nec Non Petri de Sancto Audemaro Librum de Coloribus Faciendis.</hi> CCCM 25. Turnhout (Brepols): 103-116, which is mainly derived from BnF Ms. Lat. 13768.</p>
								</note>
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Who, taking her mother’s place, conceived by the seed of her father.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Ibid., 10.300ff. Cinyras’ daughter was named Myrrha.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="90">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Scilla patri Niso, fatali crine reciso,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In the same vein, Scylla preferred you, Minos, to her father Nisus;
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>See n. 3 – this is Scylla, princess of Megara.</p>
								</note>
							 having cut off that fatal lock of hair,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="91">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Pretulit externum regem, regnumque paternum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She handed her father’s kingdom over to you,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="92">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Moinos, concedit tibi, dum fieri tua credit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As she believed that she would be yours.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="93">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed detestatus tam diri monstra reatus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, detesting the portents of such a dreadful deed,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="94">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et scelus et Scillam metuens, fugis hoc fugis illam.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You avoid both Scylla and her crime, fearing them both.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The abrupt shift to second-person from the original third-person omniscient viewpoint is noteworthy; in so doing, Petrus Pictor does not only address Minos, Scylla’s love interest, but also involves the reader. He therefore rounds off his long invective against women, which has been building up in an increasingly emotional crescendo, by breaking the fourth wall. Moreover, lines 90 to 94 are especially noteworthy as they include a sliding scale of tenses – the ablative absolute (<hi rend="italic">reciso</hi>, ‘having cut off’) gives way to the perfect indicative (<hi rend="italic">pretulit</hi>...credit, ‘preferred...believed’), and then to a perfect participle (<hi rend="italic">detestatus</hi>, ‘detesting’), which in turn yields to a present participle (<hi rend="italic">metuens</hi>, ‘fearing’), culminating finally in the present indicative (<hi rend="italic">fugis</hi>, ‘you avoid’). This gradual rise from the past into the present parallels the aforementioned shift in perspective, and underscores Petrus Pictor’s message about the constant danger which women pose. He suggests that his warnings should not be dismissed as historical and biblical examples from the distant past, but as mere ‘precursors’ (line 29, <hi rend="italic">portenta</hi>) to female wickedness in the reader’s present life.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="95">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De multis quandam referam per saecla notandam,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I shall tell of one woman out of many, who must remain infamous throughout the centuries,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="96">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ut relique discant mulieres, atque tremiscant,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So that other women might tremble at her example and learn</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="97">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ne poscant supra naturam turpia stupra.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Not to seek foul sex which exceeds the bounds of nature.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="98">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Huic fuerat natus, uultu formaque beatus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This woman would have had a son, blessed in face and figure,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="99">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si non obstaret mala sors, miserumque necaret.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Had evil fate not gotten in the way and killed the poor youth:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="100">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed serpens ille, qui nos per carmina mille</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Yet that serpent, who, through a thousand songs,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="101">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Temptat, et intentat, mouet, incitat, atque cruentat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Tempts, attacks, moves, incites, and pollutes us,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="102">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hunc infelicem mox fecit per genetricem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Soon brought ruin upon the son through his own mother.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="103">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Inquid enim genito genetrix, cupiensque cupito,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus she spoke to him,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>While present-tense verbs are used throughout the following narrative, I have translated it using past-tense verbs for two key reasons. Firstly, the historic present is commonly used for narratives involving a series of events, which applies to this case. Secondly, by translating the story of the wicked woman in the past tense, I distinguish it from the frame narrative which takes place in the author’s present time.</p>
								</note>
							 as a lover does to her beloved,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="104">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Inquid Adae seua mulier, simul anguis et Eua:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As the wild woman spoke to Adam, simultaneously both Eve and serpent:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="105">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">“Te uideo, fili, forma prestare uirili,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I see that you, my son, stand out with your manly looks:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="106">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Exornat uultum sua gratia, gloria cultum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Your face is graceful and your dress does you honour.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="107">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">De puero tali, tam pulchro, tam speciali</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, I would rejoice more greatly in such a boy – so beautiful and so special –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="108">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Multum gauderem, tibi si plus matre placerem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If I brought you more pleasure than a mother does,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="109">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Aut plus quam natus faceres michi consociatus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Or if you became more than my son, having joined yourself to me.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="110">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Visus formosus, ridens et luxuriosus</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Your lovely face, smiling and luxuriant,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="111">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et bene pressa foris labra, dulcis plena saporis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And your lips, so suited to the shape of your mouth, full of sweet flavour –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="112">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que te condecorant penitus, penitusque decorant,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">All these wholly adorn you, indeed they do,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Instead of ‘indeed they do’, the Latin (line 112) simply repeats the previous phrase with an inverted word order, which cannot be expressed in English: ‘All these wholly adorn you, adorn you.’</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="113">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Me nimis incendunt, et me, si uis, tibi uendunt.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And set me exceedingly aflame: if you want me, you can have me.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="114">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quapropter, fili, dum flore nites iuuenili,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore, my son, while you are in the flower of your youth,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="115">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dummodo pubescis, primoque calore rigescis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">While you go through puberty and harden with the first flush of passion,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="116">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ne perdas florem tenerum, tantumque decorem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Do not waste your tender prime and all this beauty.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="117">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Immo sit ad cunctas ueneres tua prona uoluntas:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead, incline yourself towards all forms of sexual pleasure,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="118">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Canis confaecta celer aduolat, ecce senecta.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For soon grey old age will come upon you.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="119">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tecum non ludemus, sed tristia cuncta feremus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I am not joking with you, but rather suffering great sorrow at this prospect.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="120">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et quia tiro rudis nescis his ludere ludis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Moreover, since you are but a young initiate, and do not know how to play the games</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="121">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quos amat ipsa Venus et Amor persuadet amenus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Which Venus herself loves and pleasant Love suggests,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="122">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tantum consenti michi, tantum crede docenti:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Simply agree to my proposition and trust in my teaching.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="123">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Illos complebo tecum, iamiamque docebo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I will explore these games with you, teaching you to play again and again.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="124">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ergo meis pare uotis, michi consociare,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Hence, obey my wishes, join yourself to me:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="125">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quicquid agis meum celabo, con[s]cia tecum.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As your accomplice, I shall keep secret all that you do with me.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="126">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tandem turbatus materno famine natus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Disturbed by his mother’s speech, the son</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="127">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Heret, miratur, stupet, et quid agat meditatur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Was lost for words. Flabbergasted and shocked, he thought of what he should do in response.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="128">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Speque bona fortis lacrimis ita fatur abortis:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Eventually, he spoke thus, shedding wasted tears in good faith:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="129">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">“Cara parens, pietate carens, miranda fateris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dear mother, you lack piety in speaking of such unusual matters:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="130">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Criminibus mirabilibus nos perdere queris.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You seek to destroy us with these astounding crimes.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="131">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quod loqueris suadet Venus puer ipse Cupido</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">What you said must have been inspired by Cupid himself, Venus’ son,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="132">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo regitur, quo dirigitur mala cuique libido.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Who controls and directs each person’s wicked lust.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="133">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non ualeo, prohibente Deo, tibi consociari</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I am not able to join myself to you in marriage, since God prohibits it;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="134">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Coniugio, sed amore pio uolo castus amari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead, I wish to love you chastely, with a pious love.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="135">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cognita namque satis series cumsanguinitatis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Our biological bond</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="136">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc scelus accusat graviter, fierique recusat.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Heavily condemns this crime and forbids it from happening;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="137">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hinc gladius regis furit, hinc sententia legis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For if it were to take place, the sword of the King would rage against us, as would the sentence of His law:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="138">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui nichil occultum, cui nullum crimen inultum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nothing is hidden from Him, and no crime goes unpunished.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="139">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mater amabilis, insuperabilis, ad meliora</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">My beloved and irreplaceable mother,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="140">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Te precor erige factaque corrige deteriora.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I beg you to devote yourself to better deeds and correct your mistakes.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="141">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Te Venus horrida flammaque torrida ledit amoris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Although terrible Venus has struck you with the torrid flame of desire</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="142">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vince uiriliter et iace fortiter arma pudoris.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nevertheless conquer it bravely and fight back strongly with the weapons of modesty.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="143">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tela cupidinis atque libidinis ignea frange,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Break down the spears of desire and the fires of lust:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="144">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Percute pectora, perdita tempora, uel modo plange.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Beat your breast and your wretched face,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p><hi rend="italic">‘Perdita tempora’</hi>, literally ‘lost temples’ (i.e. sides of forehead), is a metonymic construction, here used to mean ‘wretched face’.</p>
								</note>
							 or simply weep.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="145">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Stupra, negocia carnis, et ocia uana tremisce,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You should tremble at illicit sex, carnal intercourse, and vain leisure,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="146">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Spiritualia, perpetualia, cuncta cupisce.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And instead long for things which are spiritual, perpetual, and whole.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="147">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Suspice sidera, mater, et infera sperne deorsum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Look at the stars, mother, and spurn whatever is below:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="148">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Queque labencia uel moriencia linque retrorsum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Leave behind all these earthly impulses while they fall and die.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="149">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Scilicet omnia, sunt quasi somnia sunt fugitiva,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">All of these are like fleeting dreams;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="150">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Lapsaque tempore, sunt sine robore, non rediuiua.”</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Lacking strength, they melt away with time and do not return again.”</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="151">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mater ad haec dicta, uelut ictu fulminis icta</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Upon hearing these words, the mother was as if struck by a bolt of lightning:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="152">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Pallet, tabescit, quasi cera sub igne liquescit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She grew pale, drooped, and melted like wax under a flame.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="153">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Defectu mentis, penitus ratione carentis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Due to her weakness of mind and complete lack of reason,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="154">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quod uidet offensam se, quod grauiter reprehensam,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She felt offended and saw that she had been severely reprehended</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="155">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quod castigatur, quod casta manere rogatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And criticised. Moreover, she perceived that she was being asked to remain chaste.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="156">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et, licet ingratum sibi senciat hac uice natum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Although this outcome diminished her affection towards her son,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="157">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non tamen errori caedit, ceptoque furori,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She did not give in to error and carry out her insane plan.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="158">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hunc sed in occulto male saucia tempore multo</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead, she spent a long time nursing her wounds in secret,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="159">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Impetit, insequitur, nec eo pro uelle potitur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">All the while seeking her son and making advances on him, whom she was nevertheless unable to obtain according to her wishes.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="160">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fertque graues penas, Veneris nec stringit habenas,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She suffered heavy penalties and failed to control her desire,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="161">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dumque reluctatur Veneri, luctando grauatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">But rather felt herself to be all the more burdened while fighting against it.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="162">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nec sua compescit mala, sed magis acta calescit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Moreover, she did not put an end to her evils, but rather grew hotter as she acted:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="163">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">At postquam cernit quia filius hanc male spernit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After she saw that her son wholly despised her lust,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="164">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quod pereunt uerba, perit et sua messis in herba,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As evidenced by her wasted words and her inability to harvest the fruits of her labour,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="165">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fraudibus armatur, studet ut iuuenis perimatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She girt herself with treachery and tried to destroy the young man.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="166">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hac igitur causa, maius scelus ob scelus ausa,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Consequently, driven to greater audacity by her existing crimes,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="167">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iudicis ad sedem currit, flens introit edem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She ran into the courthouse and entered it while weeping.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="168">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Accusat natum, iacit in quem dira reatum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She accused her son and brought dreadful charges against him,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="169">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dicens: “Huc, patres, oculos huc uertite, matres,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saying: “Look here, fathers, mothers,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="170">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vosque, pii nati, patribus bene semper amati,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And you, good beloved sons,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="171">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quos non incestus Veneris contaminat aestus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Whom the incestuous heat
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p><hi rend="italic">‘Incestus...aestus’</hi> would typically be translated as ‘impure heat’, but due to the specific context in which this phrase is uttered – an accusation of incest – I have chosen the adjective ‘incestuous’.</p>
								</note>
							 of Venus has not contaminated:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="172">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Currite, deflete mecum, dampnate, dolete.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Run to my side, cry with me, curse my son, and feel my pain.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="173">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Dedecus illatum michi, monstriferumque reatum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I am the victim of an indignity and a monstrous crime.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="174">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Rem referam fedam, pudet edere, sed tamen edam,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It shames me to tell you about this sordid matter, but nevertheless I shall speak.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="175">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vnde querar refero, minor est, querimonia uero.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I barely know how to begin my complaint, but here it is.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="176">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Est puer insanus michi, lubricus, atque prophanus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I have a demented son who is lustful and profane.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="177">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quem peperisse pudet me, cum mea turpia nudet,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I am ashamed of having given birth to him, since he strips me naked;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="178">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quem doleo natum, male cum uideam fatuatum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Oh, how I regret that he was born, since I see that he has gone thoroughly mad.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="179">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic pecudum more, materno captus amore,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He is a beast; captured by love for his own mother,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="180">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cum male seuiret nuper, matremque nequiret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He has been acting savagely towards me. Since he could not win his mother over</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="181">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Donis oblatis, precibus quoque multiplicatis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Through gifts and unceasing entreaties,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="182">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vincere, luctantis contra, stuprumque negantis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">While I fought against him and turned my face from his lust</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="183">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ora, cruentauit manibus, uestes lacerauit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He befouled me with his hands, tore my clothes apart,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="184">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sic et sic egit, sic me ferus ille subegit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Did this and that, and pushed me down – the beast! – like this,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="185">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non tamen oppressit, quia me clamante recessit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">But he did not possess me, for I shouted and forced him to retreat.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="186">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ergo Deo gratus iudex prudensque senatus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">May the judge, upon whom God smiles, and the wise assembly</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="187">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Pertractent secum quid sit de talibus aequum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Determine among themselves a proportionate penalty for these acts:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="188">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quorum censura pollent ciuilia iura,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After all, it is their judgement which grants the law its power,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="189">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Per quos maiorem res publica sumpsit honorem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And it is through them that the city gains greater honour.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="190">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Patrum magestas uilescit et urbis honestas,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The majesty of the elders and the honour of the city</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="191">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ni melioratae fuerint cause uiciate.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Will be cheapened, unless injured parties receive amends.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="192">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non uni tantum fit dedecus hoc michi: quantum</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This disgrace does not affect me alone, but</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="193">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Innumeris turbis, que presunt menibus urbis.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Taints all the uncountable crowds who flock to the walls of this city.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="194">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nulla mei pietas nati, non forma, uel etas.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">My son has neither piety nor good looks, nor does his age excuse him.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="195">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quamlibet aetatem moueat, precor, ad pietatem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Even though he might use that excuse to win your mercy,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p> It is tempting to translate <hi rend="italic">‘pietatem’</hi> as ‘your piety’, but <hi rend="italic">‘pietas’</hi> really means <hi rend="italic">‘misericordia’</hi> (‘mercy’) in this case.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="196">
						<app loc="l196">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Stupra sed obscena compescant uindice pena,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l197">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I urge you all, whether great or small, whether young or old,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="197">
						<app loc="l197">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Parui, maiores, iuuenes simul, et seniores.”</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l196">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To check these foul crimes of lust with a vengeful penalty.” </rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="198">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sic accusatus puer, et mox ante uocatus</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus the youth, who had been summoned a short while ago, found himself accused.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="199">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Audit clamorem matris, lesumque pudorem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He heard his mother’s cries and perceived her lack of modesty.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This is more literally expressed as ‘her broken modesty’, or ‘her damaged modesty’.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="200">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Stat, silet ad uerba nec acerbis reddit acerba,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He stood in silence, and did not counter her bitter words with his own.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="201">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Immo uerecundus, lacrimabilis et pudibundus</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead, he behaved in a reverent, doleful, and modest manner,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="202">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vultum preclarum riuis rorat lacrimarum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Inundating his most handsome face with rivers of tears.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="203">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Seque reum pingit, et vultum crimine tinguit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He portrayed himself as the guilty party and tainted his own face with the charge,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="204">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Malens torqueri, quam matris probra fateri,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For he preferred to undergo torture rather than to speak ill of his mother,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="205">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Malens dampnari, quam crimine commaculari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And to suffer condemnation rather than to be stained with such an offence.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="206">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cumque diu fleret suspirans, atque doleret</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He wept for a long time, sighing all the while, equally troubled</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="207">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tam matris sortem, quam uicinam sibi mortem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">By his mother’s eternal fate and his own approaching death.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="208">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Protinus, allatis annalibus et recitatis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The legal records of the city were brought in and read out loud.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="209">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Pena reperta datur, ut in amnem proiciatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">A suitable punishment was found for the crime: the offender was to be thrown into the river.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="210">
						<app loc="l210">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ergo miser tandem mortem subiturus eandem,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l211">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As both the judge and the mother urged the crowd on,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="211">
						<app loc="l211">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iudicis urgente monitu, genetrice petente,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l212">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They seized, dragged, grabbed, and scratched</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="212">
						<app loc="l212">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vndique raptatur, trahitur, premitur, laceratur.</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l210">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The poor youth who was about to suffer this very death.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="213">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et sic dampnatus, postremo precipitatus</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus condemned, he was finally thrown</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="214">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Gurgitis in fundum, subiit baptisma secundum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Into the bottom of the river and underwent a second baptism.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="215">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">At scelus occultum tandem non cessit inultum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, the mother’s hidden crime did not go unpunished.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="216">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam scelerum uindex Dominus, iusti pius index,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The Lord, who takes vengeance for sins and bears pious witness on behalf of the just,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="217">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vt foret incaestus matris populo manifestus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Revealed her incest to the people.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="218">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fulminibus crebris missis, ortisque tenebris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sending down torrents of lightning and raising up the shadows,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="219">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vrbem, carnificem, puerum, pueri genetricem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He incinerated the city, thwarted the executioner,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="220">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vssit, turbauit, saluauit, dilacerauit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Saved the youth, and tore the mother into pieces.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The original Latin is constructed in the same way as the note suggested on line 40.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="221">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">O nimium fortis mala femina, femina mortis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">O wicked and over-impudent woman – woman of death indeed –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="222">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eligit ante mori, quam stulto cedat amori.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Who chose to die instead of giving up her fatuous love!</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="223">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mauult sectari stuprum, quam casta beari,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She preferred to seek out illicit sex rather than to be praised for chastity,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="224">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Mauult ulcisci male, quam mater pia dici.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And to be punished severely instead of being praised as a pious mother.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="225">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Infelix mater, mala mater, nec modo mater,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Wretched mother, wicked mother, and not even a true mother:
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p><hi rend="italic">‘Nec modo mater’</hi> literally means ‘and not only a mother’ or even ‘no mere mother’, but these translations do not convey Pictor’s negative tone.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="226">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam, quoniam natum male perdidit amne necatum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Having drowned her own son,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="227">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Suppliciis dignis, celestis torruit ignis.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She burned with the just punishment of celestial fire.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="228">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina terribilis draco, trux lupa, bestia uilis.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman is a terrible serpent,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>In Classical Latin, <hi rend="italic">‘draco’</hi> denotes a large snake; in Medieval Latin it may well mean ‘dragon’. However, as Petrus Pictor has utilised snake metaphors throughout to describe women – which corresponds to Biblical imagery –  I would rather err on the safe side and translate <hi rend="italic">‘draco’</hi> as ‘serpent’.</p>
								</note>
							 an aggressive she-wolf, a vile beast.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="229">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cum tristis diram leuiter prorumpit in iram,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That miserable creature bursts into fatal rage at the smallest provocation,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="230">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non cito pacatur, non ante reconciliatur</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And cannot be appeased quickly; on the contrary, she is never reconciled</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="231">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam paena multa, sibi uis illata, sit ulta.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Until she has avenged herself through violence.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="232">
						<app loc="l232">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hanc si ludentem male, uerbaque uana loquentem</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l233">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If her husband should, on some occasion, restrain her with a sharp scolding</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="233">
						<app loc="l233">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eius uir uerbis aliquando cohercet acerbis,</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l232">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">From clowning around and babbling vain words,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="234">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Siue leui terret uirga, ne turpiter erret,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Or even deter her from committing foul misdeeds with a stick,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="235">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ilico facta dolens, et ei succumbere nolens,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She will henceforth take offence and refuse to sleep with him.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Petrus Pictor utilises the present tense throughout; nevertheless, I have employed the future tense to preserve the emphasis on cause-and-effect in this passage, the cause being the punishment (stick, scolding) and the effect being murder (by poisoning).</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="236">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Plorat, tristatur, suspiria dat, meditatur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She will cry, upset herself, sigh, and think of</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="237">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Qualiter ut uita careat, paret huic achonita.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">How to deprive him of his life. To this end she will prepare him some monkshood.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This sentence might seem incongruous with the following one, which describes other sources of poison; therefore it is best to take <hi rend="italic">achonita</hi>, ‘monkshood’, as an umbrella term for all poisons.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="238">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tandem serpentum quesita uenena nocentum</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, having obtained the venom of poisonous snakes</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="239">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Necnon herbarum uirus graue mortiferarum</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the deadly toxin of death-bringing plants,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="240">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Conficit in potum, complens de coniuge uotum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She will mix them into a drink and thus fulfill her plan against her husband.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="241">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hoc ita sublato sponso, uix et tumulato,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Even while he is still warm in his grave,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="242">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Post malefictarum teneros questus lacrimarum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She will put on tender displays of crocodile tears,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="243">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Coniuncx quesiti subito cupit esse mariti,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And seek to become another man’s wife.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="244">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et uelut inuita negat hoc prius, usque petita.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, she will feign unwillingness until she obtains a strong suit;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="245">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ast ubi suadentum rem, perstat cura parentum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then, when her parents insist on the marriage</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="246">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nec contradici debere fatentur amici,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And her friends persuade her not to refuse him,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="247">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Laeticiae plenas uotorum laxat habenas,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She will gladly give in to happiness</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="248">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Menteque iocunda, sponso sit sponsa secula.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And transform herself into a worldly wife for her new husband</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="249">
						<app loc="l249">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quodque propinauit primo, quem perfida strauit,</lem>
						</app>
						<app lloc="l250">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Yet if he proves difficult, he will drink the same potion</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="250">
						<app loc="l250">
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si sit uir durus, erit alter idem bibiturus.</lem>
						</app>
						<app loc="l249">
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That she served her first husband, whom she treacherously murdered.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="251">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina formosa nimis esset res preciosa,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">A beautiful woman is precious beyond all description</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="252">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si male nil cuperet, si sponso fida maneret.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If she has no bad intentions and remains faithful to her husband,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="253">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed, quod abhorrendum nimis est cunctisque pudendum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">But it should be a source of horror and shame to all women</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="254">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vix habet ulla fidem, qua credi possit eidem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">That none of them can be trusted.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="255">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que quo diligitur magis, hoc grauior reperitur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The more a woman is loved, the more troublesome she becomes;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="256">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quo magis ornatur, magis inde superba notatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Similarly, she grows all the more arrogant as a result of rich ornaments.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="257">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nescit maiorem, nescit se ferre minorem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As a result, she does not recognise her superior, nor does she fulfill her inferior role in an appropriate manner.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="258">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Par
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>BnF Ms. Lat. 16699, f. 177v reads: ‘Pars quoque vincta pari’, but this is illogical and should read ‘par’, which is the preferred reading of Van Acker (1972).</p>
								</note>
							 quoque iuncta pari, cupit impariter dominari.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Although she is joined to an equal in marriage, she wants to take an unequal share of power.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="259">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Res optatiua nimis est, animeque nociua.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Woman is too desirable and thus harms the soul.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="260">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Illius uultus, bene conditus, et bene cultus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Through her well-formed and well-groomed face,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="261">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Allicit, innectit iuuenes, sua sub iuga flectit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She attracts and ensnares young men; she enslaves them</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="262">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Apte ludendo, psallendo, uana loquendo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">By playing games, performing music, and chatting about empty matters.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="263">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Que dum spectari, dum se presentit amari,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When she perceives that she is being watched and admired,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="264">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Querit maiorem membris augere decorem.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She seeks to enhance her physical beauty:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="265">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tunc pingit uisum gratum, format bene risum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Consequently, she paints her face beautifully, sets her mouth into a smile,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="266">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vestibus ornatur nitidis, gemmis honeratur,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Dresses herself in shining garments, and weighs herself down with jewels</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="267">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Floribus innectit crines, et se bene pectit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She weaves flowers into her hair and arranges it in a becoming manner,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="268">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Stricta succiungit se zona, basia fingit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And also girds herself with a tightened belt. She performs the sort of kisses</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="269">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Qualia uelle putat iuuenes, iuuenesque salutat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Which she expects will please young men, 
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p><hi rend="italic">‘Fingere’</hi>, here translated as ‘perform’, has a dual meaning which is also applicable to these verses on the trickery which accompanies seduction: it can also mean ‘to invent’.</p>
								</note>
							 greets them warmly,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="270">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fertque manu flores, et dulces cantat amores.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Carries flowers in her hands, and sings about sweet romance.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="271">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si uero nescit cantare, loquendo capescit</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, even if she cannot sing, she uses her speech</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="272">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cor auditoris, quod uulnere languet amoris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">To capture her listener’s heart, which throbs with the wound of love.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="273">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Factaque uenalis, uenatio demonialis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Selling herself to him, hunting him like a demon,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="274">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Prostat, ut incaestum querat de corpore questum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She incites him into seeking illicit pleasure from her body.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="275">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iupiter
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>The scribe glosses ‘amator’, ‘lover’, for ‘Iupiter’.</p>
								</note>
							 hanc aliquis oculis dum cernit iniquis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Some Jupiter, armed with his impure gaze,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="276">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sic incedentem, iuuenes sic allicientem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Sees her behaving in this manner and attracting young men;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="277">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vultu candenti nitidam, cultuque decenti,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He notices the shine of her pale face and her decorous dress.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="278">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eius uexatur mox ignibus, et meditatur:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Immediately, he feels himself singed by fire, and considers</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="279">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Qualiter hanc Ledam celerem faciat sibi predam,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">How he should quickly take possession of this new Leda.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="280">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam prece pretemptat, donis persepe frequentat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He seduces her with entreaties and showers her in gifts,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="281">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vt sua postposito uelit esse puella marito.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So that she might give herself to him behind her husband’s back.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="282">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sed male securus coniuncx de coniuge durus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nevertheless, her strict husband begins to feel insecure,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="283">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam sic prostantem, sic cernit ubique uagantem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As he sees her offering herself freely and wandering all about.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="284">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Arguit etatem teneram, puerae leuitatem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">On account of her young age and her youthful levity,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="285">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Inque domo, tenere flentem cogit residere,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He forces his tearful wife to stay at home.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="286">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vallatamque seris, custodibus atque seueris,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He walls her in with lock and key and assigns her care to austere guards,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="287">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non sinit exire thalamis, ludosque subire.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Forbidding her from leaving the marital home and entering into her usual games.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="288">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam quia custodit, non diligit ille sed odit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">However, because he guards her, he ceases to love her:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="289">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Odit et infestat, et ut hec sit adultera prestat.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead he hates her and attacks her, treating her as an adulteress.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="290">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui custos durus nequid aut obsistere murus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In any case, nothing - not a strict guard, not walls,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="291">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non iugis pena, sed nec sera, siue catena,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Not punishments, bars, or chains -</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="292">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quin faciat secum, si uult, colludere mechum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Can stop her from taking on a lover:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="293">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">O male seruatus thesaurus sic uiolatus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">O badly-preserved treasure, thus violated,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="294">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Qui dum seruatur, furem uocat ut rapiatur.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Which encourages a thief to steal it even while it is being guarded!</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="295">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Atque quod obscenum nimis est, querens alienum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">What is more, it is extremely obscene that a wife, while seeking another man,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="296">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sponsa suum prodit sponsum, contempnit et odit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Should betray, despise, and hate her own husband.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="297">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ergo monstriferae metuens, homo, dampna Chimere,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore, reader, fearing the injuries of that monstrous Chimera,
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>In Greek mythology, the Chimera is a fire-breathing hybrid creature. <hi rend="italic">‘Monstrifera’</hi> is more literally translated as ‘monster-bringing’ but the Chimera, which symbolises Woman, does not usher in other beasts: it is monstrous in itself.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="298">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sis exemplorum memor hic tibi propositorum;</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Keep the aforementioned examples in mind.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="299">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nuptas matronas, ad plurima crimina pronas</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Remember to avoid married women, who are given to many offences,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="300">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Donaque prebentes uiduas, in amore furentes,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As well as love-crazed widows offering gifts.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This verse strongly echoes Verg. <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi> 2.49: <hi rend="italic">‘Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes’</hi> (‘I fear the Greeks, even bearing gifts’).</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="301">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Necnon uirgineas uitare memento choreas,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Leave dancing maidens alone,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="302">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Illarum mammas teneras fugiens quasi flammas.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And flee their tender breasts as if they were made of flame.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="303">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hostibus his ternis, ut prescriptum bene cernis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">These three types of foes – as the preceding verses indicate –</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="304">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Incentiuorum crescunt fomenta malorum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Incite and encourage the growth of many evils.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="305">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Has fuge serpentes uirus letale uomentes,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Avoid therefore these serpents who spit out fatal venom,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="306">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Has hostes uita, ne te fugiat tua uita.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And flee these enemies, lest you should lose your life.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="307">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Claustra tue mentis signato meis documentis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Seal the gates of your mind with my examples,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="308">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ne liget illecebris uariis te fraus muliebris.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So that you will not find yourself entangled by the various traps of female deceit.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="309">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quem semel illa ligat, curis sine fine fatigat,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Once a woman has trapped a man, she will harass him with unending cares;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="310">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quem sub se flectit, seruili compede nectit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Once she has forced him into subservience, she will shackle him into servitude.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="311">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Res ita plena dolis non est sub sidere solis</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There is nothing at all under the sun which is more filled with tricks</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="312">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Rebus in innumeris, uelut est animus mulieris.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Than the soul of Woman.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="313">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">O quam fallaci modulo studioque sagaci,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">O, with such cunning means and keen enthusiasm</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="314">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Stultos comprendit iuuenes ubi retia tendit!</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Does she seize foolish youths and scoop them up in her net!</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="315">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fraudis multimodos uersuto pectore nodos</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In her trickery, she twists knots of all kinds within her chest,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="316">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Voluit, et euoluit, soluit, ligat atque resoluit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Untwists them, unties them, ties them again, then once more unties them:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="317">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vt male seducat miseros, et ad infera ducat.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She does all this in order to seduce wretched souls and lead them to Hell.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="318">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quisquis ei cedit, nec ab eius amore recedit,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore, whoever yields to Woman and does not give up his love</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="319">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tandem falletur, tandem laqueo capietur;</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Will find himself deceived and caught in a noose.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p><hi rend="italic">‘Laqueus’</hi> can also mean ‘trap’ more generally.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="320">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cuius amor, uisus, caro mollis, basia, risus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The love, sight, soft flesh, kisses, smiles,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="321">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Alloquium, tactus, uariique libidinis actus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Conversation, touch, lustful acts,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="322">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vox etiam lena, laqueus sunt atque catena,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And whorish voice of Woman are all nooses, chains,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="323">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Et graue tormentum quorumlibet insipientum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And heavy torments for the unwise.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="324">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Felix est supere quisquis ualet ista cauere,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He who can avoid these things is truly fortunate;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="325">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quem non haec tangit contagio, non furor angit.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For madness does not disturb the man who remains uncontaminated by Woman.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="326">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hic infelicem probo quisquis amat meretricem,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I say truly, whoever loves a whore is most unfortunate indeed;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="327">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cuius amor dirus, tandem pungens quasi uirus,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For her love is fatal and stings like venom,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="328">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sub specie mellis distillat pocula fellis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she prepares a cup of bitterness in the guise of honey.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="329">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Cuius amor nex est, caro uermis, gloria fex est,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Her love is a chain, her flesh is vermin, her glory comprises the dregs of the earth;</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="330">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Verba, lenis uentus, fumus decor, umbra iuventus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Her words are a soft breeze, and yet her smokescreen of beauty is but the shadow of youth.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="331">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iam calamo fesso, que sit mala femina cesso</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">My pen is exhausted;
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This is the literal meaning of <hi rend="italic">‘calamo fesso’</hi>, but Pictor of course does not refer to the inanimate pen, but to himself: ‘I am exhausted’.</p>
								</note>
							 I shall now stop writing about the wicked Woman.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="332">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Scribere. Quod scripsi minus est quam congruit ipsi.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nevertheless, what I have managed to set down falls far short of Woman’s fair share of censure.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="333">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Si michi Nasonis, si detur lingua Catonis,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Even if I should receive the tongue of Ovid or that of Cato,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="334">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Claraque linguarum facundia magniloquarum,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the famed skill of linguistic eloquence,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="335">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Non tamen exsoluo uerbis, scriptisque reuoluo,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I would not be able to outline in words or describe in my verses</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="336">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam sit uersuta, quam perfida, quam sit acuta,</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">How wily, treacherous, keen,</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="337">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Quam sit dampnosa mala femina, quamue dolosa.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Dangerous, and sneaky a wicked woman is.</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="338">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nesciat hoc nemo, quod carmine signo supremo:</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Let no one be unaware of the following truth, with which I shall round off my poem:</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
					<l n="339">
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Femina rara bona, sed que bona digna corona.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">‘Rarely is a woman good, but a good woman is worthy of a crown.’</rdg>
						</app>
					</l>
		</body>
	</text>>
</TEI>
