<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>‘On Roman Origins of the Lithuanians’ <hi rend="italic">from the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia</hi></title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Alana Felton</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Alana Felton</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>Compiled in the 1520s, the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia (henceforth Chronicle) is an original composition of unknown authorship. Aristocratic in tone, the Chronicle includes a description of the legendary origins of the Lithuanian princes and nobles: that they descended from Roman patricians who, under the leadership of Prince Palemon, fled the tyranny of Emperor Nero. It was likely compiled at the court of the powerful magnate Albertas Goštautus while he was the Voivode (governor) of Vilnius and Grand Chancellor of Lithuania from 1522 to 1539. Most scholars agree that the Chronicle’s focus on Lithuania’s noble origins suggests that it was used in the 16th century as a historical justification for Lithuania’s autonomy in its union with Poland and to distinguish Lithuania from neighboring Slavic realms.</p>
				<p>The Polish historian Jan Długosz (1415-1480) was the first to write in a work of history the idea that the Lithuanians descended from Roman patricians in his Chronicles of the Kingdom of Poland. It is likely that the anonymous author of the Chronicle found this information in Długosz’s work and developed a detailed and dynamic narrative of the foundation of the Lithuanian state. The Chronicle with an enumeration of the Roman emperors from Augustus to Nero, and attributes the flight of Palemon, the legendary founder of Lithuania and Nero’s relative, to Nero’s tyranny. It describes how Palemon, along with four well-known noble Roman families by the names of Centaurus, Columna, Rose and Ursini, and five hundred others, sailed to Lithuania in search of a safe place to live. The remainder of the text provides vivid descriptions of the great beauty and abundance of what would become Lithuanian lands and describes how names were chosen for important cities. It also provides a genealogical record of Palemon’s progeny and founded important cities and regions in Lithuania. In fact, the text credits Palemon’s son Kernus with giving the Lithuanians their name by combining the words riverside “litus” and pipe “tuba” which became “Litustuba” in Latin and “Litva” in Ruthenian. </p>
				<p>The Chronicle is ambiguous about the temporal and geographical settings of the events it describes. Besides the year of Christ’s birth and mention of Palemon’s flight during Nero’s reign, no dates or indicators of time are provided. Moreover, Palemon, a figure from antiquity, is anachronistically tied to prominent Roman families from the Middle Ages. Additionally, many of the cities and other locations in the text cannot be linked to existing 16th-century locations. These ambiguities reflect the legendary nature of the Chronicle’s narrative and suggest that its author intended to emphasize the antiquity of the Lithuanian state and its nobility. </p>
				<p>Scholars today argue that the Chronicle’s portrayal of Lithuanians’ ancient Roman roots speaks to the 16th-century Lithuanian nobility’s historical and political consciousness. By linking the 16th-century Lithuanian state to Roman culture and history, the Chronicle’s author(s) influenced future official state historiography and political doctrine, as well as conceptions of collective identity. In fact, Uladzimir Kananovich (see Further Reading below) has argued that the Chronicle speaks more to the political and cultural reality of the 16th century than to the much earlier period it describes. Some of the names of rulers and noble families mentioned in the Chronicle belong to well-known noblemen of the 15th and 16th centuries, suggesting the author(s)’ intent to legitimize contemporary authority figures by connecting them to historical legendary leaders. Therefore, the Chronicle can be read as providing a history not only of the Lithuanian state but of regional noble communities in power in the 16th century. </p>
				<p>The text used for this translation is taken from the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia, a 16th-century compilation written in Ruthenian from the Świdzinski Miscellany of Lithuanian Chronicles, once part of the Krasiński Collection. Unfortunately, the manuscript itself burned during World War II; however, paleographic descriptions by Evfimii Karskii and Franciczek Pułaski provide necessary information about its contents, while individual texts, including The Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia, were published by Afanasii Fedorovich Bychkov in 1893 and later in Polnoe sobranie russkikh letopisei. Two versions of the Chronicle are known: the shorter version was witnessed by the lost Krasiński copy and the longer version by the Alshevskii, Archeographic, Patriarch, Rumiantsev (Moscow, Russian State Library, Collection 37, № 435), and Tikhonravov copies.</p>
				<p>The manuscript used in this translation represents the second redaction of the Chronicle, in which the account of the Roman descent of the Lithuanians first appears. The Chronicle is written in Ruthenian, the written language of the ethnic East Slavic population of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Poland. This area, generally referred to as Ruthenia, corresponds to portions of modern-day Lithuania, Belarus, Ukraine, Poland, and southern Russia. </p>
				<p>Frost, Robert. "Æque Principaliter." In The Oxford History of Poland-Lithuania: Volume I: The Making of the Polish-Lithuanian Union, 1385-1569, Oxford University Press, 2015, pp. 405-423.</p>
				<p>History of Lithuanian Chronicles and the socio-political situation in which they were written</p>
				<p>Shpakau, Miraslau. “Ideological Implications of the Earliest Lithuanian Version of the Roman Myth.” Białoruskie Zeszyty Historyczne, 2018, t. 49, pp. 7-24.</p>
				<p>Analysis of the expression of regional identity as presented in the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia</p>
				<p>Tolochko, Oleksiy. “Belarusian-Lithuanian Chronicles.” In Encyclopedia of the Medieval Chronicle, edited by Graeme Dunphy and Cristian Bratu. Accessed May 28, 2021. doi:http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/2213-2139_emc_SIM_00293. </p>
				<p>General information about 15th and 16th century Belarusian-Lithuanian Chronicles.</p>
				<p>Verkholantsev, Julia. “Ruthenia (Lithuania-Rus).” Europe: A Literary History, 1348 – 1418, edited by David Wallace, vol. 2, Oxford University Press, 2016, pp. 420-439. </p>
				<p>Historical background of Ruthenian language and literature </p>
				<p>Wilson, Andrew. “Ruthenia.” In Belarus: The Last Dictatorship in Europe, Yale University Press, 2011, pp. 33-47. </p>
				<p>Brief history of Ruthenian language and culture</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>A chronicle version according to the Swidziński Miscellany of Lithuanian Chronicles, Biblioteka Ordynacji Krasińskich (Krasiński Collection) # 82, ff. 21-39v. (Pułaski 1915, 76-78).</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">СПИСОКЪ ГРАФА КРАСИНСКАГО. Б. ЛѢТОПИСЕЦЬ ВЕЛИКОГО КНѦЗЬСТВА ЛИТОВЪСКОГО И ЖОМОИЦЬСКОГО.</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Register of Count Krasinskii: Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"‘On Roman Origins of the Lithuanians’ from the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>The transcription accompanying this translation is derived from the Chronicle of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Samogitia from the Świdzinski Miscellany of Lithuanian Chronicles as printed in the Polnoe sobranie russkikh letopisei izdannoe po vysochaishemu poveleniiu Arkheograficheskogo komiccieiu: Tom semnadtsatyi: Zapadnarusskiia letopisi in 1917. It has been created according to the following criteria: All transcribed words rendered in italics in the transcription in Polnoe sobranie russkikh letopisei have been reverted to superscript letters that are indicated with a “titlo” ( ҃ ). The original punctuation has been maintained to introduce modern readers to medieval composition and reading style. The English translation uses punctuation and spacing in accordance with modern notions of sentence and paragraph composition. Common English spellings of the names of peoples and locations are used when known and transliterated otherwise.</p> 

					<p>The translator would like to thank Professor Julia Verkholantsev for her substantial assistance in translating this excerpt. </p>
					
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Сталосѧ єсть воплощеє сн҃а Бж҃ьего ѿ ст҃го Дх҃а зъ блвеное дв҃ци прчтое Мр҃іи ѿ почакꙋ сотворенiа всего свѣта. лѣта пѧтысѧного пѧсотного двѧцать шестого.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The incarnation of the Son of God by the Holy Spirit from the Blessed Virgin, most pure Mary, happened in the year five thousand, five hundred and twenty-six from the beginning of the Creation of the entire world.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ѡно чау паство Риское. было пре цесаре  Авгꙋсто. которы иже не токо ѡдномоу Римꙋ. але и всемоу свѣтꙋ панова.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At that time, the Roman Empire was under Caesar Augusts, who ruled not only Rome, but also the entire world.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ꙗко вышеи писано чау цесарьства Авгꙋстова. сн҃ъ Бж҃їи нароⷣ лсѧ. а чау Тивириа цесарѧ второго по Авгꙋсте на кртѣ вонꙋю моукꙋ принѧ длѧ збавеꙗ. и ѿкꙋпеꙗ рожаю члв҃чего.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As is written above, in the time of Caesar Augustus’ rule the Son of God was born, and at the time of Caesar Tiberius, the second after Augustus, He accepted voluntary suffering on the cross for the deliverance and redemption of the human race.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">за которого  Тивириѧ цесарѧ. вси рѣчи и пррчества напонивши по востанїю из мр҃твы встоупилъ на н҃бо и селъ на правици Бг҃а ѡц҃а. ѿколе  дн҃ѧ соуного маеть прїити соудити живыхъ и мр҃твы и ѿдати комоудо подлѫгъ заслоуги его.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At the time of Caesar Tiberius, He [Christ], having fulfilled all sayings and prophecies, entered into heavan and sat at the right hand of God the father, whence on the Day of Judgement He will come to judge the living and the dead to to give to each according to his merit.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а по см҃рти Твириѧ цесарѧ. былъ цесаремъ Гаиѡсъ. по Гаиюсе. Клавди. по Клавдїи цртвова сн҃ъ его Нерѡ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And after the death of Caesar Tiberius, Gaius was caesar, after Gaius was Claudius, and after Claudius, his son Nero reigned.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">которыи  Неронъ былъ панъ ѡкрꙋтныи а невъставичныи власнꙋю макоу свою и докторѧ своего навышьшого. своею рѫкою заби бе кождое причины. ѡ см҃рть приправилъ. и некоко кро мѣсто Риское. каза  запаливати. а ни длѧ чого толко длѧ то. и бы сѧ томоу дивова. а потехꙋ с того мевалъ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This Nero was a cruel and temperamental ruler who killed his own mother and his highest tutor with his own hand, murdered them without any reason, and several times ordered the city of Rome to be set on fire just so that he could watch it and entertain himself.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и кн҃жата и панѧто Риски. и шлѧтамъ и всеꙋ поспоствꙋ кривды и втиснеꙗ великиѧ чини.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And on the dukes and Roman nobles and gentry and all the common people he inflicted great injustice and oppression.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">длѧ чого  всѧки поданы его. длѧ великого ѡкрꙋтества его и невъставичности не бы нихто певенъ а ни бепече. не толко именеи. альбо скарбовъ але и здороꙗ своего.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And because of that, due to his great cruelty and temperamentality, there was no one among all his subjects who was sure and safe, neither about their property and belongings, nor their life.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а такъ многые ѡпꙋскаючи имеꙗ а скабы свои втекаⷧ ꙵ҇до ромаиты земль наследѫючи справеливости покоѧ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And so, many people, abandoning their properties and belongings, fled to other lands in search of justice and peace.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">где  ѡдно кже Риское имене Полемо. которыи же цесарꙋ Неронꙋ бы кровныи. забралъсѧ з жоною и з дѣтми и скарбы своими и подъданными своими</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And there, one Roman duke by the name of Polemon, who was a relative of Caesar Nero, gathered his wife, children, belongings, and subjects.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">с которы жо кн҃жете собралосѧ пѧсо шлѧхты з жонами и  дѣтми. и  многыми люми.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And with this duke there gathered five-hundred gentry with their wives, children, and many domestics.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="3">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и взеши с собою ѡдного ѡстронома и пошли в корабле море по заходѫ слн҃ца хотеⷱ  собе знаити на земли месцо слоушное. и где бы мели поселити. а мешкати с покоемъ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And having taken with them an astronomer<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>A celestial navigator.</p></note>,  they left by sea to the west, desiring to find for themselves a suitable place on earth where they could settle and live in peace.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а с тыⷨ ꙵ҇ шлѧхты чотыри были рожаи навышшие имене Китоврасы Колюны Рожи Оургы</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And among those noblemen, four were of the highest birth, named: the Centaurus, the Columns-Colonna, the Rose and the Urs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а та ѡни не малыи ча по морю ходечи пришли Межизеского морѧ. и дошли до реки до Шꙋма.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And so, travelling by sea for a long time, they came to the Mediterranean Sea and reached the Shum River.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и тою рекою Шоумою в море ѡкиꙗнъ. и море  ѡкиꙗно  дошли до оусть. и где река Немо впадывае. в море ѡкиꙗнъ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And by that Shum River into the Ocean Sea, and by the Ocean Sea they came to the mouth of the River Neman, where it flows into the Ocean Sea.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="4">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">потом пошли Немном оу верхъ. ажь в море зовемое Малое которое называетсѧ. море Неновое. а с тое причины тоє море Немновое называетсѧ. ижь в тое море впадаєть Немо дванацами оустьи и кодое зоветсѧ свои имене Скиꙗ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then they travelled up the Neman all the way to the sea called Little, also called the Neman Sea because the River Neman flows into it by twelve mouths (one is called by its own name, Skilia).  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и пошли ты оустьемъ оу верхъ и дошли цѣлого Немна. где вжо ѡнъ самъ во ѡдно месци тече весь</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And they went up this estuary and covered the whole of the Neman, where it already flows undivided in one place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="5">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а оу верхь Неномъ пошли до реки Дꙋбисы где  вшеши в тꙋю рекꙋ Дꙋбисꙋ. и на нею нашли горы высокие. И на ѡны гора ровнины великие и дꙋбровы на ѡны гора ровнины великие и дꙋбровы  роскошные. и ромаитое ѡѳитости напонены роного рожаю. звере то есть напервеи. тоуровъ зоубреи лосеи єленеи сернъ рыеи кꙋниць лисиць бѣлокъ горнастаевъ ласиць. и ины ромаиты рожаевъ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And they went up the Neman to the Dubysa River, where, having entered into that Dubysa River, they found tall mountains overlooking it, and, on these mountains, great plains and magnificent forests, and a various abundance of different kinds of animals, above all, bulls, bison, moose, deer, antelopes, lynx, martens, foxes, squirrels, ermine and weasels and other different species.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и тꙋ те в река великѫю объѳїто рыбъ непосполиты. и не токо тые рыбы которыє в ты сѧ река плодѧ. але множьство рыбъ ромаиты а дивны з морѧ приходѧ а то за тою причиною. иже недалеко оустье Немновоє где Немо в море впадываеть.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And here in the rivers there was also a great abundance of extraordinary fish, not only those fish which breed in these rivers, but also a lot of different and unusual kinds of fish come from the sea because the Neman Estuary where the Neman flows into the sea is close by.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">на которыми  реками на Дꙋбисою. и на Немно и на Юрою та сѧ поселили. и почали ромноживатисѧ. и ѡно мешьканьє ихъ на тыми реками велми имъ пообалосѧ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">There on those rivers, on the Dubysa, the Neman and the Jūra, they settled and began to procreate, and they really liked that life on these rivers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и назвали тоую землю словеньски ꙗзыко побережнаꙗ землѧ. а Литовъскимъ. ꙗзыко назвали Жемоискаꙗ землѧ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And they called this land in the Slavic language ‘the Poberezhnaia<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>“Poberezhnaia” translates to “along the shore” or “coastal.”</p></note> land’, and in the Lithuanian language they called it ‘the land of Samogitia’.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а пото вышереченое кн҃же Палемо  вродилъ тре сн҃овъ сташїи Боркгъ. дрꙋгы Коуна. третїи Спера</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And later, the aforementioned Duke Polemon begat three sons: the oldest Borkus, the second Kunas, and the third Spera.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">старшии   сн҃ъ Боркгъ вчини горо на Юре реце и ложено имѧ того кнж҃ати посполе з рекою. и имѧ реце Юра а кнж҃ати Боргъ. и назва тотъ горо Юрборкъ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The oldest son, Borkus, established a city on the river Jūra and the name of this duke was joined with the name of the river – that is, the name of the river is Jūra, and the name of the duke is Borkus, and he named this city Iurbork.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а середнїи сн҃ъ Коуна пришо на оустьє реки Неважи и где ѡна впадаеть в Немо и вчини тоу горо и назва его имене своимъ Кꙋнасовъ горо</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the middle son, Kunas, came to the mouth of the river Nevėžis where it falls into the Neman and established a city there and named it with his own name – the city of Kaunas.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а третїи сн҃ъ Спера пошо дале в поущи к восходꙋ слн҃ца. и перешоши рекоу Невѧжоу. и рекꙋ Св҃тꙋю и третию рекꙋ Шивентꙋ и нашолъ ѡзеро лоуками и ромаиты дерево ѡкрашено. где  то полюбивши на ты ѡзеро поселилсѧ. и тоє ѡзеро имене свои назвалъ Спера.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the third son, Spera, went further eastward into the dense forest and having crossed the river Nevėžis and the river Sviataia<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>In Lithuanian, the river is called Šventoji.</p></note> and a third river Širvinta, he found a lake ringed by fields and a variety of trees, where, finding it to his liking, he settled and gave the lake his own name – Spera.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и пановалъ много лѣ. а пото змеръ бе плодꙋ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he ruled for many years, and then he died without an heir.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и поданыи его милоуючи его. а поле Риского ѡбычаѧ вчинили бована на паме его и навали Спера.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And his subjects, who loved him, following the Roman custom, created an idol in his memory and called him Spera.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="6">				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а пото ѡные люⷣ  мешькаючи ѡколо него. и почали ѡѳери чинити и за Бога мети а пото коли то болванъ сказилсѧ. и ѡни тоє ѡзеро и тоє местцо хвалили. и мели за Бг҃а.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And then these people who lived next to the idol began making sacrifices and considering him a god, and then, after that idol deteriorated, they worshipped the lake and the whole area as divine.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и по немъ межи собою гдрѧ не мѣли и мешкали бе пана. н навратившисѧ воспакъ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And after Spera they did not have a ruler and lived without a leader, and they came back.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The sentence does not specify to where Spera’s subjects returned but simply indicates that they turned back, perhaps to where Spera lived prior to establishing his own settlement, as described above.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">по малы часе бра его Боркгъ которы мешка на Юрборкꙋ вме не маючи детеи.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After a short time, his [Spera’s] brother Borkus who lived in Iurbork died without children.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ино бра его Коуна вометь и тꙋю чаⷭ  брата своего Борка. и горо Юрборкъ и тою чаⷭ ю его боуде и город Юрборкъ. пановати.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His other brother Kunas took both Borkus’ land and the city of Iurbork and he began ruling both that land and the city of Iurbork.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ѡноє кн҃жа Коуна мелъ двѫхъ сн҃въ. ѡдного Кернꙋса а дрѫгого Кгинъбоунта.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That Duke Kunas had two sons: one Kernus and the other Ginbunt.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="7">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">пауючи емоу в земли в Жомоитьскои. почасѧ  множити и роширѧти. и выхоⷣ ти за рекоу Велью в землю Завескоую и прошо рекꙋ Св҃тꙋю выше. и нашолъ место веми хорошо. и сподобалосѧ емꙋ тое местцо велми. и ѡнъ та поселисѧ. и назва тое местце именемъ сн҃а своего Кернꙋса Керново. и да томоу сн҃ꙋ своеꙋ Кернꙋсꙋ. а пото оумре.  </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When he was ruling in the Samogitian land, he began to increase and expand it beyond the river Veliia<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>This river is referred to by as both the Veliia, of Slavic origin, and Neris, of Baltic origin. In modern-day Lithuania, it is most often referred to as Neris but the Chronicle uses the Slavic name.</p></note> into the land beyond the Veliia, and having passed the river Sviataia upwards, he found a very good place, and he liked that place very much, and he settled there and named this place Kernovo after his son, Kernus, and gave it to that son of his, Kernus, and after that he died.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и почне сн҃ъ его панова  Керноу на всеи земли Завескои по границꙋ Латыгалъскꙋю и по Завелеиски Брѧславль а по рекꙋ Двинꙋ.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And his son Kernus began to rule over all the land beyond the Veliia up to the Latgalian border and to Braslav Zavelski, all the way to the Dvina River.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а бра его Кгибоуⷩ  на Юръборкоу. а на Коунасове и на всеи земли Жомоитьско.  </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And his brother Gibunt ruled in Iurbork and in Kaunas, and over the whole land of Samogitia.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а в тотъ ча где Керноу панова на Завелеискои сторонѣ. люⷣ  тыи его што за Веею посели. игрывали на трꙋба доубасны. и прозва то Керноу берегъ по вълоскѫ. гдѣ сѧ люⷣ  его множать литоусъ а трꙋба што на ни играють тоуба.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And at that time when Kunas ruled over the trans-Veliia land, his people who had settled beyond Veliia used to play wooden trumpets, and in Latin<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Although the author uses “po-vlosku,” which means Italian, here, he more likely means Latin.</p></note> Kunas called that shore where his people were procreating ‘Litus’, and the trumpet which they played ‘tuba’.  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и далъ имѧ ты люде свои по латине зложивши бере литоу. а трꙋба тоуба и да имъ имѧ литоутоуба.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he gave the name to his people in Latin, combining riverside, ‘litus,’ and trumpet, ‘tuba,’ and he called them ‘litustuba.’  </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="8">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">то пакъ простые люⷣ  не вмѣли звати по латине. и почали звати Литва и ѿ того чау паство Литовъское почалосѧ звати и множити ѿ Жомоити.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But then the common folk did not speak Latin and began calling it Litva, and since that time, the Lithuanian state derived its name and arose from Samogitia.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">кн҃зь великыи Керноу панова на Литве а кн҃зь Кгибоун на Жомоити. и не малы ча пановали. а жили межи собою вов покои.  </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Grand Duke Kernus ruled over Lithuania and Duke Gibunt over Samogitia, and they reigned for a long time and lived with one another in peace.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">кн҃зь пакъ Керноу не ме  сн҃овъ. токо ѡднꙋ докꙋ имене Поѧтꙋ. а боудꙋчи ѡнъ в старости своеи. а не хотечи паства своего ѿ дочки своее ѿдалити. и принѧ до нее зѧте собе с Китаврау имене Кгирꙋсъ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But Duke Kernus did not have sons, only one daughter named Poiata, and being in his old age and not wanting to take his principality away from his own daughter, he accepted for her a son-in-law from the Centaurus family, named Girus.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">а Кгибоутъ на Жомоискои земли и пауючи Кгибоутꙋ на Жомоити оумре. а сн҃а своего Моⷩ вила зоставитъ на Жомоитьско  кн҃зьстве.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And Gibunt ruled over the land of Samogitia, and when Gibunt ruled over Samogitia he died, and left his son, Montvil, to rule over the principality of Samogitia.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">и Монътвилъ много кн͠жи на Жомоити. а мелъ двоу с͠новъ ѡдно Немноса а дрѫгого Скирмота.   </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And Montvil ruled in Samogitia for a long time and had two sons – one Nemnos and the other, Skirmont.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>