<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Merciful God and on the Birds' Glorification</title>
				<author>Sanā’ī of Ghazna</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>Sanā’ī al-Ghaznavī, Abū al-Majd Majdūd ibn Ādam. Huva kitāb-i mustaṭāb-i kullīyāt. Bombay: Khan Sahib M.M. Shirazi, 1328 [1910].</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Navid Saberi-Najafi</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>Sanā’ī of Ghazna (d. 1131 C.E.) was the first major poet of classical Persian Sufi literature. He was a monumental poet not just because of his versification skills, but also because of his profound influence upon Sufi poets such as ‘Aṭṭār of Kadkan (d. 1225 C.E.) and Mawlavī (Rumi) (d. 1273 C.E.). “On the Merciful God and on the Birds’ Glorifications,” in the Dīvān [collection of poems], is a qaṣīda (laudatory poem) comprising three key themes: nature, the centrality of the Sufi concept of dhikr (remembrance) to man’s salvation, and tawḥīd (the Oneness of God).</p>
				<p>At the very beginning of the poem, Sanā’ī depicts one of the blessings of God, which is in the form of bountiful rain. Spring is the ideal setting for the poet to portray the avian species’ glorifications, not only because the revivification of nature takes place, but more importantly, because spring’s abundant rain is a sign of God’s forgiveness toward mankind. Dhikr—a central practice in Islamic esoterism, derived from the Qur’an—and tawḥīd are two themes communicated through multifarious talking birds, such as the humā—a mythical bird like an eagle, who acknowledges the Oneness of God by saying, “The Unequaled is One.” Medieval Persian authors deployed the bird metaphor to concretize abstract Sufi concepts (e.g., dhikr). Further, the Qur’an—an important source of influence upon Muslim thinkers—likens birds to human communities (6/Al-An‘ām: 38). Sanā’ī conceives of birds as purposeful signs for humans to make sense of the universe. The red pigeon, for instance, serves as a spiritual model for humans, saying huwa [He] “one-hundred times with each breath.”</p> 
				<p>The poem contains abundant stylistic features. Sanā’ī’s use of periphrasis is seen in “The Riḍwān (an angel) opens all the gates of Paradise,” which is a circumlocutory way of emphasizing divine blessings in springtime. He employs sensory imagery: olfactory (“qālīyih” [a fragrant substance comprising musk, ambergris, and pussy willow], “mounds of camphor,” etc.), auditory (“wind’s blowing,” “cock’s crow,” “wailing,” etc.), tactile (“silk and ermine coat,” etc.), kinesthetic (“quivering trees,” “lark’s strut,” etc.), and thermal (“autumn”). This rich imagery provides the reader with a vivid picture of nature. The poet’s allusion to 55/Al-Raḥmān: 70 (“ ‘good and beautiful ones’ ”) illustrates that he was inspired by the Qur’an. Other stylistic features include alliteration (“character and customs” [sīrat va sān]) and consonance (“the Omnipotent Subduer” [qādir-i qahhār]). Finally, in classical Persian literature, it was common for poets to address themselves—especially at the end of poems—by using their pen names; the final distich that includes the poet’s pen name (i.e., Majdūd) in a qaṣīda is called takhallus. Sanā’ī’s use of takhallus might convince his audience to take his sermon seriously: whilst the poet pleads with his readers to shun the indulgences of the fleeting world, he acknowledges in the final distich that he needs to purify his own soul (“Majdūd! You are closer to this state, for / Old age has indeed summoned autumn”).</p>
				<p>The Dīvān, in which the aforementioned poem appears, was published in Bombay in 1910 by Khan Sahib M.M. Shirazi. The collection contains 14,000 distichs that mainly revolve around religious themes, such as eschewing the nafs [carnal soul], performing the dhikr, and abandoning the cupidity of worldly substance and goods, among others.</p>
				<p>De Bruijn, J.T.P. Of Piety and Poetry: The Interaction of Religion and Literature in the Life and Works of Ḥakīm Sanā’ī of Ghazna. Brill, 1983. A very detailed study of Sanā’ī</p>
				<p>De Bruijn, J.T.P. “Sanā’ī.” Encyclopaedia Iranica, 17 May 2012. Accessed 4 September 2020. A general introduction to Sanā’ī</p>
				<p>Johnson, Kathryn V. “A Mystic’s Response to the Claims of Philosophy: Abū’l Majd Majdūd Sanā’ī’s Sayr al-‘Ibād ilā’l-M‘ād.” Islamic Studies, vol. 34, no. 3, 1995, pp. 253-295. A thorough analysis of Sanā’ī’s notable allegory</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><ref target="https://www.loc.gov/item/2013415205/">Sanā’ī al-Ghaznavī, Abū al-Majd Majdūd ibn Ādam. Huva kitāb-i mustaṭāb-i kullīyāt. Bombay: Khan Sahib M.M. Shirazi, 1328 [1910].</ref></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">در توحید خداوند غفور و تسبیح طیور فرماید</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">On the Merciful God and on the Birds’ Glorifications</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"<!--Title in English-->" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>In the transcription, punctuation marks and diacritics have been used to aid the reader. The English translation has attempted to preserve the Persian text’s elevated diction.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">آراست جهاندار دگرباره جهانرا<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>چون خُلد برین کرد، زمین را و زمان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">HELLO CHECK NINE Once again, God beautified the world,<lb/>Turned the Earth and time into the Most Exalted Paradise.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>فرمود که تا چرخ یکی دور دگر کرد<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>خورشید بپیمود مسیر دَوَران را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As soon as the firmament made one orbit, He ordered<lb/>The sun to travel its circular path.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>ایدون که بیاراست مرآن پیرِ خرِفرا<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>کاید حسد، از تازگیش، تازه جوان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He beautified that senile, old man in a way that<lb/>His sprightliness enkindled the fair sapling’s envy.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>هر روز جهان خوشتر از آن است چو هر شب<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>رضوان بگشاید همه درهای جنان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Each day the world is more pleasant, for each night<lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Riḍwān</hi> opens all the gates of Paradise.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>گوئی که هوا غالیه آمیخت بخروار<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>پر کرد از آن غالیه‌ها، غالیه‌دانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It appeared as if the air had mixed lots of <hi rend="italic">qālīyih,</hi><lb/>Filling the <hi rend="italic">qālīyih,</hi> holder with <hi rend="italic">qālīyih,</hi>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>گنجی که به هر کُنج، نهان بود ز قارون<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>از خاک برآورد، مر آن گنج نهان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The treasure in every corner that was hidden from <hi rend="italic">Qārūn,</hi><lb/>[The air] brought that hidden treasure out of the earth.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>ابری که همی برف ببارید ببرّید<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>شد غرقهٔ بحری که ندید ایچ کرانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The clouds that continuously rained snow, broke,<lb/>Submerged in a sea in which no shore was visible.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن ابرِ دُرربار، ز دریا که بر آید<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>پر کرده ز دُرّ و درم و دانه دهانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That pearl-laden cloud which rises from the sea,<lb/>Showers [river] mouths with pearls, coins, and raindrops.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>از بسکه ببارید به آب اندر، لؤلؤ<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>چون لؤلؤِ تر کرده همه آبِ روان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Pearl-drops rained down so hard that<lb/>All the flowing water turned into fulgent pearls.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>رنجی که همی باد فزاید ز بَزیدن<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>بر ما بوزید از قِبَلِ راحتِ جانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wind’s blowing, which causes ever-increasing hardship,<lb/>Came from a direction that comforted the soul.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>کوه آن تلِ کافور بدل کرد بسیفور<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>شادیّ روان داد، مر آن شادرَوانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The mountain turned mounds of camphor into fine silk,<lb/>Gladdening the soul of the dear departed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>بر کوه، از آن تودهٔ کافورِ گرانبار،<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>خورشید سبک کرد، مر آن بارِ گران را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The heavy heaps of camphor on the mountain,<lb/>The sun lightened those burdensome loads.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>خاکی که همه ژاله ستَد از دهنِ ابر<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تا بر کند آن لالهٔ خوش خُفته ستانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The earth that absorbs all the dew from the cloud’s mouth,<lb/>Uproots that dormant, supine tulip peacefully asleep.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>چندین ز هوا ژاله ببارید بدو، ابر<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تا لاله‌ستان کرد، همه لاله‌ستانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From the sky, the cloud rained down heavy dew on it,<lb/>Creating a vast field of supine tulips.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>از رنگ گل و لاله، کنون باز بنفشه<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>چون نیل شود، خیره کند، گوهرِ کان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Given the flowers’ and tulips’ colors, it is time for the violet to bloom.<lb/>Upon turning cerulean, it would bedazzle a mine’s gem.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>شبگیر، زند نعره کُلَنگ از دلِ مشتاق<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>وز نعره زدن، طعنه زند نعره‌زنانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At cockcrow, the crane calls, its heart ablaze with passion,<lb/>And by calling, it reproves [other] callers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن لکلک گوید که «لَکَ‌الحَمدُ لَکَ‌الشُّکر!<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تو طعمهٔ من کرده آن مار دمان را.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That stork says, <hi rend="italic">“lak al-ḥamd-u lak al-shshukr</hi>;<note type="critical" anchored="true"><p>praise be to You and thanks be to You</p></note><lb/>You have made that frightful snake my prey.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>قُمری نَهد از پشت قبایِ خَز و قاقُم<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>اکنون که بتابید و بپوشید کتان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The turtledove doffed its silk and ermine coat,<lb/>Donning a vesture of linen now that it feels hot.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>طاوس کند جلوه چو از دور ببیند<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>بر فرقِ سرِ هدهد، آن تاجِ کیانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The peacock performs a display when it espies afar<lb/>The <hi rend="italic">Kīyān</hi> Crown on the parting of the hoopoe’s head.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>موسیجه همی گوید: «یا رازقِ رزّاق<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>روزی‌ده و جان‌بخش توئی، انسی و جانرا.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wood pigeon is saying, “O Supplier of Sustenance!<lb/>You are the soul-giving sustenance-supplier of man and of the djinn.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>زاغ از شَغَبِ بیهده، بربندد، منقار<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>چون فاخته بگشاده به تسبیح، زبانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The chough closes its bill to futile, clamorous chattering.<lb/>Like the collared turtledove, its tongue is open to glorification.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>پیوسته هما گوید: «یکّیست یگانه.»<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تا در طرب آرد، بهوا بر، وَرَشانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The <hi rend="italic">Humā</hi> constantly says, “The Unequaled is One,”<lb/>Delighting the mountain pigeon up in the air.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>گنجشکِ بهاری، صفتِ باری، گوید<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>کز بوم برانگیزد، اشجارِ نوان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The spring sparrow recites the attributes of the Creator,<lb/>Enlivening the Earth’s quivering trees.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>«هو» گوید «هو»، صد، بدمی، سرخ کبوتر<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>در گفتنِ «هو» دارد، پیوسته لبان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">“Huwa,”</hi> says the red pigeon one-hundred times with each breath, <hi rend="italic">“huwa.”</hi><lb/>In saying <hi rend="italic">“huwa,”</hi> its tongue is constant.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>چَرغان، بسرِ چنگ، در آورده تذروان<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تسبیح شده از دهن مرغ مر آن را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The saker falcons have clutched the pheasants in their talons;<lb/>That has made the birds’ mouths utter glorifications.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>شارک، چو مؤذّن بسحر، حلق گشاده<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>آن ژولک و آن صعوه از آن داده اذانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The starling, like the muezzin, throats out [its melody] at dawn.<lb/>That red lark and that accentor intone the <hi rend="italic">adhān</hi> in tune.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن شیشکان، شاد، از این سنگ بدان سنگ<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>پاینده و پوینده، مر آن پیکِ دوان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Gladsome, those grouse alight upon rock after rock,<lb/>In amaranthine quest of that running messenger.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن کبکِ مُرَقّع، سَلَبِ برچِدَه دامن<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space> از غالیه غُل ساخته از بهرِ نشانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That partridge, in a patched, flared skirt,<lb/>Has made a necklace of perfumed, black tresses as an ornament.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>بنگر بهوا بر، بچکاوک که چه گوید:<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>«خَیر و حَسَنت بادا، خیرات و حِسان را.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Behold, in the air, what the lark says,<lb/>“May [He] bless the ‘good and beautiful ones’ for their good deeds.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>نازیدن نازو و نواهای سریچه<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>ناطق کند آن مردهٔ بی‌نطق و بیانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The lark’s strut and the wagtail’s warble,<lb/>Turn the inarticulate, speechless dead into orators.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن کُرکی گوید که «توئی قادرِ قهّار<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>از مرگ همی قهر کنی مر حیوانرا.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That Crane says, “You are the Omnipotent Subduer,<lb/>Perpetually subduing the death of creatures.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>پیوسته همی گوید آن سر‌شبِ تشنه:<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>«بی ‌آب ملک صبر دهد مر عطشانرا.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That thirsty falcon is constantly saying,<lb/>“May the King bestow patience upon the ardent.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>مرغابی سرخاب که در خاک نشیند<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>گوید که «خدائی و سزائی تو جهانرا.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The red duck that sits on the ground,<lb/>Says “You are the venerable Lord of the world.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>در خوید، چنین گوید کَرَکی که «خدایا!<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>تو خالقِ خلقانی صد قرن قران را.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Sweating, the quail clamors, “O God!<lb/>The Creator of creation over hundreds of years of conjunctions.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>گویند تذروان که «تو آنی که بدانی<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>رازِ تنِ بیقوّت و بیروح و روان‌ را.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The pheasants crow, “You are the one who knows<lb/>The mystery of a strengthless, soulless body.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن باز چنین گوید: «یا رب! تو نگهدار<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>بر امّتِ پیغمبر، ایمان و امان را.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That falcon says, “O Lord!<lb/>Protect the faith of the Prophet’s community and give them sanctuary.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آن کرکسِ باقوّت، گوید که «بقدرت<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>جبّار نگهدارد، این کون و مکانرا.»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The mighty vulture says, “Powerfully,<lb/>The Omnipotent protects the universe.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>بنگر که عقاب از پیِ تسبیح چه گوید:<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>«آراسته دارید، مر این سیرت و سانرا!»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hearken what the eagle says for its glorification:<lb/>“Beautify your character and customs!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>بلبل چه مُذکِّر شده، قمری قاری <space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>برداشته هر دو، شَغَب و بانگ و فغانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The nightingale has become a sermonizer, the turtledove a Qur’an-reciter;<lb/>Both are warbling, chanting loudly, and wailing.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آید بتو، هر پاس، خروشی ز خروسی<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>«کی غافل! بگذار جهانِ گذرانرا!»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Night and day, you hear the cock’s crow:<lb/>“Eschew the passing world, O neglecter!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>آوازه برآورده که «ای قوم! تنِ خویش<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>دوزخ مَبَرید، از پیِ بهمان و فلانرا!»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">[The cock] has cried, “O people!<lb/>Do not condemn your bodies to Hell for so-and-sos!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>دنیا چو یکی بیشه شمارید، ژیان شیر<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>در بیشه مشورید مر آن شیرِ ژیانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">View the world as a jungle [with a] lion, fierce;<lb/>In that jungle, do not provoke that fierce lion.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>در جُستنِ نان، آبِ رخِ خویش مریزید<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>در نار مسوزید روان، از پیِ نان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In seeking bread, do not destroy your dignity.<lb/>Do not burn your soul for bread.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>ایزد چه بزنّار نبسته است میانتان<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>در پیشِ چو خود، خیره مبندید میانرا</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Since God has not girded you with a girdle,<lb/>Do not irrationally gird your waist.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>زان پیش که جانتان بستانَد مَلَکُ‌الموت<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>از قبضهٔ شیطان بستانید عنان را!»</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Before the Angel of Death takes your soul,<lb/>Remove the [soul’s] bridle from Satan’s grip.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><milestone unit="stanza"/>مجدود، بدین حال، تو نزدیک‌تری، زانک<space quantity="20" unit="chars"></space>پیریت به نَهمار فرستاده خزان را</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">Majdūd!</hi> You are closer to this state, for<lb/>Old age has indeed summoned autumn.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
