<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>"Underneath my forehead I carry your beautiful image"</title>
				<author>Jordi de Sant Jordi</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription By by</resp>
					<name>Albert Lloret</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Albert Lloret</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>This poem was composed ca. 1410-1424 by Valencian author Jordi de Sant Jordi, a son of a Muslim convert and valet of the chamber of the king of the Crown of Aragon, Alfonso the Magnanimous (1396-1458). It is believed to have been dedicated to the widowed Queen Margarida de Prades (1387-1429). The poem is written in Catalan with Occitan traits. It is in versos estramps, blank verses ending in unique, sonorous, words that are also known as rims fènix. Some of these rhyme words come from the famous sestina by Occitan troubadour Arnaut Daniel. Versos estramps in fact seem to be an evolution or an innovative version of the traditional sestina.</p>
				<p>This love poem features a sustained and multifaceted praise of the lady with attention to both her physical and moral beauty as well as a declaration of the steadfast love of the lyric voice. A dense, object-oriented imagery pervades each stanza. The text is considered the most remarkable love song of the trobar ric tradition in medieval Catalan poetry.</p>
				<p>This poem is a unicum copied in Zaragoza, Biblioteca de la Universidad de Zaragoza, MS 210, fol. 98v-99r (the Cançoner de Saragossa). The manuscript has been digitized here: http://zaguan.unizar.es/record/535?ln=en. It contains a compilation of Catalan verse dating to 1461-1462. It is the oldest known manuscript to transmit Ausiàs March’s poetry, and an important witness to the transmission of the poetry of several other authors, including Pere Torroella and Lleonard de Sors.</p>
				<p>de Riquer, Martí and Lola Badia, editors. Les poesies de Jordi de Sant Jordi. Tres i Quatre, 1984. This is the canonical edition and commentary of Sant Jordi’s works.</p>
				<p>Jordi de Sant Jordi. Poesies. Edited by Aniello Fratta. Barcino, 2005. This edition makes important textual contributions and advances a debated Italianizing interpretation of Sant Jordi’s poetry.</p>
				<p>Torró, Jaume. “El cançoner de Saragossa.” Translatar i transferir: La transmissió dels textos i el saber (1200-1500). Edited by Anna Alberni, Lola Badia i Lluís Cabré. Obrador Edèndum, 2010, pp. 379-415. This is the most up-to-date study of the songbook containing Sant Jordi’s poem.</p>
				<p>Micó, José María. “Translating Medieval Catalan Poetry Today: Jordi de Sant Jordi and Ausiàs March.” Translation Review, vol. 87, 2013, pp. 18-29. Reflections on translating Sant Jordi’s poetry into Spanish.</p>
				<p>Terry, Arthur. “Jordi de Sant Jordi and the Ethics of Chivalry.” Three Fifteenth-Century Valencian Poets. Department of Hispanic Studies, Queen Mary and Westfield College, 2000, pp. 24-38. Short introduction to Sant Jordi’s work in English. It contains a reading of the poem.</p>
				<p>Albert Lloret. “The Space in the Poem (Jordi de Sant Jordi, IX & XIV).” Revealing New Perspectives: Hommages to Stephen G. Nichols from his Colleagues, Friends and Students, edited by Kevin Brownlee and Marina Brownlee, Peter Lang, 2021. Study of space in two poems by Sant Jordi.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><ref target="http://zaguan.unizar.es/record/535?ln=en">Zaragoza, Biblioteca de la Universidad de Zaragoza, MS 210, fol. 98v-99r</ref></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">"Jus lo front port vostra bella semblança"</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">"Underneath my forehead I carry your beautiful image"</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Underneath my forehead I carry your beautiful image" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>I have punctuated the text, regularized i/j, u/v, and segmented enclitics following modern conventions. I have only made two corrections to obvious copying errors, both accepted in modern editions: jusmetets, correcting (*iustametz) and fonch (correcting *fonchs).</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Jus lo front port vostra bella semblança,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Underneath my forehead I carry your beautiful image,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">de que mon cors nit e jorn fa gran festa;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That’s why I celebrate you, night and day;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que, remiran la molt bella figura,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For, by looking at your beautiful figure,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">de vostre ffaç m’es romassa l’empremta,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A trace of your face has remained in me.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que ja per mort no se’n partra la forma,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Its shape won’t go away when I die,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ans, quant seray del tot fores d’est segle,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Instead, when I will have entirely left this earthly life,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">cels qui lo cors portaran al sepulcre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Those who will bring my body to the tomb</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">sobre me faç, veuran lo vostre signe.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Will find your sign on my face.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Si com l’infants quant mira lo retaula</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Like the little kid who watches the altarpiece</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">e, contemplant la pintur·ab himatges,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And contemplates the painting and its images</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ab son net cor, no lo·n poden gens partre</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With a pure heart, and doesn’t want to separate from it</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">(tant ha plasser de l’aur qui ll’environa),</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">(So much does he enjoy the gold that surrounds it),</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">atressi·m pren devan l’amoros sercle</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That’s how I feel when I’m in front of the love circle</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">de vostre cors, que de tants bens s’anrama,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Of your figure, for it’s embellished with so many qualities</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que, mentre·l vey, mas que Deu lo contemple;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That, while I’m watching it, I contemplate it better than God;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">tant hay de joy per amor qui·m penetre.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This love that penetrates me brings me so much joy.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3" type="stanza">
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Aixi·m te pres e liatz en son carçre</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That’s how he has me, captive and tied up, in his jail,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">amors ardents, com si·stes en hun coffre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This ardent Love, as if I were inside a chest,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">tancat jus claus, e tot mon cors fos dintre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Locked in, all of me inside,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">on no pusques mover per null encontre.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Without a chance to break out.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Car tant es grans l’amor que us ay, e ferme,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So big is my love for you, and so steadfast,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que lo meu cor no·s part punt per angoxa,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That my heart won’t move away, not one bit, out of anguish,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">bella, de vos, ans es ·say ferm com torres</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From you, beautiful one, but will rather be strong as a tower</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">e sol amar a vos, blanxa colomba.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And will only love you, white dove.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Bella sens par, ab la pressensa noble,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Unmatched beauty of noble presence,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">vostre bel cors bell fech Deu sobre totas,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">God made your pretty body superior to any other,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">gays e donos, lluu pus que fina pedre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Gay and gentle, brighter than a gemstone,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">amoros, bels, plus penetrans que stella;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Loving, beautiful, more penetrating than a star;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">d’on, quan vos vey ab les autres en flota,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For, when I spot you among other people,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">les jusmetets<note anchored="true"><p>Correcting <hi rend="italic">iustametz.</hi></p></note> si com fay lo carvoncles,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You subdue them as does the carbuncle,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que de virtuts les finas pedres passa:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Which surpasses the qualities of any gemstone;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">vos etz sus ley com l’estors sus l’esmirle.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You are above them like the goshawk is above the merlin.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="5" type="stanza">
				<l n="33">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">L’amor que us hay en totes les part[s] m’ascle</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">My love for you is splintering every part of me</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="34">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">quan non amech pus coralment nuls homens;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For no one has ever loved so sincerely;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="35">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"> tan fort·amor, com cesta que·l cor m’obre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Such a strong love, like this one that opens my heart,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="36">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ne fonch<note anchored="true"><p>Correcting <hi rend="italic">fonchs.</hi></p></note> jamays en nul cors d’hom ne arme.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Has never been in anyone’s body or soul.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="37">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Mas suy torbats que no fonch Aristotills,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I am more upset than Aristotle ever was</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="38">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">d’amor, qui m’art e mos sinch senys desferme.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For love, which burns me and unleashes my five senses.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="39">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Co·l monjos bos que no·s part de la setla,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Like the good monk who does not leave his cell,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="40">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">no·s part mon cors da vos, tant com dits d’ungle.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">My heart does not move away from you, like the finger from the nail.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="6" type="stanza">
				<l n="41">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ho, cors donos, net de frau e delicte,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Oh, gentle lady, clean of deceit and offenses,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="42">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">prenets de me pietats, bela dona,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Have pity on me, beautiful lady,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="43">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">e no suffrats quez aman-vos peresca,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And don’t allow that I die by loving you,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="44">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pus qu·eu vos am may que nulls homs afferme,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For I love you more than anyone could affirm;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="45">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">per que us suppley a vos, qu·etz le bells arbres</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That is why I beg you—since you are the handsome tree</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="46">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">de tots bos fruyts, hon valors grans pren s·ombre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Of all good fruits, where the high Worth rest on its shade—</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="47">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">que·m retenyats en vostra valent cambre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To keep me in your prized chamber,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="48">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">pus vostre suy e seray tant com visque.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For I am yours, and so will I be for as long as I live.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="7" type="stanza">
				<l n="49">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Mos richs balays, cert, vos portats le timbre</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">My prized spinel, you certainly wear the crown</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="50">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">sus quantes son e·l mundenal registre,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Over all women in the worldy registry</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="51">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">car tots jorns naix en vos cors, e revida,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For every day are born in you, and revive,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="52">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">bondats, virtuts, mes qu·en Pantasilea.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Goodness and virtue, more than they ever did in Penthesilea.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
