<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Sermon on St. Nobody</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Based on the edition in</resp>
					<name>Martha Bayless, ed. Fifteen Medieval Latin Parodies. Toronto: Pontifical Institute of Medieval Studies, 2018.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Emma Grover</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Nina Du</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The “Sermon on St. Nobody” is a pseudo-hagiographical text that relies for humorous effect on a simple conceit: it treats the Latin word nemo, meaning no one or nobody, as a name, then quotes the Bible and other prominent texts to give an account of this supposed saint’s extraordinary deeds; for example, from Job 12:14, “If God imprisons a man, it is Nobody who can release him.” The many variations of the “Sermon on St. Nobody” are part of a lively tradition of religious parody that flourished across medieval Europe, especially in the later Middle Ages. Medieval education, especially monastic education, fostered a deep familiarity with a relatively consistent textual canon, an environment almost tailor-made for parody. That this account of “St. Nobody” was written in Latin makes the erudition of the intended audience clear, as does the deep familiarity with biblical passages that is required to get the jokes. Other such parody saints also emerged in the later Middle Ages, such as St. One-Another (Invicem), whose veneration Jesus especially promotes with the command to “love one another.” None of these others, however, seems to have achieved such widespread success as St. Nobody: half a dozen separate versions of the “Sermon on St. Nobody” have been identified, from nineteen different manuscripts. Nor did St. Nobody remain popular exclusively among monks; he moved out of the monastery in the early modern period and was referenced in vernacular art and literature, including, as Bayless notes, Shakespeare’s Tempest.</p>
				<p>The first iteration of the “Sermon on St. Nobody” was written by one Radulphus in the late thirteenth century. The text was, however, embedded in a much longer tradition of medieval Latin parody, and it would be transformed by that tradition in turn. The iteration of the “Sermon on St. Nobody” presented here for the most part resembles Radulphus’s version only in concept. The Latin text used for this translation is taken from Graz, Universitaetsbibliothek 904, fols. 175r-176v, as edited by Martha Bayless. This particular manuscript dates to c. 1425 and contains a hodgepodge of religious and secular texts, including a selection of verse proverbs in both Latin and German.</p>
				<p>Bayless, Martha, ed. Fifteen Medieval Latin Parodies. Pontifical Institute of Mediaeval Studies, 2018.</p>
				<p>Billy, Dennis J. “Hagiographical parody in the Ysengrimus,” Quidditas, vol. 12, 1991, pp. 1-12</p>
				<p>Doležalová, Lucie. “Receptions of Obscurity and Obscurities of Reception: The Case of the Cena Cypriani,” Listy filologické / Folia philologica, vol. 125, no. 3/4, 2002, pp. 187 -197</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Graz, Universitätsbibliothek 904, fols. 175r-176v.</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Nemo</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Sermon on St. Nobody</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>Sermon on St. Nobody is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nemo</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Sermon on St. Nobody</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Vir erat in oriente, Nemo nomine, et erat uir ille ut allter Iob inter omnes orientales.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There was a man in the East by the name of Nobody, and this man was as another Job among all the Easterners.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Magnus namque erat iste Nemo sanctus: magnus in genere et prosapia, magnus in potencia, magnus in scientia, magnus in clemencia &lt;et&gt; in compassione, magnus in honore et reuerentia.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For that Nobody was a great saint: great in origin and lineage, great in power, great in learning, great in mercy and in compassion, great in honor and reverence. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Hec autem omnia supra dicuntur ex sacra scriptura, cui nephas est reclamandum et contradicendum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> More is said of him than all others in sacred scripture, which it is a sin to protest or speak publicly against. </rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="2">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item Nemo, dico, primo fuit magnus in genere et prosapia et similis Ade, qui fuit nec creatus nec genitus sed formatus
							secundum prophetam dicentem: <i>Dies formabuntur et Nemo in eis</i>.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I say first that Nobody was great in origin and lineage and was like Adam, who was not begotten or born but was formed, as the prophet says: Days will be formed and Nobody in them.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Ps. 138:16.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit eciam de genere militari, unde apostolus: Nemo militans deo.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Furthermore he was of a warlike origin, hence the apostle says: Nobody fighting for God.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to 2 Tim. 2:4.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Imo fuit nobilitate miles qui propriis et non alienis stipendiis militauit, unde illud apostoli:
							<i>Nemo tenetur propriis stipendiis militare.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, he was a soldier of renown, who served at his own expense and not others’, hence the following, of the apostle: Nobody serves as a soldier at his own expense.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to 1 Cor. 9:7.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="3">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam fuit de genere non qualicumque sed regali, Ecclesiastici ii: <i>Nemo ex regibus sumpsit exordium.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Furthermore, he was not of a common but a regal origin, as in Ecclesiastes 2: <i>Nobody began life among kings</i>.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Wis. 7:5. Adding to the parodic effect, the in-text citation is false, and the quote has been truncated in such a way that the meaning is radically reshaped; <i>ex regibus</i> qualifies <i>nemo</i> in the original context rather than <i>sumpsit</i> exordium, as it does here.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam fuit de cognacione uirginis gloriose eo quod fuerit de stirpe regia et de cognacione Elizabet, Luc 1: <i>Nemo est in cognacione tua.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For he was of the relatives of a glorious virgin, who was of a regal lineage, and of the relatives of Elizabeth, as in Luke 1: <i>Nobody is among your relatives.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 1:61.</p>
								</note>
						</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Nec fuit solum de stirpe regia sed cum ipso deo legitur semper regnaturus, Ecclesiastici xxi: 'Nemo semper regnaturus.'</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Nor was he only of a regal lineage, but it is said of him by God himself that he will reign forever, Ecclesiastes 21: Nobody will reign forever.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>Not only is the in-text citation here false, but this is not actually a biblical quote. </p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="4">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Secundo, dixi, iste Nemo magnus fuit in potencia, prius quia aperit quod deus claudit, unde illud: <i>Deus claudit et Nemo aperit.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Second, I said this Nobody was great in power, because he opens what God closes, hence the following: <i>God closes and Nobody opens</i>.
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Rev. 3:7.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Iob 12: <i>Si incluserit hominem, Nemo est qui aperiat.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Job 12: <i>If God imprisons a man, it is Nobody who can release him.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Job 12:14.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item de manu dei audacter eripit, Iob 2: <i>Cum sit Nemo qui de manu tua possit eruere.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He also takes boldly from the hand of God, as in Job 2: <i>Since it is Nobody who can pluck [me] from your hand.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Job 10:7. The truncation of the quote gives the <i>cum</i> clause causal force rather than the concessive of the original context.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item edifficat quod deus destruit, unde Iob: <i>Si deus destruit, Nemo est qui edifficat.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He also builds up what God destroys, hence Job: <i>If God destroys it, it is Nobody who can build it up.</i>
								<note type="critical"  anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Job 12:14.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item ipsum deum superat et uincitt, Ecclesiastici ii: Nemo uincit deum.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He also surpasses and conquers God himself, as in Ecclesiastes 2: Nobody conquers God.
								<note type="critical"  anchored="true">
									<p>This is not actually a biblical quote.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Propterea quod deus fecit, iste Nemo illa potest facere si uoluerit, sicut dixit Nicodemus in ewangelio:
							<i>Nemo potest ista signa facere que tu facis.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> For this reason God made it so that this Nobody could do whatever he wanted, just as Nicodemus says in the Gospel:
								<i>Nobody can do the signs you do.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to John 3:2.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item gaudium ab apostolis potenter tollit, unde in ewangelio: <i>Et gaudium tuum Nemo tollet a uobis.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">He also powerfully takes away joy from the apostles, hence in the Gospel: <i>And Nobody shall take your joy away from you.</i>
									<p>This refers to John 16:22.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Imo quod maius est, animam a Christo rapit: <i>Animam meam Nemo tollit.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, what is greater, he takes away life from Christ: <i>Nobody takes away my life.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to John 10:18.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item duobus dominis potest seruire utiliter, quod multis uidetur inpossibile et quod est contro ewangelium, iuxta illud ut habetur in ewangelio: <i>Nemo potest duobus dominis seruire.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He can also serve two masters usefully, which seems impossible to many and is against the Gospel, just as follows, as it is had in the Gospels: <i>Nobody can serve two masters.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Mat. 6:24.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="5">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Tercio dixi quod iste Nemo magnus fuit &lt;in&gt; scientiis.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Third, I said that Nobody was great in knowledge.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Sciuit <i>utrum amore uel odio dignus sit.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> He knew <i>whether he was worthy of love or hate.</i>
								<note type="critical"  anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Eccl. 9:1.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam magnus in scientia, principaliter in grammatica, Prisciano se conformans, ipso attestante: <i>Neminem inueni mihi socium.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Furthermore, he was great in learning, chiefly in grammar, describing him thus with Priscian himself affirming: <i>I have found Nobody my peer.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Priscian’s Institutiones 17.87.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit enim magnus in arismetrica, secundum illud apostoli: <i>Nemo poterat dinumerare turbam.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For he was great in arithmetic, according to the apostle, as follows: <i>Nobody could number the crowd.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Rev. 7:9.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit magnus in musica, item Apocalypsis: <i>Nemo poterat dicere canticum.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He was great in music, also in Revelation: <i>Nobody could sing that song.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Rev. 14:3.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit eciam magnus propheta, secundum Matthei dictum: <i>Nemo propheta acceptus in patria sua.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he was a great prophet, according to the saying of Matthew: <i>Nobody the prophet was accepted in his homeland.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 4:24 (in-text citation false).</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="6">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item fuit magnus in clementia et compassione.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He was also great in mercy and compassion.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Primum signum compassionis quia Christo fuit compassus in cruce morienti, unde illud Isaie: <i>Ecce quomodo moritur iustus et Nemo considerat.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The first sign of his compassion was that he had pity for Christ dying on the cross, hence the following from Isaiah: <i>Behold how the righteous man dies and Nobody looks.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This is from the sixth responsory for Holy Saturday; cf. Isaiah 57:1-2.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Etiam martiribus compassus fuit pro Christo morientibus, iuxta illud: <i>Viri iusti tolluntur et Nemo percipit corde.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Furthermore he had pity for the martyrs dying for Christ, according to the following: <i>Righteous men are taken up and Nobody takes it to heart.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This is drom the sixth responsory for Holy Saturday; cf. Isaiah 57:1-2.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item Lazaro mendicante compassus fuit qui poscrebat uentrem suum <i>saturari de micis que cadebant de mensa diuitis,</i> et Nemo ei dabat.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> He also had pity for Lazarus the beggar who asked that his belly <i>be filled with crumbs that fell from the wealthy man’s table, and Nobody gave to him.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Isaiah 57:1.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item filio prodigio compassus fuit, Luc iii, <i>qui cupiebat uentrem suum saturare de siliquis quas porci comedebant et Nemo illi dabat.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 16:21.</p>
								</note>
								
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit etiam pauperum consolator, unde Ecclesiastici x: <i>Verti me ad alia et uidi calumpnias que sub sole geruntur et consolatorem Neminem inueni.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He was also the comforter of the poor, hence Ecclesiastes 10: <i>I turned myself to others and I saw the foul deeds that came to pass under the sun and I found Nobody to be a comforter.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Eccl. 4:1.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam fuit magnus in uita contemplatiua, deo et sanctis seruicia inpendenda, iuxta illud: <i>Nemo accendit lucernam.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He was also great in the contemplative life, the service to God and the saints to which one ought to devote oneself, according to the following: <i>Nobody lights a lamp. </i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 11:33.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam magnus fuit in uita actiua iuxta illud: <i>Nemo mittens manum ad aratrum.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> He was also great in the active life, according to the following: <i>Nobody putting his hand to the plow.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 9:62.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="7">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item ut omnem eius dignitatem ita concludam breuiloquio, fuit iste sanctus Nemo ita dignus quod singulari honore honorauit eum dominus per suas salutationes sibi transmittendo:
							<i>Neminem salutaueritis per uiam.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> Also, so that I might thus define all his dignity with concision, this Saint Nobody was so worthy because the Lord honored him with a remarkable honor by sending his greetings to him:
								<i>greet Nobody on the way.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Luke 10:4.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit magnus domini consiliarius, ut ibi: <i>Nemini dixeritis uisionem hanc.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He was the Lord’s great confidant, as then: <i>tell this vision to Nobody.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to Mat. 17:9.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Eciam ex speciali auctoritate concedit ei ut possit cum duabus contrahere matrimonium, iuxta decretum:'Nemo licet habere duas uxores.'</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Furthermore, the Lord allows him by special decree to enter into marriage with two women, according to the doctrine: “Nobody is permitted to have two wives.”
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>There is no specific source.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Fuit iste Nemo magnus in audacia, quia cum Iudei non fuerunt ausi manus mittere in Ihesum, ipse audacter irruit in eum et ligauit eum et sepeliuit,
							iuxta illud: <i>Et Nemo in eum misit manum.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> This Nobody was great in boldness, since when the Jews did not dare to lay hands on Jesus, he bravely rushed at him, tied him up, and buried him,
								according to the following: <i>And Nobody laid hands on him.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to John 7:44.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>

				<p n="8">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">In fine iste sanctus Nemo accusauit eam mulierem deprehensam in adulterio, iuxta illud dictum domini: <i>Mulier, qui sunt qui te accusabat?</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Finally, this Saint Nobody accused the woman caught in adultery, according to the following saying of the Lord: <i>Woman, who are they who accused you?</i>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"><i>Nemo te contempnauit?</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"><i>Has Nobody condemned you?</i></rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Respondit mulier: <i>Nemo, domine.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The woman answered: <i>Nobody, Lord.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to John 8:10-11.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Item ut omnem eius concludam dignitatem, iste Nemo, uana huius mundi uidens, conscendit ad celestia, iuxta illud Iob ii: <i>Nemo ascendit in celum.</i></lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Also, so that I might conclude his dignity, this Nobody, seeing the emptiness of this world, ascended to the heavens, according to the following
								from Job 2: <i>Nobody ascended into heaven.</i>
								<note type="critical" anchored="true">
									<p>This refers to John 3:13 – another egregiously false in-text citation.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Ut illuc ascendamus hoc prestet nobis deus trinus et unus.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">May we ascend there, where God, triune and one, may stand before us.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">Amen.</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Amen.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
