<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt' >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Song of Peter</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Robert Forke</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robert Forke</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Mae Velloso-Lyons</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The Song of Peter is the oldest surviving hymn in the German language. Hymns are a form of religious poetry sung in praise of God, often during religious ceremonies such as the Mass celebrated by medieval Christians. The tradition of Christian hymns was popularised in the West by Ambrose of Milan (c.340 –397 CE), who wrote hymns in Latin (though some claim that Hilary of Poitiers was the first composer of Latin hymns). Hymns in the “Ambrosian” style remained a very popular part of Christian worship until the Council of Trent (1545-63 CE), when most hymns were abolished from Catholic liturgical practice. The Song of Peter is transmitted with neumes, an early medieval form of musical notation, which suggests that it was supposed to be sung, possibly during religious processions. Written down in the first third of the tenth century CE in a Bavarian dialect of the Old High German language, it is one of the earliest examples of end rhyme in a German text. This was a change from the Germanic alliterative verse which dominated earlier, where the same consonants were repeated within the same line. It is unknown whether the author of the Song of Peter was influenced by the end rhymes of Otfrid of Weißenburg's Gospel Harmony (composed c.870 CE) or whether the Song of Peter predates Otfrid’s work. The song calls upon St. Peter the Apostle in three strophes of three lines. Each strophe ends with the refrain, “Kyrie eleyson. Christe eleyson”, which is Greek for “God, have mercy. Christ, have mercy.” The refrain points to Peter's special role in the Christian faith as the overseer of admission into Heaven (see, for example, the Biblical passage Matthew 16:19: “I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven; whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven”).</p>
				<p>The song survives in only one manuscript, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek Clm 6260, now held in Munich. The manuscript originally stems from the Freising Cathedral library and was written in the second half of the ninth century CE. It contains discussions, in Latin, of religious texts. The Song of Peter was written down later, on the very last page below the end of Hrabanus’s Maurus Commentary on Genesis (f.158v).</p>
				<p>Bostock, John Knight, Kenneth Charles King, and D. R. McLintock. A Handbook on Old High German Literature. Clarendon Press, 1976.</p>
				<p>Haug, Walter and Benedikt Konrad Vollmann. Frühe Deutsche Literatur und Lateinische Literatur in Deutschland 800-1150. Deutscher Klassiker Verlag, 1991. Old High German text and modern German translation: pp.130-131; Commentary and extensive bibliography: pp.1117-1120</p>
				<p>Liberman, Anatoly. “Petruslied.” German Writers and Works of the Early Middle Ages: 800 – 1170, edited by Will Hasty and James Hardin. Gale Research, 1995, pp. 252-254.</p>
				<p>McLintock, David R. “Petruslied.” Dictionary of the Middle Ages, vol. 9, edited by Joseph Reese Strayer. Charles Scribners Sons, 1987, p. 546.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek Clm 6260 f.158v</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Petruslied</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Song of Peter</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"The Song of Peter" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>Abbreviations in the Old High German text are expanded, spelling and punctuation otherwise follow the manuscript.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>

				<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
			</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<facsimile>
		<graphic url="BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v.png" xml:id="BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Petruslied</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Song of Peter</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<pb ed="#Transcription" facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
			<fw facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v" type="header" place="margin-topright"></fw>
			<pb ed="#Translation" facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
			<fw facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v" type="header" place="margin-topright"></fw>
			<lg>
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">﻿Unsar trohtin hat farsalt sancte petre giuualt daz er mac ginerian</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Lord gave Saint Peter the power to save</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ze imo dingenten man. kyrie eleyson christe eleyson.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">those entrusted to him. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Er hapet ouh mit vuortun himriches portun. dar in mach er skerian</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With words, he also guards the gates of heaven through which he admits</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">den er uuili nerian. kirie eleison criste [eleyson]</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">those whom he wishes to save. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.
							<note type="critical" anchored="true">
								<p>Peter’s words can possibly be understood as the key to the gates of Heaven. According to Haug (1991), p.1119, this idea is present in other Latin hymns.
								</p>
							</note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pittemes den gotes trut alla samant uparlut. daz er uns firtanen giuuer</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let us entreat God’s disciple, loudly and in unison, so that he grants</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">do ginaden<note type="critical" anchored="true">
								<p>This verse can also be found in Otfrid’s Gospel Harmony (I7,28), but with the Frankish form 'ginadon which results in an assonance instead of a rhyme.
								</p>
							</note>. kirie eleyson criste eleyson</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"> mercy to us sinners. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>