<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt' >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Song of Peter</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Robert Forke</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robert Forke</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Mae Velloso-Lyons</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek Clm 6260 f.158v</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Petruslied</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Song of Peter</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"The Song of Peter" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>Abbreviations in the Old High German text are expanded, spelling and punctuation otherwise follow the manuscript.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>

				<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
			</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
		<facsimile>
		<graphic url="BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v.png" xml:id="BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
	</facsimile>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Petruslied</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Song of Peter</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<pb ed="#Transcription" facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
			<fw facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v" type="header" place="margin-topright"></fw>
			<pb ed="#Translation" facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v"/>
			<fw facs="#BSB_Clm_6260_f.158v" type="header" place="margin-topright"></fw>
			<lg>
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">﻿Unsar trohtin hat farsalt sancte petre giuualt daz er mac ginerian</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Lord gave Saint Peter the power to save</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ze imo dingenten man. kyrie eleyson christe eleyson.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">those entrusted to him. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Er hapet ouh mit vuortun himriches portun. dar in mach er skerian</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With words, he also guards the gates of heaven through which he admits</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">den er uuili nerian. kirie eleison criste [eleyson]</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">those whom he wishes to save. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.
							<note type="critical" anchored="true">
								<p>Peter’s words can possibly be understood as the key to the gates of Heaven. According to Haug (1991), p.1119, this idea is present in other Latin hymns.
								</p>
							</note>
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Pittemes den gotes trut alla samant uparlut. daz er uns firtanen giuuer</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let us entreat God’s disciple, loudly and in unison, so that he grants</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">do ginaden<note type="critical" anchored="true">
								<p>This verse can also be found in Otfrid’s Gospel Harmony (I7,28), but with the Frankish form 'ginadon which results in an assonance instead of a rhyme.
								</p>
							</note>. kirie eleyson criste eleyson</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"> mercy to us sinners. Kyrie eleison. Christe eleison.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>