<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Loss of Buda and Captivity of Bálint Török</title>
				<author>Sebastian Tinódi</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>Tinódi Sebestyén összes költeménye in the Hungarian Electronic Library</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Maria Dobozy</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
				<p>Sebastian Tinódi (1505–1556) was an excellent lutanist, a prolific poet and a popular performer of secular “event songs”. In 1554, he printed his poems with accompanying melodies in the first songbook ever published in Hungarian, Cronica. Its success fulfilled his stated goal to celebrate and commemorate the heroic deeds of Hungarians for both his contemporaries and for posterity. His songs are comparable to the narrative songs that memorialized and commented on epoch-making events, and which were common throughout Europe in the 15th and 16th centuries.</p>
				<p>“The Loss of Buda and Captivity of Bálint Török” deals with very recent events in Hungarian history, namely the loss of the city of Buda following the death of King Janos I of Hungary. Initially the hero, Török, allies his forces with the Turks to defeat the Habsburg besiegers. Even though Török and his allies are victorious, the Ottoman sultan, Suleiman I, takes control of the city and imprisons Török, sending the queen and the infant king—Janos’s son, Janos II—to Transylvania to set up a Hungarian court as vassals of the Ottoman Empire. Few lines are devoted to recounting the action; instead the hero is repeatedly praised for his loyalty. In this way, the narrative forms the frame for a lament: a lament for the loss of the capitol city, for the loss of the king, and for the poet’s loss of his patron.</p>
				<p>Previously, scholars studied Tinódi primarily for what they assumed to be a historically accurate depiction of events. Recognizing the tendentious nature of the genre of event poetry, the emphasis has more recently shifted to assessing his literary impact and the possible influences of other European literatures on his work. In this song, Tinódi imitates oral compositional style, which can be seen in the redundancy, repetititon and formulaic phrases—all typical features of oral style in Hungarian. Indeed, his repetitions are often reminiscent of a refrain (some of these repetitious phrases have been omitted from the translation so that the text will not be tedious for the modern reader). Another notable stylistic feature is the direct address to the audience. Tinódi’s compositions were all intended for performance, and he himself sang them to various audiences. Direct address would have helped to enliven his performance and establish a closer rapport with his listeners.</p>
				<p>Cronica, Sebastian Tinódi’s songbook of 1544, contains this song and twenty-one others together with his own musical compositions. It was printed in Kolozsvár (Cluj-Napoca, Romania). A few original copies are extant as facsimile editions. The source for this translation is the standardized transcription accessible on the Hungarian Electronic Library website, Tinódi Sebestyén összes költeménye: http://mek.oszk.hu/01100/01100/index.phtml.</p>
				<p>Czigány, Lóránt. Oxford History of Hungarian Literature from the Earliest Times to the Mid-1970s. Oxford, Clarendon, 1984, pp. 40–43. http://mek.niif.hu/02000/02042/html/index.html</p>
				<p>Short, reliable introduction to Tinódi. Available electronically.</p>
				<p>Dobozy, Maria. “Two Cultural Perspectives on the Battle of Lippa, Transylvania, 1551.” Fifteenth Century Studies, vol. 38, 2013, pp. 21–39.</p>
				<p>Discusses the influence of German event poetry on Tinódi and the historical accuracy of the two poems.</p>
				<p>Dobozy, Maria. “Sebestyén Tinódi Lantos.” Christian-Muslim Relations 1500 - 1900, edited by David Thomas. Brill, 2015. http://dx.doi.org/ 10.1163/2451-9537_cmrii_COM_26618</p>
				<p>Seláf, Levente. “Between Lyric and Epic: The Great Turkish War in German, Italian and Hungarian Ereignisliedern.” Controversial Poetry, 1400–1635, edited by Judith Keßler, Ursula Kundert, and Johan Oosterman. Brill, 2020, pp. 61–86.</p>
				<p>Analyses genre and function of Italian, German, and Hungarian poetry that deals with religious, political and military conflicts.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><ref target="http://mek.oszk.hu/01100/01100/index.phtml">Tinódi Sebestyén összes költeménye, Hungarian Electronic Library</ref></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Buda veszéséröl és Terek Bálint fogságárol</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Loss of Buda and Captivity of Bálint Török</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"The Loss of Buda and Captivity of Bálint Török" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>The goal has been to render the Hungarian in clear and smooth English prose. The original is composed of 50 mono-rhyming quatrains of morphemic rhymes using the popular 12 syllable line. This translation conforms to the quatrain structure while avoiding rhyme and meter. Each stanza expresses a complete thought or idea. This parallel stanza format facilitates comparison of translation to original. Punctuation follows the needs of modern English. Sometimes sentences have been split to accommodate English syntax and others have been connected. Names of well known, high-ranking persons have been anglicized; others have been modernized. All Hungarian names are given surname second. Places and persons named are capitalized and identified in the notes. Specific historical details mentioned are also explained in footnotes. Sections containing direct address are marked by syntax as the singer’s voice, and seldom lend themselves to setting off with quotation marks. Quotation marks are used only to indicate the speech of a character within the text.</p>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Siralom adaték sok rendbéli népnek,<lb/>Ki hírével lészön föld kerekségének,<lb/>Mert vége lőn immár mi víg életünknek,<lb/>Eszt tevé fogsága kegyös vezérünknek.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Lamentation is the fate of many regular soldiers<lb/>on hearing the tidings going around the entire globe<lb/>because our joy-filled life has come to an end,<lb/>caused by the imprisonment of our benevolent commander.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Esztökben vegyétök ez úrnak fogságát,<lb/>Jó Terek Bálintnak tőlünk így elváltát,<lb/>Lám, minden értötte jámborul szolgáltát,<lb/>Mindenik urának mindönben hív voltát.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Keep secure in your memory the captivity of this magnate,<lb/>the forced departure of trustworthy Bálint Török.<lb/>Everyone can well see his dependable service<lb/>as well as his unfailing loyalty toward each of his lords.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>This appears to imply that Bálint Török has been loyal to 3 parties in sequence, that is,  Ferdinand of Austria, Sultan Suleiman, and King János I Szapolya of Hungary. See Ferenc Szakály. <hi rend="italic">Tinódi Sebesytén Kronika</hi>. Budapest: Europa Kiado, 1984 p. 570.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Benn Erdélyben lőn János király halála,<lb/>Ottan ő udvara igen megpusztula,<lb/>Urakban egynéhány mert ott meghasonla,<lb/>Kik miatt ez ország ím mind elpusztula.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When King János died in Transylvania,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>John (János) I Szapolya, Governor (<hi rend="italic">voivode</hi>) of Transylvania and King of Hungary, 1526-1540.</p></note><lb/>his court there turned barren as<lb/>several of the magnates split into factions;<lb/>because of them this entire country crumbles.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="4" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ágyúkkal némötök ottan készülének,<lb/>Kincses Buda alá hamar sietének,<lb/>Törést és nagy rontást ők nagyot tevének,<lb/>Azért az Budában nem férköszhetének.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Germans made ready their canons<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The besiegers are called “Germans” and their place of origin is called Germany, although these are German speakers and other mercenaries from Habsburg territories, and not necessarily imperial troops.</p></note><lb/>in their hurry to reach treasured Buda.<lb/>They succeeded in a great breaching of walls<lb/>but they cannot occupy the castle of Buda.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Begun March 12, 1541 by Ferdinand’s army, the siege lasted 6 months.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="5" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Serénsége vala jó Terek Bálintnak,<lb/>Mert igen hív vala az király fiának,<lb/>És ővéle öszve az szegín országnak,<lb/>Rettenetös vala mind az némöt pártnak.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Worthy Bálint Török is much occupied<lb/>because he’s completely faithful to the king’s son<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>This is John Sigismund, King elect of Hungary and Prince of Transylvania, 1540-1571.</p></note><lb/>binding himself to the struggling nation<lb/>and intimidating the Habsburg party.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="6" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Terek császár hallá némötnek erejét,<lb/>Hamar készítteté az ő nagy erejét,<lb/>Basáit, szancsákit, sok rendbéli népét,<lb/>Memhet basát hagyá, mint császári képét.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Turkish Sultan learns the strength of the German troops<lb/>and quickly assembles his strong forces,<lb/>collects his pashas, sanjaks and many regular troops,<lb/>appoints Mehmet Pasha his commander-in-chief.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="7" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Igen parancsolá császár az basának,<lb/>Hitöt, szép szót írna az magyar uraknak,<lb/>Jelösben mindennél jó Terek Bálintnak,<lb/>Szóval, ajándékval magad ajáld annak.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Sultan issues orders to his pasha to send<lb/>with sweet words assurances to the Hungarian magnates<lb/>and most especially to daring Bálint Török:<lb/>“With words and gifts seek his good will.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="8" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Az basa indula, Eszékre ha juta,<lb/>Jó Terek Bálintnak hamar elírata,<lb/>Nagy szép szókkal őtet hozzá hívattatá,<lb/>Minden jóval lenne, császár aszt fogatta.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the pasha set out, arriving in Eszék,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Osijek, Croatia</p></note><lb/>rapidly sending to brave Bálint Török<lb/>his summons with many gracious words:<lb/>“All will go well; the sultan has promised.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="9" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nagy gongya lőn erre jó Terek Bálintnak,<lb/>Eszt ő megjelönté fő-fő szolgáinak,<lb/>Oly tanács adaték ez nemes úrfinak,<lb/>Hitlevelét kérje az terek császárnak.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This missive worries Török gravely,<lb/>he conveys this to his most trusted retainers.<lb/>They advise the nobly born man to<lb/>ask for safe conduct from the Turkish sultan.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="10" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Úrfi így felele bánatos beszédben:<lb/>„Ha én hitöt kérök az én levelemben,<lb/>Kezd kétségök lenni az én hívségömben,<lb/>De csak bízom magam én jó Istenömben.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The nobleman responds with sorrowful words:<lb/>“If I ask for safe conduct in my letter<lb/>then they will begin to question my loyalty.<lb/>Thus I place my trust in my own true God.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="11" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sokak szidnak engöm az hajas tereknek,<lb/>Szerető uraim nyilván vagyon néktök,<lb/>Terek barátsága úgy nem kell kedvemnek,<lb/>Mint olyan hitetlen ragadozó ebeknek.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Many defame me as the hairy Turk.<lb/>My loving nobles, it’s clear to you<lb/>that I do not favor the friendship of the Turks<lb/>because they are infidel dogs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="12" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Lám, mi nem láthatánk oly jó fejedelmet,<lb/>Ki megrontja vala gonosz terek népet,<lb/>Szabadítja vala ez keresztyén népet,<lb/>Értök szerencsére vetöm én fejemet.”</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Now since we can find no good ruler<lb/>who could defeat the wicked Turkish army<lb/>and liberate our Christian nation,<lb/>for them I will wager my head.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="13" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Indula, Tárdánál az táborban juta,<lb/>Egy sátort az basa hamar vonyattata,<lb/>Ott nagy tisztösséggel abban szállattatá,<lb/>Fő-fő terekekkel néki udvartata.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He departs and finds his way to the Turkish camp at Tárda.<lb/>Immediately the pasha sets up a tent for him<lb/>and arranges elegant accommodations.<lb/>The high-ranking Turks come to do him honor.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="14" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Jó Verbőczi Imre nála kedves vala,<lb/>Mint egy attyafiát úgy szereti vala,<lb/>Mert nagy szíve szerént néki szolgál vala,<lb/>Basa sátorában akkort véle vala.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Worthy Imre Werböczi treats him with affection.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Imre Werböczi is king’s commissioner.</p></note><lb/>Because he loves him like a brother,<lb/>he serves him with great generosity of heart;<lb/>they are together in the pasha’s tent.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="15" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Terekek csudálják szépön termött voltát,<lb/>Mert régön hallották ő jó vitéz voltát,<lb/>Azomban elhozák császár ajándokát,<lb/>Azután elhozák basa ajándokát.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Turks admire his well-proportioned beauty<lb/>for they have long heard of his famed prowess.<lb/>First they bring in the sultan’s gifts,<lb/>then they bring in the pasha’s gifts:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="16" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Öltözött lovakat, aranyas ruhákat,<lb/>Avval az császárnak nagy kegyelmes voltát,<lb/>És Memhet basának minden barátságát<lb/>Úrfi ott ajánlá nagy hív szolgálattyát.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">well-trained horses, gold-stitched clothing.<lb/>The sultan thus displays his generosity<lb/>and Mehmet Pasha his unreserved friendship.<lb/>The young lord offers his loyal service [in return].</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="17" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Rajta az basa lőn oly nagy vigasságban,<lb/>Hamar béhívatá az ő sátorában,<lb/>Szép édös beszéddel lőn véle tanácsban,<lb/>Hogy császárnak lenne hív szolgálattyában.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The pasha was greatly pleased with him<lb/>and soon invited him to his own tent.<lb/>He began the council with honey-sweet speech<lb/>to commit him to the sultan’s loyal service.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="18" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Termetét, szömélyét basa megszömlélé,<lb/>Udvara népit es széllel megszömlélé,<lb/>Szebben termött embört soholt ő nem lele,<lb/>Az úrfival basa ott arról beszélle:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The pasha observed his bearing, his demeanor<lb/>and reviewed each of his court retainers as well.<lb/>Never had he seen a more stalwart man.<lb/>The pasha then speaks to the young lord,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="19" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Udvara népével Budára sietne,<lb/>Szolgálna császárnak, és ott véle lenne,<lb/>Mit császár akarna, mindaz-tévő lenne.<lb/>Úrfi elbúcsúzék, basátúl elméne.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">asks him to advance his troops to Buda<lb/>with due speed and there help the sultan, stand by his side,<lb/>do the sultan’s bidding according to his needs.<lb/>The young lord takes his leave from the pasha and departs.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="20" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sok múlatság nem lőn akkort ő dolgába,<lb/>Házátúl siete az romlott Budába.<lb/>Immár basa vala Kányánál táborba,<lb/>Szent Gellérnél vannak némötök barlangba.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He was not pleased with this turn of events.<lb/>Leaving home, he hurried to battered Buda.<lb/>By now the pasha has encamped by Kánya<lb/>and the Germans are ensconced in the caves of St. Gellért Hill.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="21" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dunát béállották nagy vízi erővel,<lb/>Magokat béásták környül nagy vermökvel,<lb/>Megrakták álgyúkval, vannak bátor szível,<lb/>Memhet basát várják fejenként víg kedvvel.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Danube they have secured with artillery boats.<lb/>They have dug protective trenches around themselves<lb/>and filled them with canons, those brave-hearted men.<lb/>Each one awaits Mehmet Pasha with happy anticipation.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="22" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">El-bé Terek Bálint ha juta Budába,<lb/>Az budai sok jó lőn nagy vigasságba,<lb/>Az magyar urakval lőn ő oly tanácsba:<lb/>Népöket szállíták kinn az hegy aljába.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Once Bálint Török arrived safely in Buda,<lb/>the many good warriors fell to rejoicing.<lb/>He came to take counsel with the Hungarian magnates:<lb/>their soldiers they transported to the base of the hill.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="23" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tőnek ostromokat az némöt táborra,<lb/>Elvegy terekekvel együtt mennek harcra,<lb/>Kösztök Török Bálint szíve bátorságra,<lb/>Csudaképpen siet némötök sáncára.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They [Hungarians] pounded the German camp.<lb/>The Turks joined forces with them and entered the fighting.<lb/>Foremost among them, Bálint Török of courageous heart,<lb/>rushed marvelously swiftly at the German encampment.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="24" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Jó Príni Pétörrel ő szömbe lött vala,<lb/>Ki nagy szép szavával igen kéri vala,<lb/>Hogy az terek mellől hamar elállana,<lb/>Mert az császár hiti végre őt megcsalná.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He came upon the brave Peter Príni<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Príni is Peter Perényi, a powerful magnate, supported at times King John Szapolya and Ferdinand of Habsburg at others. His warning of Turkish duplicity is confirmed in historical sources. Szakáy, p. 572.</p></note><lb/>who with eloquent speech tried to convince him<lb/>to leave the Turkish alliance right away<lb/>because the sultan will betray him in the end.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="25" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nagy hitleveleket néki jelent vala,<lb/>Császár, basa, szancsák kiket attak vala,<lb/>Mely hitlevelekre császárhoz ment vala,<lb/>Hittel őt megcsalván, megfogatta vala.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Of what value are those letters of safe conduct,<lb/>the ones given by sultan, pasha, and sanjak?<lb/>Whoever has relied on them and gone before the sultan<lb/>has been betrayed, has been imprisoned.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="26" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ott jó Terek Bálint ezzel sem gondola,<lb/>Urához, herceghöz igaz szível vala,<lb/>Kiért ő halálát ott nem szánja vala,<lb/>Attya szerelméjért ím mely nagy kárt valla.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But valiant Bálint Török remains undaunted.<lb/>He stands with resolute heart behind his lord John Sigismund<lb/>for whom he would not regret giving his own life.<lb/>For love of his father [the late king], take note what a grave loss he suffers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="27" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dráván terek császár immár elkült vala,<lb/>Az némöt táborba hamar hír jött vala,<lb/>Császár hatalmátúl úgy rettentek vala,<lb/>Titkon Duna vizén ők költöznek vala.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Turkish sultan has already crossed the Drava River.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The Drava River valley was the chief passage through which invaders from the southeast came into Hungary and Austria.</p></note><lb/>The German encampment soon hears word of it;<lb/>they so fear the sultan’s might<lb/>that secretly they retreat across the Danube.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="28" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Jó Pest várasában sokan elkelének,<lb/>Bennök az táborba kik ott rekedének,<lb/>Terek, magyar miatt mind megöletének,<lb/>Terekek úsztatnak, sokan elkelének.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Many Germans cross the river to Pest, the fair city.<lb/>Those who remain in the encampment<lb/>are all killed by the Turks and Hungarians<lb/>as many Turks chase them across the river.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="29" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nagy hamar terekek Pestben bémenének,<lb/>Nagy gazdagságokat, álgyúkat nyerének,<lb/>Némötország felé némötök sietnek,<lb/>Vízerővel öszve el-felsietének.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Turks move into Pest rapidly<lb/>and capture much equipment and several canons.<lb/>The Germans head directly toward Germany,<lb/>fleeing together in their artillery boats.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="30" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Császár Scambriához azomba eljuta,<lb/>Nagy szép sátorokat ott ő felvonyata,<lb/>Nagy hálákat ada, Allát kiáltata,<lb/>Az ő basáihoz víg kedvet mutata.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Meanwhile Sultan Suleiman reaches Sicambria<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Sicambria (Obuda) is the old town of Buda, upriver of Buda hill and castle.</p></note><lb/>and pitches large, elegant tents.<lb/>He calls out to Allah, giving him profuse thanks<lb/>and shows his pashas a well-pleased countenance.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="31" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">János királnénak Budában izené,<lb/>Hogy az királ fiát őnéki küldené,<lb/>Menni főúr vagyon, őt alákésérné,<lb/>Mindenik hívségét azzal jelöntené.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He sends to John’s Queen Isabella in Buda<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Isabella (Jagiello) widowed queen of John I. The baby and heir to the throne is John II Sigismund. Suleiman had promised to support him.</p></note><lb/>that she should send the king’s son to him.<lb/>All the lords were to accompany him<lb/>thereby to demonstrate their loyalty.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Specifically orders the king’s counselors to come.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="32" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Vala nagy bánattya királné asszonnak,<lb/>Véle egyötömbe az magyar uraknak,<lb/>Nem hihetnek vala nyilván az császárnak,<lb/>Azért királfival aláindulának.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The queen is sorely distressed<lb/>as are the Hungarian lords along with her.<lb/>Clearly they cannot trust the sultan; yet<lb/>nevertheless they escort the prince.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="33" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">János herceg vala aranyas szekérben,<lb/>Az urak körűle vannak késérésben,<lb/>Mikoron jutának császár eleiben,<lb/>Császár látá őket, vala víg kedvében.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Prince János is in a golden carriage.<lb/>The lords surround him and protect him.<lb/>When they reach the sultan’s presence,<lb/>he observes them and is well pleased.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="34" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tanácsában császár mondá az basáknak,<lb/>Hercegöt megadnák királné asszonnak,<lb/>Az urakban ötöt megtartósztatnának,<lb/>Hercegöt felvivék, urak meg maradának.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In council, the sultan tells his pashas<lb/>the prince is to be returned to the queen [his mother]<lb/>and five of the lords will be detained.<lb/>They then send the prince back; the lords must remain.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The five magnates detained were Brother George Martinuzzi regent, István Werböczi, Péter Petrovics, Bálint Török, Orbán Batthyány. Szakály, p. 570.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="35" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Az basák beszéllik hatalmas császárnak<lb/>Nagy jó vitésségét jó Terek Bálintnak,<lb/>Mindönöknél feljebb dícséretöt adnak,<lb/>Hogy mind az két párton jobb vitézt nem monnak.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The pashas describe to the powerful sultan<lb/>the great bravery of undaunted Bálint Török.<lb/>They praise him above all others<lb/>claiming that in both camps no commander is better:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="36" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">„Te felségöd hogyha mast esztelbocsáttya,<lb/>Vannak sok vitézi, hogyha feltámasztja,<lb/>Az Drávát felségöd míg által halaggya,<lb/>Hátul való néped ő mind levágattya.”</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“If your majesty permits him to leave now<lb/>he has plenty of soldiers to call on.<lb/>Then while your majesty crosses the Drava River,<lb/>he will cut down your rear guard.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="37" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Eszt császár hogy hallá, hagyá őt megfogni,<lb/>És az több urakat Budába bocsátni.<lb/>Budának várasát hagyá elfoglalni,<lb/>Az szolgáló népet mind el-kibocsátni.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After the sultan hears this, he orders him arrested<lb/>and the remaining lords sent back to Buda.<lb/>He orders the city of Buda occupied<lb/>and all the hired troops expelled.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="38" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Szép szóval úrfiat vivék egy sátorban,<lb/>Ott az több urakat bocsáták Budában,<lb/>Terekek menének sokan az várasban,<lb/>Császárnak foglalák, vannak nagy vígságban.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">With sweet words they took the worthy lord into a tent;<lb/>the remaining lords they sent back to Buda.<lb/>A great many Turks invaded the city,<lb/>taking control gladly on behalf of the sultan.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="39" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Igen kiáltatá császár nagy felszóval:<lb/>„Az ki szolgáló nép, menne hamarságval,<lb/>Mert fél óra múlva büntetik szablyával.”<lb/>Minden, ki eszt hallya, siet gyorsaságval.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The sultan had a warning loudly proclaimed:<lb/>“Those who are hired for service, leave immediately<lb/>or in a half hour you will be punished with the saber.”<lb/>All who hear this take flight.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="40" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Igen fosztogaták őket, úgy bocsáták,<lb/>Az királné asszont mind felrakottaták,<lb/>Minden ő kincsével el-kiindíttaták,<lb/>Császár hagyásából békével bocsáták.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They [Turks] stripped them of their valuables before they let them go.<lb/>The queen they packed up<lb/>with her treasures and sent her off<lb/>in peace, as the sultan had ordered.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="41" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Gyorsan az urakkal asszony kisiete,<lb/>Lippa felé császár őtet késérteté,<lb/>Budának szép várát sírva megtekinté,<lb/>Azzal önnönmagát igen keseríté.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The queen hastened away with the lords.<lb/>The sultan gave them an escort to Lippa.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Queen Isabella and John Sigismund set up the Hungarian court in Lippa,Transylvania.</p></note><lb/>As she looked back at beautiful Buda castle, she wept;<lb/>it caused her even deeper grief.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="42" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ez jó Terek Bálint marada fogságban,<lb/>Rusztán basa tartja az ő sátorában,<lb/>Szolgáinak izent ő nagy bánatjában,<lb/>Hívséggel lennének ő szolgálattyokban.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Worthy Bálint Török remained captive;<lb/>Rustan Pasha held him in his own tent.<lb/>In his great distress he sent to his retainers<lb/>a request that they remain in faithful service.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="43" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Terek Jánost, Ferencöt, néki két szép fiát<lb/>Hallgatnák egyemben ő asszony szép társát,<lb/>Fogadnák mindenben ő parancsolását,<lb/>Gondolnák az Pökri Lajosnak példáját.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">János and Ferenc Török, his two handsome sons<lb/>together with his fair wife desired to attend him<lb/>and to carry out his every command.<lb/>They would follow the example of Lajos Pökri.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The comparison is unclear. Lajos Pekry fought intrepidly against the Turks. Ferdinand arrested him 1537. He then spent 6 yrs in Turkish captivity whereas Török spent 9. Tinodi could not have known this in 1541. Szakály, p. 571.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="44" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hitlen terek császár hitinek nem álla,<lb/>Ez nemes úrfiat véle vivé alá,<lb/>Az Szulimán basát Budán hatta vala,<lb/>Így nagy nyereséggel ő el-alászálla.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The faithless Turkish sultan went back on his word.<lb/>He took the noble lord with him and<lb/>left Suleiman Pasha in charge of Buda.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Suleiman Pasha was the first commander of Buda. Szakály, p. 571.</p></note><lb/>With great winnings he then departed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="45" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Fohászkodik vala és igen sír vala<lb/>Jó Terek Bálintné, hogy hírt nem hall vala,<lb/>Mert ő vitéz urát igen félti vala,<lb/>Hogy az terek hiti végre meg ne csalná.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Bálint Török’s virtuous spouse prays and weeps constantly<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>She was Kathleen Pemflinger.</p></note><lb/>for she has received no word from him<lb/>and she fears for that valiant man’s life,<lb/>fears that ultimately the Turks will betray him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="46" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Egy levelet néki ha megmutatának,<lb/>Hogy fogsága volna ő vitéz urának,<lb/>Erő szakaszkodék kezének, lábának,<lb/>Földhöz üté magát, ott sokan sírának.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One letter is shown to her<lb/>that her courageous husband is being held captive.<lb/>The strength in her arms and legs melts,<lb/>she throws herself to the ground; many lament loudly.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="47" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Csudaképpen töri, fárasztja ő magát,<lb/>Sírva apolgatja futosó két fiát,<lb/>Oly igen kesergi urának fogságát,<lb/>És az két fiával az nagy árvaságát.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">She beats herself tirelessly, punishes her body<lb/>and with lamentation she cares for two strong sons.<lb/>She bemoans her husband’s captivity<lb/>and the distressing, orphaned status of her boys.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="48" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ígyen éjjel-nappal hallyák kesergését,<lb/>Immár nem alítja világban élését,<lb/>Hallya meg az Isten az ő könyörgését,<lb/>Hogy hamar láthassa ura megjövését.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Her wailing can be heard night and day.<lb/>No longer does she assert that he still lives;<lb/>yet beseeches God to hear her prayer<lb/>that she may see the homecoming of her lord.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="49" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ti jó keresztyénök, tegyünk áldozatot,<lb/>Hogy Isten hallgasson tőlünk imádságot,<lb/>És megszabadíccsa jó Terek Bálintot,<lb/>Hívön szolgálhassa ez szegín országot.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">You good Christians, let us make an offering<lb/>that God may accept our prayers<lb/>and set free our worthy Bálint Török.<lb/>May he faithfully serve this wretched land.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="50" type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ezörötszáznegyven és egy esztendőben<lb/>Budáról császárnak el-alámentében,<lb/>Szigetben ki szörzé, vala nagy fektében,<lb/>Vitéz urán való nagy kesergésében.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">After the Sultan departed from Buda,<lb/>in 1541, the author composed this<lb/>while in his sick bed in Sziget<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The court of Szigetvár, Baranya County.</p></note><lb/>out of great sadness for his valiant lord.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Since the Sultan withdrew about September 15, 1541, Tinódi probably composed this in October of that year.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
