<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Wessobrun Prayer</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<name>Björn Buschbeck</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Hannah Frakes and Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>The Wessobrunn Prayer is one of the only extant examples of Old High German alliterative verse, in which alliteration is the primary poetic feature. Notably it was intentionally preserved in a codex (manuscript book) of collected texts, including several Latin texts and German glosses. This is unusual: most extant Old High German texts were written in the margins and endpapers of manuscripts. Latin was preferred for church writing as the more prestigious and official language. The Wessobrunn Prayer is similar thematically and formally to the Old High German poem “Muspilli.” The codex has been dated to around 810 CE, and the prayer is written in Carolingian Miniscule (the standard script of the time). The prayer was named for the abbey at Wessobrunn in Bavaria where the codex resided for centuries before it was discovered and studied by philologists and eventually moved to the state library in Munich. The location where it was written and the identity of the author are unknown, though it was certainly someone with a knowledge of theology, perhaps a cleric or a monk. The prayer itself speculates about God and the universe before Creation, and emphasizes the power of the Holy Trinity and the nothingness before creation. There is a possible Anglo-Saxon influence: a star shaped rune is used for the common prefix “ga-,” and the format is similar to prayers used by Anglo-Saxon missionaries as they spread Christianity in Germany during the 8th century. Some of the language at the end of the prayer is parallel to the Nicene Creed, a declaration of faith standardized by the church in the 4th century. Scholars are interested in the Wessobrunn Prayer because of its unique poetic form. It is possible that there were many similar texts that did not survive.</p>
				<p>The Wessobrunn Prayer is held at the Bayerische Staatsbibliothek in Clm 22053, fol. 65v-66r.</p>
			</notesStmt>
						<sourceDesc>
							<p>Bayerische Staatsbibliothek Clm 22053 foll. 65v-66r</p>
							<listWit>
								<witness xml:id="Transcription">Das Wessobrunner Gebet</witness>
								<witness xml:id="Translation">The Wessobrun Prayer</witness>
							</listWit>
						</sourceDesc>
					</fileDesc>
					<encodingDesc>
						<projectDesc>
            				<p>"The Wessobrun Prayer" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
         				</projectDesc>
         				<editorialDecl>
	        				<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        				<interpretation>
        					<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
						</interpretation>
						<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
						</editorialDecl>
					</encodingDesc>
				</teiHeader>
				<facsimile>
				</facsimile>
				<text>
					<front>
						<div>
							<head>
								<title>
									<app>
										<lem wit="#Transcription">De Poeta / Das Wessobrunner Gebet</lem>
										<rdg wit="#Translation">Of the Creator / The Wessobrun Prayer</rdg>
									</app>
								</title>
							</head>
						</div>
					</front>
					<body>
						<l n="1">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">Dat gafregin ih mit firahim firiuuizzo meista,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">This I learned among men as the greatest wonder,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="2">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">dat ero ni uuas noh ûfhimil,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">That [once] there was neither earth nor heaven above,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="3">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">noh paum ... noh pereg ni uuas, ni ... nohheinîig,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">Nor was there tree ... nor mountain nor…. anything,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="4">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">noh sunna ni scein</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">nor did the sun shine,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="5">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">no mâno ni liuhta,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">nor did the moon glow,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="6">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">noh der mâreo sêo.</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">nor [was there] the great sea.</rdg>
							</app>

						</l>
						<l n="7">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">Dô dâr niuuiht ni uuas enteo ni uuenteo,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">When there was nothing, neither end nor change,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="8">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">enti dô uuas der eino almahtîco cot, manno miltisto, </lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">there was the one almighty God, the most generous of all beings,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="9">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">enti dâr uuârun auh manake mit inan cootlîhhe geistâ.</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">and with him there were many glorious spirits.</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="10">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">enti cot heilac…</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">And the holy God…</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="11">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">Cot almahtico,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">Almighty God,
								</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="12">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">du himil enti erda gaworachtos,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">You who created heaven and earth,
								</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="13">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">enti du mannun so manac coot forgapi,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">And gave men so many good blessings,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="14">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">forgip mir in dino ganada</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">in your mercy, grant me</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="15">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">rehta galaupa</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">true faith</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="16">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">enti cotan willeon,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">and good will,</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="17">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">wistom enti spachida enti craft,</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">wisdom and cleverness and strength</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="18">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">tiuflun za widarstantanne, enti arc za piwisanne endi dinan</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">to resist the devil, and to shun evil and</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
						<l n="19">
							<app>
								<lem wit="#Transcription">willeon za gauurchanne.</lem>
								<rdg wit="#Translation">to work your will.</rdg>
							</app>
						</l>
					</body>
				</text>
			</TEI>