<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM "http://www.menota.org/menotaP5.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'http://www.menota.org/menota-entities.txt' >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Concerning the Sun and the Moon</title>
				<author>Nicolaus Pergamenus</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Based on the edition by</resp>
					<name>Johann Georg Theodor Grässe</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Astrid Khoo</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Irene Han</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>This Dialogus Creaturarum (“Dialogue of Creatures”), is one of eight such texts published by the Global Medieval Sourcebook. It was composed in the fourteenth century and its authorship remains debated, though it was historically attributed to either Nicolaus Pergamenus, about whom little is known, or Magninus Mediolanensis (also known as Mayno de Mayneriis), who was a physician. In recent years, beginning with Ruelle 1985, scholars have tended towards the conclusion that the Dialogus was compiled in Milan, though not necessarily by Magninus.</p>
				<p>The text consists of 122 dialogues largely populated by anthropomorphic “creatures”, loosely defined; sections translated for the Global Medieval Sourcebook feature elements (fire, water), planetary bodies (the Sun, the Moon, Saturn, a cloud), animals (the leopard and unicorn), as well as a talking topaz. Each dialogue is further divided into two sections, the first part depicting an encounter between these creatures – two is the usual number, though some dialogues have one or three – that ends in a violent conflict. This experience is summed up in a moral, typically delivered by the defeated party, which is then exemplified in the second half of the dialogue through citations from historiography, literature, and sacred scripture. Common texts cited include the pagan authors Seneca the Younger and Valerius Maximus, along with the Christian writers Paul, Augustine, and John Chrystostom and compilations such as the Vitae patrum (“Lives of the Fathers”) and Legenda aurea (“Golden Legend”).</p>
				<p>The great precision with which these references are cited – often including book and chapter numbers – suggests that the Dialogus was designed as a reference text containing recommendations for further reading, and more specifically as a handbook for constructing sermons (as indicated in the Preface). This purpose does not, however, detract from its entertaining style, which derives in no small part from the passionate dialogue that takes place between the creatures and the fast-paced descriptions of their battles against one another. These features explain the popularity of the Dialogus, which ran through numerous editions from the late fifteenth century onwards: the illustrated text compiled by Gerard Leeu was printed eight times in the eleven years from 1480 to 1491: once in French, twice in Dutch, and five times in Latin.</p>
				<p>Two manuscript versions of the Dialogus Creaturarum exist. Of these, only the so-called “short redaction” has been printed; Gerard Leeu opted for this version of the text in the first Latin edition (1480) and all the vernacular translations are based upon it. This short redaction is attested in twelve manuscripts from the late fourteenth and early fifteenth centuries, and is thought to best reflect the original text, which was composed after 1326. This dating derives from the fact that it borrows heavily from a compilation, the Libellus qui intitulatur multifarium, which was compiled at Bologna in that year (see Ruelle 1985, p. 22). In contrast, the “long redaction” survives in only two manuscripts, both of which are comparatively late (in or after 1431): Toledo, Biblioteca capitular, 10-28 and Torino, Biblioteca Nazionale Universitaria, H. III. 6. In these manuscripts, the Dialogus Creaturarum is commonly presented under the title Contemptus Sublimitatis (“The Contempt of Worldly Power”), which reflects its structure as a handbook of moral examples.</p>
				<p>Cardelle de Hartman, Carmen and Estrella Pérez Rodríguez. “Las auctoritates del Contemptus Sublimitatis (Dialogus Creaturarum).” Auctor et auctoritas in Latinis medii aevi litteris/Author and Authorship in Medieval Latin Literature: Proceedings of the VIth Congress of the International Medieval Latin Committee (Benevento-Naples, November 9-13, 2010), edited by Edoardo D’Angelo and Jan Ziolkowski, SISMEL - Edizioni di Galluzzo, 2014, pp. 199-212. Demonstrates that instead of nine manuscripts as previously thought, there instead exist 15 complete manuscripts and a fragment, and outlines these manuscripts’ relationship to one another.</p>
				<p>Kratzmann, Gregory C, and Elizabeth Gee, editors. The Dialoges of Creatures Moralysed: A Critical Edition. Brill, 1988, pp. 1-64. Edition of the medieval English translation first published in 1530 (original author unknown), but the Introduction contains information on the translation history and dissemination of the Latin Dialogus more generally.</p>
				<p>Schmitt, Jean-Claude. “Recueils franciscains d’exempla et perfectionnement des techniques intellectuelles du XIIIe au XVe siècle.” Bibliothèque de l’École des chartes 135, 1977, pp. 5-21. Discusses the front matter in early manuscripts of the Latin Dialogus, which contained both a list of titles and an alphabetical index of moral lessons to facilitate citation.</p>
				<p>Rajna, Pio. “Intorno al cosiddetto Dialogus creaturarum ed al suo autore.” Giornale storico della letteratura italiana, vol. 10, 1887, pp. 75-113. Advances arguments for two possible authors: Nicolaus Pergamenus and the Milanese doctor Mayno de Mayneriis, with a strong preference for the letter, and summarises the style and contents of the Dialogus.</p>
				<p>Ruelle, Pierre, editor. Le “Dialogue des creatures”: Traduction par Colart Mansion (1482) du “Dialogus creaturarum’’ (XIVe siècle). Classe des Lettres et des Sciences Morales et Politiques, Collections des Anciens Auteurs Belges, n.s. 8, Palais des Académies, 1985, pp. 1-80. Annotated edition of the medieval French translation by Colart Mansion, but the Introduction outlines the manuscript tradition and authorship of the Latin Dialogus.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Nicolas de Bergame &#91;Nicolaus Pergamenus&#93;, <hi rend="italic>">Dialogus creaturarum, moralisatus, jucundus, fabulis plenus</hi>, Goudae, 1481</p>				
				<p>Transcribed in Johann Georg Theodor Grässe,<hi rend="italic>"> Die beiden ältesten lateinischen fabelbücher des mittelalters</hi> Tübingen: Litterarischer verein in Stuttgart, 1880, pp. 138-139</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">De sole et luna</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Concerning the Sun and the Moon</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
				<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Concerning the Sun and the Moon" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
            	<p>The source used for transcription and translation is Johann Georg Theodor Grässe’s 1880 edition, entitled Die beiden ältesten lateinischen Fabelbücher des Mittelalters: des Bischofs Cyrillus Speculum Sapientiae und des Nicolaus Pergamenus Dialogus Creaturarum (Tübingen: Literarischen Verein in Stuttgart). This edition can be accessed online <ref target="https://archive.org/details/diebeidenltesten00grss/page/n4">here.</ref>  Grässe bases his text on the 1480 edition by Gerard Leeu, which is itself most likely derived from several of the manuscript copies; for a full list, see Cardelle de Hartman and Pérez Rodríguez 2014, pp. 199-200. A late medieval printed version of the text, dating from 1481, is held at the Bibliothèque nationale de France in Paris and is available to view online <ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k1519000f/f43.item">here.</ref></p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">De sole et luna, dial. 1.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Concerning the Sun and the Moon, the first dialogue</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p>
				<s n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">﻿Sol est secundum philosophum oculus mundi, jocunditas dei, pulchritudo coeli, mensura temporum, virtus et origo omnium nascentium, dominus plantarum, doctor et perfector omnium stellarum.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">According to the philosopher, the Sun is the world’s eye, God’s delight, the beauty of the sky, the measure of time, the virtue and origin of all living beings, the lord of the plants, not to mention the teacher and perfecter of all stars.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna vero, ut dicit Ambrosius in Exameron, est decor noctis, mater totius humoris et ministra, mensura temporum, dominatrix maris, immutatrix aëris et æmulatrix solis, et propter quod est æmulatrix solis, soli incepit detrahere et eum diffamare.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The moon, however, as Ambrosius says in his Exameron, is the night’s finery, the mother and servant of all liquids, the measure of time, the queen of the sea, the transformer of the air, and the imitator of the Sun. 
							<note type="critical" anchored="true">
								<p>
									 <hi rend="italic">‘Aemulatrix’</hi> is a play on words: not only ‘imitator’, which I have retained as the moon reflects the light of the Sun, but also ‘rival’.
								</p>
							</note>
							Since she had long been the Sun’s imitator, she began to withdraw from him and defame him.
						</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sol autem hoc sentiens loquutus est lunæ dicens: quare mihi detrahis et blasphemas?</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Sun, sensing this, spoke to the Moon, saying, “Why do you pull me down, and blaspheme me?</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ego semper te illuminavi et præcessi, tu autem semper me odis et impugnas.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I have always illuminated you, and gone ahead of you; yet now you hate me and attack me.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui luna: recede a me, quia te non diligo, cum propter tuum magnum splendorem ego nihil appretior in mundo; si non esses, seculo superlata essem ego.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To whom the Moon answered, “Depart from me for I do not love you. After all, thanks to your great splendor, the world does not value me at all. If you did not exist, I would be extolled as the greatest being in the world.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cui sol: ingrata sufficiat tibi magnificentia tua; si ego in die, tu vero in nocte perlustras.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In turn, the Sun responded, “Thankless creature, let your magnificence satisfy you. Indeed, I shine in the day, but you shine at night.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Obediamus ergo creatori nostro et noli superbire super me, sed me permitte lucere in die ac bona domini munire.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let us therefore obey our creator. Stop behaving arrogantly towards me, but allow me to shine during the day and guard over the good works of the Lord.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna vero magis animata recessit cum furore et stellas ad se clamavit aggregavitque magnum exercitum et cum sole prœliari cœit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At this, however, the Moon drew back, even more incensed with fury. She called the stars to herself, assembling a great army, and began to battle with the Sun.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sagittas enim mittebat adversus solem et cum jaculis percutere nitebatur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">She sent arrows against the Sun and strove to pierce him with darts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sol autem cum esset superius, descendit et lunam cum mucrone partitus est et stellas dejecit dicens: sie semper, cum eris rotunda, faciam tibi.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Nevertheless, since the Sun inhabited a higher sphere, he simply descended and split the Moon with the point of his sword. Then, casting down the stars, he said, “Thus shall I always cleave you when you are full.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hac enim de causa, ut fabulæ dicunt, luna nunquam rotunda permanet et stellæ casum habent.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As the stories say, it is because of this that the Moon never stays full and the stars fall.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Luna ergo coufusa in verecundia mansit dicens: turgidam melius partiri erat quam totam perire.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The thwarted Moon wallowed in shame, saying: “It is better to be divided when overfull than to perish entirely.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Sic enim multi superbi et elati volunt sibi dominari nec superiorem vel similem cupiunt habere.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In this way many of the proud and the powerful want to rule alone, and they desire to have neither superiors nor equals.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde glosa: superbia est elatio incensa quæ inferioribus despiciens superioribus et paribus satagit dominari.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Hence the following gloss: “Pride is incensed dignity which, despising inferiors, tries to rule over both superiors and equals.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nam velle quidem esse super omnes vituperabiliter malum est, sustinere alterum sibi similem gloriosum est, ut ait Chrysostomus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Indeed, to desire to outrank all others is horribly wicked, but it is glorious to hold another up as equal to oneself.” So says Chrysostomos.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">De talibus enim dicit poeta: tolluntur in altum ut lapsu graviori cadant.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Concerning such matters, the poet says, “The exalted are raised up so that they can experience a more grievous fall.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Et nota, quod, quanto est major assensus, tanto est major et periculosior casus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Moreover, it is known that the greater one’s popularity is, the more perilous his fall will be.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Qui enim de plano et infimo loco cadit, cito resurgit, qui autem de alto, cito surgere nequit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For he who falls from a flat and low place rises again swiftly, but he who falls from a height cannot rise again swiftly.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Rami enim arboris, ut dicit Chrysostomus, qui staut in summitate, cito a magno vento franguntur, qui autem sunt ad radicem, conservantur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As Chrysostomus says, “The tree’s branches growing aloft are quickly broken by a great wind, but those at the root are saved.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Unde etiam ait Quintus Curtius, quendam dixisse Alexandro quod, licet arbor magna crescat in altum, tamen vento citius exstirpatur, et licet leo tam sit superbus, tarnen parvarum avium efficitur cibus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Quintus Curius also relates that someone once said to Alexander, “Although a great tree might grow into the heavens, it will nevertheless be uprooted quickly by wind. Similarly, although a lion might be so proud, he will eventually be made into the food of small birds.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Quidam philosopbus veniens ad sepulturam Alexandri ait: heri non sufficiebat isti totus mundus, hodie quinque sepultura pedum est contentus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When arriving at Alexander’s tomb, one philosopher said, “Yesterday the whole world was not enough for this man. Today, he is content with his five-foot grave.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>