<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Antonio Loschi’s analogy</title>
				<author>Poggio Bracciolini</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription from</resp>
					<name>Basel 1538 (Reprinted in Poggio Bracciolini, Scripta in editione Basilensi anno 1538 collata. Ed. Riccardo Fulbini. Turin: Bottega d'Erasmo, 1964.)</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robin Wahlsten Böckerman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10032427r">Paris, BnF Latin 8770a</ref></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Comparatio Antonii Lusci</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Antonio Loschi’s analogy</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Antonio Loschi’s analogy" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Facetia 82</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Joke 82</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ciriacus Anconitanus, homo verbosus et nimium loquax, deplorabat aliquando, astantibus nobis, casum atque eversionem Imperii Romani,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Ciriaco d’Ancona, a verbose and far too talkative man, was once lamenting the fall and destruction of the Roman empire, while we were standing nearby.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">It seemed to cause him great pain.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">inque ea re vehementius angi videbatur.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tum Antonius Luscus, vir doctissimus, qui in coetu aderat, ridens hominis stultam curam:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then Antonio Loschi, a very learned man who was in our group, laughed at the man’s stupid worry and said:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Hic persimilis est,' inquit, 'viro Mediolanensi, qui, die festo, cum audisset unum e grege cantorum (qui gesta heroum ad plebem decantant) recitantem mortem Rolandi, qui septingentis iam ferme annis in proelio occubuit,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“He is very similar to a man from Milan who on a feast day heard a man from a group of singers (who were singing about the deeds of the heroes to the people) recite the Death of Roland, who had died in battle almost seven-hundred years ago.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">coepit acriter flere, atque inde,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The man started crying bitterly.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">cum uxor domum reversum maestum ac gementem vidisset, rogassetque quidnam accidisset novi:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Later when his wife upon his return saw him sad and mournful, she asked him what had happened.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Heu! mea uxor,' inquit, 'defunctus sum!'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He said: “oh dear wife, I just want to die!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Mi vir,' uxor ait, 'quid tibi adversi evenit?</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wife said: “dear husband, what misfortune has befallen you?</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Solare, atque ad cenam veni.'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Cheer up and come to dinner!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">At ille cum in gemitu perseveraret, neque cibum vellet sumere, tandem instantius maeroris causam percontanti mulieri:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">But he kept on sighing and refused to eat, and finally the wife demanded to know the reason for his grief and he replied:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">“Do you know what news I heard today?”</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">An nescis,' respondit, 'quae nova hodie audivi?'</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Quaenam, vir?' uxor inquit.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wife said: “What news, husband?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Mortuus est Rolandus, qui solus tuebatur Christianos!'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Roland, the lone protector of all Christians, is dead!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Solata est mulier insulsam maestitiam viri, et vix tandem ad cenam potuit illum perducere.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The wife then soothed the husband’s silly grief and could, with some difficulty, make him come to dinner.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>