<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The elegant reply of the Florentine poet Dante</title>
				<author>Poggio Bracciolini</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robin Wahlsten Böckerman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Responsio elegans dantis poete florentini</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The elegant reply of the Florentine poet Dante</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"The elegant reply of the Florentine poet Dante" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Facetia 57</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Joke 57</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dantes Alligerius, poeta noster Florentinus, aliquamdiu sustentatus est Veronae opibus Canis veteris Principis de la Scala, admodum liberalis.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Our Florentine poet Dante Alighieri dwelled for a while in Verona, sustained by the older Cangrande della Scala, a very noble ruler.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Erat autem et alter penes Canem Florentinus, ignobilis, indoctus, imprudens, nulli rei praeterquam ad iocum risumque aptus,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">However, there was also another Florentine at Cangrande’s, an ignoble, unlearned, and ignorant man, not fit for anything excepts for jokes and laughter.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">cuius ineptiae, ne dicam facetiae, Canem perpulerant ad se ditandum.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">His fooleries (I will not call them jokes!) had made Cangrande enrich him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cum illum veluti belluam insulsam, Dantes, vir doctissimus, sapiens ac modestus, ut aequum erat, contemneret:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Dante, who is most learned, wise, and modest, showed contempt for this inelegant beast of a man, which was just, he said:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Quid est' inquit ille, 'quod tu, cum habearis sapiens ac doctissimus, tamen pauper es et egenus, ego autem stultus et ignarus divitiis praesto?'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“How is it that you, who think yourself wise and very learned, still is poor and destitute, while I, who is stupid and ignorant, am very rich?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tum Dantes: 'Quando ego reperiam dominum,' inquit, 'mei similem et meis moribus conformem, sicuti tu tuis, et ipse similiter me ditabit.'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To which Dante replied: “When I have found a lord who is like me and my manners, just as you have, then he will reward me in a similar manner.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Gravis sapiensque responsio!</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A deep and wise answer!</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Semper enim domini eorum consuetudine qui sibi sunt similes delectantur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For the lords always find pleasure in the habits of those who are like themselves.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>