<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Conclusion</title>
				<author>Poggio Bracciolini</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robin Wahlsten Böckerman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Conclusio</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Conclusion</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Conclusion" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Visum est mihi eum quoque nostris confabulationibus locum adiicere, in quo plures earum, tanquam in scena, recitatae sunt.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I think I should also introduce the place where many of my conversations were recited as though on a scene.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Is est ‘Bugiale’ nostrum, hoc est mendaciorum veluti officina quaedam, olim a secretariis institutum iocandi gratia.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This place is our “Bugiale,” which is like a type of workshop for liars and was once founded by secretaries for the sake of amusement.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Consuevimus enim, Martini Pontificis usque tempore, quemdam eligere in secretiori aula locum, in quo et nova referebantur, et variis de rebus, tum laxandi ut plurimum animi causa, tum serio quandoque, colloquebamur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Ever since the time of Pope Martin (V) we used to choose a place in a remote chamber where news was reported, but we also used to talk about many different things, often to relax our spirits, but sometimes also serious matters.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Ibi parcebatur nemini in lacessendo ea quae non probabantur a nobis, ab ipso persaepe Pontifice initium reprehensionis sumpto:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">There no one would be spared when it came to criticising things we did not approve of, very often the pope himself would take the lead in this reproof.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">quo fiebat ut plures eo convenirent, veriti ne ab eis ordiremur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">For this reason, it happened that many people gathered there for fear that we would start with them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Erant in eo principes fabulator Razellus Bononiensis, cuius nonnulla in confabulationes coniecimus;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The leaders in this were the story-teller Razello di Bologna, some of whose stories I’ve thrown into this collection;</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Antonius item Luscus, qui saepius inseritur, vir admodum facetus;</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and Antonio Loschi, a witty man who is often introduced in this work;</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Cinciusque Romanus, et ipse iocis deditus.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and Cincio Romano, also a man fond of jokes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Nos quoque plura e nostris addidimus non insulsa.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And I also added many of my own not too inelegant stories.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Hodie, cum illi diem suum obierint, desiit ‘Bugiale’,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Today, after they have left us, the “Bugiale” has ceased to be.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">tum temporum, tum hominum culpa, omnisque iocandi confabulandique consuetudo sublata.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Both time and men are to blame, and the entire custom to joke and converse has disappeared.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>