<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>A witty reply from the same poet</title>
				<author>Poggio Bracciolini</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription from</resp>
					<name>Basel 1538 (Reprinted in Poggio Bracciolini, Scripta in editione Basilensi anno 1538 collata. Ed. Riccardo Fulbini. Turin: Bottega d'Erasmo, 1964.)</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Robin Wahlsten Böckerman</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><ref target="https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b10032427r">Paris, BnF Latin 8770a</ref></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Eiusdem poete faceta responsio</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">A witty reply from the same poet</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"A witty reply from the same poet" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Facetia 58</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Joke 58</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Huic ipsi inter seniorem aliquando iunioremque Canes prandenti, cum ministri utriusque, dedita opera, ante pedes Dantis, ad eum lacessendum, ossa occulte subiecissent,</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Dante was once seated for dinner between the older and younger Cangrande<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Literally "big dog"</p></note>, when their servants intentionally tried to hurt him by secretly throwing bones in front of his feet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">remota mensa, versi omnes in solum Dantem, mirabantur, cur ante ipsum solummodo ossa conspicerentur.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When the table was removed everyone turned toward Dante and wondered why there were bones in front of him only.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Tum ille, ut erat ad respondendum promptus:</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To which Dante, always prepared to reply, said:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">'Minime,' inquit, 'mirum, si Canes ossa sua comederunt: ego autem non sum Canis.'</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“It is little wonder if the dogs have eaten their bones, but I am not a dog!”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>