<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>To the tune “Midnight Tune”&#8212;"Frozen clouds dim the sky"</title>
				<author>Liu Yong</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 37.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Qian Jia</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Notes by</resp>
					<name>Nina Du</name>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
					<name>Dante Zhu</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Manya Bansal</name>
					<name>Dante Zhu</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
				<p>Unlike most ci, this one is composed of three stanzas (as are several others by Liu Yong). The first two stanzas concern what the speaker sees while travelling across the country by boat; in the third stanza, prompted by these sights, he reflects on his own life choices.</p>
				<p>Liu Yong was possibly the most widely-read ci writer in the Northern Song period, with fans ranging from courtesans to officials and critics. He excelled in writing love songs, portraying the emotions of lovelorn individuals in unprecedented detail and depth. Despite being born into a family of officials, he did not lead a successful professional life. After he failed keju, the Imperial Chinese civil service examination, he wrote the song “To the tune ‘Crane Soaring in the Sky’”, in which he claimed that ci poets are as important as prime ministers. This led the Ren Emperor of Song 宋仁宗 to personally deem him unfit for imperial service. The emperor suggested that if he really thought that way, he should just be a ci poet instead of pursuing the career of an official. The emperor went so far as to deliberately fail Liu Yong in his following attempt at the exams.</p>
				<p>Liu Yong’s continued output of poetry, deemed frivolous, trivial and vulgar by court officials, had a lasting impact on his professional life. He did not pass the civil service exam until he was 48 years old; before that, he spent much of his time with singers and courtesans, writing ci and living a hedonistic existence. After he finally passed keju, he worked as a low rank official in several areas and sought to advance his career through the assistance of the prime minister of that time, Yan Shu, who was also a famous ci poet (and is featured in this collection). Yan Shu mocked the frivolity of Liu Yong’s lyrics and refused to assist him, and the emperor, upon learning of his attempt, commented that Liu Yong, as a ci composer, should stick to composing ci. In response to the emperor’s comment, Liu Yong, in typically rebellious fashion, began signing his ci “composer of ci by imperial decree”. He made a final attempt to salvage his career by writing a complimentary ci to the emperor, but this was regarded as offensive and the emperor stripped him of his official titles and stated that he would never be accepted back at court. From then on, he returned to his previous lifestyle, indulging in the company of singers and courtesans.</p>
				<p>Because of his unique life experience, the sentiments expressed in Liu Yong’s ci are often very different from the views typically expressed in Chinese society at that time, with an especially cynical attitude towards serving the empire and a pronounced defense of hedonism. Nevertheless, Liu Yong’s ci were extremely popular throughout the empire, giving rise to the frequently repeated observation that “if you can see a well in a place, you can hear Liu Yong’s ci being sung there”. As every tiny town had a well, this indicates the wide reach of Liu’s lyrics.</p>
				<p>Liu Yong is also notable for his many formal innovations to ci poetry. Before Liu, most ci were written to accompany short tunes, but he initiated a trend of writing lyrics for longer tunes, which allowed for more complex portrayals of human psychology. He was also less restrained by the tune, and often modified the traditional rhyme as well as the line breaks. For example, even when he wrote two ci to the same tune, they might sound very different from one another, with different rhymes, line lengths or numbers of lines. The tunes that Liu Yong used were also more diverse than those of his contemporaries: some were folk songs, and some he composed himself. Many of Liu Yong’s ci have a stronger narrative element, probably due to the influence of storytellers whose street performances he would have watched. Liu received considerable criticism for his focus on love and for his use of commonplace language rather than a refined poetic vocabulary, but this did little to curtail his popularity or his influence on the development of the ci genre.</p>
				<p>Chang, Kang-i Sun. The Evolution of Tz’u Poetry: from Late Tang to Northern Sung. Princeton UP, 1980.</p>
				<p>A standard survey of the early history of Chinese song lyrics (romanized as both ci and tz’u).</p>
				<p>Egan, Ronald. “The Song Lyric.” The Cambridge History of Chinese Literature, vol. 1, edited by Stephen Owen, Cambridge UP, 2010, pp. 434-452.</p>
				<p>An overview of the genre.</p>
				<p>Owen, Stephen. Just a Song: Chinese Lyrics from the Eleventh and Early Twelfth Centuries. Asia Center, Harvard UP, 2019.</p>
				<p>A recent new history of the genre.</p>
				<p>Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋, editor. Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Zhonghua shu ju, 1965. 5 vols.</p>
				<p>A comprehensive edition of ci from the Song dynasty and the source text for the ci  in this collection (introductions and annotations are in Chinese).</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Text based on Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 37.</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">夜半樂</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">To the tune “Midnight Tune”</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>To the tune “Midnight Tune”&#8212;"Frozen clouds dim the sky" is part of <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi>, a digital compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. This larger project comprises computer-readable transcriptions and/or editions of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century, and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia; accompanied by new English translations; high-resolution digital images of manuscript/early print sources, where available; an apparatus that includes critical introductions, textual notes and annotations; and a flexible user interface with which to navigate these materials.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>The original text of this ci is based on the edition by Tang Guizhang 唐圭璋 (Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 2. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965). Punctuation follows the edition. Since ci poetry rarely includes personal pronouns, and gender-differentiated pronouns did not exist in Classical Chinese of this period, the gender of the speaker as well as their perspective (e.g. first, second or third person) must often be deduced by the translator from context.</p>
					<punctuation marks="all">Punctuation follows the edition.</punctuation>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">夜半樂</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To the tune “Midnight Tune”</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1">
				<!--Each stanza needs its own line group <lg>-->
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">凍雲黯淡天氣，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Frozen clouds dim the sky,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">扁舟一葉，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">a thin boat</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">乘興離江渚。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">departs the riverside on a whim, </rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">渡萬壑千巖，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">crosses a thousand valleys and a thousand canyons,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">越溪深處。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">into the depth of Yue streams<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>In Chinese folklore, this river is associated with a beautiful woman named Xi Shi, whose name has become synonymous with female beauty. According to the tale, she often washed her clothes in this river.</p></note>,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">怒濤漸息，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Raging waves gradually die down,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">樵風乍起，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A favorable wind suddenly rises.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">更聞商旅相呼。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then I hear the traveling tradesmen calling to each other<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>A common way for tradesmen to communicate with each other at that time.</p></note>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">片帆高舉。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The lone sail hangs high;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">泛畫鷁、</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the painted bird<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>“鷁” is a legendary bird that was often painted on boats. It was believed to be a lucky charm for sailors because it could fly over water during storms. Here, “the painted bird” refers to the boat that the speaker is on.</p></note>,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">翩翩過南浦。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I swiftly pass the southern bank.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2">
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">望中酒旆閃閃，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Before my eyes, the wine shop banner swings,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">一簇煙村，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">a small village wreathed in smoke,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="14">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">數行霜樹。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">and rows of frosty trees.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="15">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">殘日下，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The setting sun retreats,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="16">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">漁人鳴榔歸去。 </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The fishermen strike the side of the boat<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The fishermen strike the boat to give themselves a beat to sing along to.</p></note> and return.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="17">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">敗荷零落， </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Withered lotuses fall apart,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="18">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">衰楊掩映，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Fading willows cover and reveal.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="19">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">岸邊兩兩三三，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On the bank, in groups of two or three,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="20">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">浣沙遊女。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Girls are doing laundry<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>A typical scene for women at that time, but it could also be associated with the story of Xi Shi (see note above).</p></note>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="21">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">避行客、</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Avoiding the travelers,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="22">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">含羞笑相語。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">shy, they smile, chatting to each other.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="3">
				<l n="23">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">到此因念，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Being here brings back my thoughts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="24">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">繡閣輕拋，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I have abandoned the embroidered chamber<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Refers to a bedroom. It implies that the poet has left behind the wealthy, domestic life that he could otherwise have led.</p></note>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="25">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">浪萍難駐。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Like a duckweed in the waves, I have nowhere to stay.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="26">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">嘆後約</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I sigh at the thought of reunion&#8212;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="27">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">丁寧竟何據。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">who can now believe in the earnest words that were said back then?</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="28">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">慘離懷，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Wretched is the parting heart,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="29">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">空恨歲晚歸期阻。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">vainly regretting that the year has come to an end and the time to return home<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>In the Lunar calendar, the end of the year means the coming of Spring Festival, the most important festival for the reunion of families.</p></note> has been delayed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="30">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">凝淚眼、</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I let my watery eyes gaze</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="31">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">杳杳神京路。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">at the long, distant road to the capital.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="32">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">斷鴻聲遠長天暮。 </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The cry of the wild goose resounds, lingering in the vast evening sky.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
