<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>An account of how the Cypriots gained victory over Alexandria</title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>David Wrisley</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"<!--Title in English-->" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ذكر كيفية ظفر القبرسي بالإسكندرية</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Subtitle in original language--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Subtitle in English--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و ذلك أن نائب السلطان بثغر الإسكندرية، وهو الأمير خليل صلاح الدين بن عرام كان غائبا عن الثغر المذكور بالحجاز الشريف بسبب الحج،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The prince Ṣalāḥ al-Dīn ibn ʿArām, the vice-sultan was absent from the inlet of Alexandria, since he was in Holy Hijaz to complete his hajj,</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و كان نائبا عنه فيه بإشارة الأمير الاتبكى يلبغا الخاسكى أمير يسمى جنغرا.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Meanwhile, the Atabeg prince Yalbughā al-Khāssikiyy, also known as "Janghara," was acting in his place.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فلما دخل جنغرا المذكور الإسكندرية رأى طوائفها المتطوعة الحارسة لميناءها تنجر عليه بالجزيرة</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When Janghara came to Alexandria, he saw the reserve guard regiments in the port advancing onto the peninsula.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بقسيّهم الجرخ الموترة و أعلامهم الحرير المنشورة ، مع ما بأيديهم من المزاريق و الرماح ، و الدرق و الصفاح و الزرد النضيد ، و مصفحات الحديد ، و النفط الطيار، الصاعد منه لهب النار،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They brandished well-strung bows and displayed silk banners, carrying javelins, lances, shields, halberds, layered coats of mail and armor and blazing Greek fire.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و هم بملبوسهم المختلف الألوان ، كالزهر في البستان.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They wore so many colors that they looked like flowers in a garden.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فلما عاينهم جنغرا بكى و قال: # هؤلاء أهل الجنة لرباطهم و جهادهم في سبيل الله # قد طاب و الله العيش بقوة هذا الجيش # لو اتى إلى الإسكندرية جميع نصارى الرومانية، ما قدروا على هذا الجيش الثقيل على الإسكندرية ، بل يكسرون النصارى، و يصيرونهم قتلى أسارى</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When he spotted them, tears fell from his eyes and he said: # “These are the people of paradise. Look at their devotion and how they strive in the cause of Allah. # How delightful our life has become, oh Allah, thanks to the strength of this army. # If all the Christians would come to Alexandria, not only could they not fend off this mighty army, but they would be broken, left dead or hostaged."</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">			
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فأقام جنغرا بالإسكندرية من شوال سنة ست و ستين و سبعمائة إلى المحرم</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Janghara was in Alexandria for three months from Shawwal in the year 766 until Muharram.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The author uses the Hijri calendar here, Shawwal being the tenth month and Muharram being the first. This means that Janghara arrived in Alexandria around July 1365 CE.</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ينظر لتلك الطوائف التي لكل طائفة منها ليلة في الأسبوع تبيت تحرس بساحل الميناء،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He saw the regiments that took turns each day of the week watching over the coastal port.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و ربما بات ليالي في الغرفة التي على باب مسجد تربة طغية، و يقدم قدامه قانوسين أكرتين مقابل باب المسجد المذكور.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He even slept nights in a small room near the Turbat Ṭāghiyya mosque in front of which he had placed two lanterns completely full of oil.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و تأتي طائفة الزراقين يطلقون النفط</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The regiment known as the "Blue Regiment" came and was launching burning oil. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و هو ينظر من طيقان الغرفة المذكورة إلى الشرار الطيار، و اللوالب التي تدور بألوان النار، من الخضرة و الصفرة، و البياض و الحمرة.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Janghara caught a glimpse through the arrow hole in the room's wall of the flying sparks and the spinning flamethrowers combusting in all colors, from green to yellow, white to red.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فيحصل بذلك الإنشراح، من العشى إلى الصباح،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He feasted his eyes on this display from dusk to dawn.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و يبتهج أيضا بنظره إلى كثرة الخلائق المنتشرة على الساحل من الرماة و العوام،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It brought him joy also to see so many people spread out on the coastal front line, military and civilians alike.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و قد نصب لهم سوق فيه من أصناف المأكول يشترون و يأكلون، # و من ماء الروايا و القرب التي تحمل من البلد إليهم يشربون.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">A market was set up for them with all kinds of food to buy and eat, # and waterskins were brought from inland so they could drink.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فإذا أصبحوا إنتظمت الطائفة التي باتت تحرس مدخل البلد في همة و جلد، و كثرة و مدد،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the morning, the large regiment that had guarded the city entrance all night got back into formation with zeal and vigor, and in great numbers.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فتجتمع لدخولهم الرجال و النسوان، ينظرون لأقوام كزهر بستان، من حسن الملابس و بياض تلك الطبالس،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The city’s men and women gathered together for the occasion, and they saw the regiments, their beautiful clothes and their white robes looked like flowers in a garden.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فتزغرتن لهم النسوان إعلانا، عند مشاهدتهن لهم عيانا، و الأبواق حينئذ تصرخ، و الكوسات تدق، و المزامر تزمر،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Upon seeing them, the ladies announcing their arrival by ululating and the horns blew, the symbols clashed and the mizāmir<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>An oboe-like wind instrument.</p></note>bellowed. </rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و الأعلام منشورة، و المباخر بالطيب معمورة،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Flags waved and censers were lit and an aromatic smoke wafted through the air.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و دخانها يفوح، فتنبسط لتلك الروائح الأرجة كل روح،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Each and every soul took pleasure in these beautiful smells.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">والناس في فرح و سرور، لرؤية ذلك الجيش المحبور المهتز له الشوارع و الدور.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the people were delighted to see the victorious army, the houses and streets shaking with the regiments’ advance.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فينما هم كذلك على عادتهم مستمرون، و في ثغرهم مطمئنون، و لا تروعهم الأعداء و لا راوا مكروها أبدا، إذ دهمهم صاحب قبرس اللعين، في جنده الضالين، شتت شملهم أجمعين، فروا منه في البلدان،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">As was their custom—self-assured on their inlet—their faces did not betray the slightest fear of the enemy, nor did they see the deception or the coming attack of the cursed Cypriots and their infidel soldiers—may Allah scatter them about and make them run back to their countries.<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The Cypriots mentioned in this passage refer to the armies of King Peter I of Cyprus (Pierre I de Lusignan).</p></note></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و دخل البلد باطمئنان،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And the regiments entered the city with ease.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و ذلك في يوم الجمعة الثاني و العشرين من المحرم سنة سبع و ستين و سبعمائة، و النيل منتشر على البلاد،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This was on Friday, 22 Muharram 767, when the Nile River spilled over its banks.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">قصد الملعون باتيانه ذلك الزمن لتتعوق النجدة من مصر لبعد الطريق من الجبل،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The cursed [Cypriots] planned to come at that very moment to forestall reinforcements arriving from Cairo on account of the long distance across the terrain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فنال الخبيث قصده في ذلك اليوم و الذي بعده، و تحصن قبل إتيان النجدة بمراكبه،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">That day the sly Cypriots managed to do just that, securing their position before help came by boat.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و فرح بسلامة نفسه و مكاسبه، فلو كان بها أمراء مجردة ما نال الخبيث منها ثمن زردة،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Cypriots were happy on account of their own safety and their gain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فلو كان بها أمراء مجردة ما نال الخبيث منها ثمن زردة # لكن كان ذلك في الكتاب مسطورا، و كان أمر الله قدرا مقدورا.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If there had been powerful princes nearby the sly Cypriots would not have gained a penny, # but alas it was meant to be, and by Allah's will, it was fated to happen.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="3">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">عن يزيد بن حبيب أن عمرو بن العاص  رضي الله عنه لما فتح الإسكندرية، # و رأى بيوتها و بناءها مفروغا منها همّ أن يسكنها</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Yazīd ibn Ḥabīb said that when ʿAmr ibn al-ʿĀṣ<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Amr ibn al-ʿĀṣ led the Muslim conquest of Egypt and the surrender of Alexandria in the early years of Islam, 641 or 642 CE.</p></note>—may Allah be pleased with him—first conquered Alexandria # he found its home and its buildings empty and he thought that he should live there.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">و قال: مساكن قد كفيناها،# فكتب إلى عمر بن الخطاب رضي الله عنه يستأذنه في ذلك،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">He said: “these dwellings will suffice for us” # and he wrote to ʿUmar ibn al-Khaṭṭāb<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Umar ibn al-Khaṭṭāb was one of the most important of the companions of the Prophet Muhammad.</p></note>—may Allah be pleased with him—asking him to accept that they live there.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فقال عمر لرسوله: هل يحول بيني و بين المسلمين ماء؟</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Umar inquired of his messenger : “Is there water between me and the Muslims?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">قال: نعم يا أمير المؤمنين، إذا جرى النيل،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The latter responded: “Yes, Prince of the Faithful, provided the Nile flows.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فكتب عمر إلى عمرو: إني لا أحب أن تنزل المسلمين منزلا يحول الماء بيني و بينهم في شتاء و لا صيف إلا إذا كثروا،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So, ‘Umar wrote to ‘Amr: “I do not like that the Muslims are settled in a place separated from us by water—in winter as in summer—except if they are outnumbered.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">فتحول عمرو بن العاص من الإسكندرية إلى مصر،</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">So, ʿAmr ibn al-ʿĀṣ left Alexandria for Cairo.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="4">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>				
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p></p></note></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>