<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>The Damsel of Carcayçiona</title>
				<author>Anonymous</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name>Jordan Rosen-Kaplan</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Jordan Rosen-Kaplan</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Jordan Rosen-Kaplan</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Global Medieval Sourcebook</publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Madrid, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC), MS Junta 57</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">ذنزالّ كركيسين</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">The Damsel of Carcayçiona</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>"The Damsel of Carcayçiona" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
				<interpretation>
					<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ءالركنتميانت دال ذنزالّ كركيسين</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The Account of the Damsel of Carcayçiona</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div n="1">
				<p n="1">
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">﻿بسم الله الرّحمان الرحيم وصلى الله على سيدنا محمد الكريم وعلى الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">﻿In the name of God, the Merciful; and God bless our master, Muhammad, and his family.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءاست ءاش ءالركنتميانت دالذنزالّ، كركيسين فجّدالراي نجرب كنل بّلم راكنتذ بّر علي إبن ابا الحسن إبن جابّر فجّ ذا عبد الله ابّر سعيد فجّذا طاهر إبّر عمر فجّذا سعيد.
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This is the telling of the story of the damsel of Carcayçiona, daughter of King Naǧreb, accompanied by the dove, retold by ᶜAli, son of Abu al-Haçan, son of Ǧabir, son of ᶜAbu Allah, and by Çaᶜid, son of Ṭahir, and by ᶜUmar, son of Çaᶜid.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>This is a conventional opening. Note the emphasis on lineal relationships, which likely comes as a product of the fact that many of these tales have oral traditions which precede them. The people mentioned could be called the authors, but it's more likely that they have some prominence in the oral retelling of this tale, whether broadly across the culture or specifically with respect to the scribe.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دزان كا ءانترنذ ألماسكد دالمانشجار دا الله محمد، صلعم، هلّرن أن كر ذاجانتا، اياشتب ءانالّش عمر إبن الخطاب إعلي إبن ابي طالب إكعب الاخبار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They say that when entering into the mosque of the messenger of God and Muhammad, blessed be his name, a huddle of people could be found and among them was ᶜUmar, son of al-Haṭṭib, and ᶜAli, son of Abi Ṭalib, and Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر ديش علي إبن ابي طالب
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then, ᶜAli, son of Abi Ṭalib, said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا كعب الاخبار كوانتنش ألغن كش مربلّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār, tell us something marvelous.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش كعب الاخبار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بلزاما يا راي دالش كارايانتاش أش دا شبا ركا ءان لش  بّرمارش دالمنذ ابيا ان ري دالش رمنش كا ببي ءان لهندا كا اذرب الش إذلش إ ءار راي دا مي بوان كندسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“It pleases me to do so. King of the Believers, you must know that in the beginning of the world, there was a king of the Romans who lived in India, who worshipped idols, and was a very wealthy king. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">غبارنب  سو رّين كن مجّ امر اجشتسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He governed his kingdom with great love and justice. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءاشتا راي ن ءانجاندر كريترفشت كا توب سيانتا انش،
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This king did not have a child; he was one hundred years old. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ابّانش ءالراي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He thought:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كم نو تاني فج
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Why do I not have a child?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كيّلا ءابّرالّ غرندا بّيانش إمنذ أن ذي كا شا الّاغشان تذش لش شبيش داش راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">A grand idea came upon him, and one day, he ordered all the sages in his kingdom to come to him. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ايلاغرنشا تذش اذش لاش ءال رّاي كا  مرشان ءان شوشبار إسانسي ش ابي داتانار فجش أبّر كا لاءار داباذذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And all of them came and the king told them to look at their knowledge and science to see if it was possible for him to have children or why he had been devoid of them. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">امررن لش شبيش بّر ش شبار ءان ل ماداسن ادشيارنلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the sages searched through their knowledge in medicine and told him:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر، اش داشبار كا ت كواربّ ءاش فري اشلّا دات ل ءاشبارما مي فريا، ان بّواش كنسابّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Sir, you must know that your body is cold and your ejaculate comes out cold from your body and so you don’t conceive.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">اش ماناشتار كا تابّربيانداش داشبّاسيش كا شاان مي كليانتاش فشت كا شلغ دا ت ل ءاشبّارم كليانتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It is necessary that they provide you with special spices so that when you consume them, your body will ejaculate hot sperm.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">افزل ءالراي اشي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the king did as such. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ابّاراش دشيارنلا لش ءاشترلغش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After, the astrologers told him:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر، ن أن ذود شن كا أش داأبّر كريتور بار نشبامش ش شار مجّ افانبّر بّركا بامش ل ءاشتارالّ ذابانش اشانتذ شبّرا ءالشغن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Sir, there is no doubt that you will have a child, but we do not know if it will be male or female because we see the star of Venus situated upon the sign of Venus.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش ءالراي كنبن كن ش مجّار أل كمينس دال دي ايانبّارانّشا لامجّار ابّري ان كريتر دالش مش فارمشش دالش مجّاراش الّمرنل كركيسين.
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So the king convened with his woman at the start of the day and impregnated the woman and imparted a creature who was among the most beautiful of women, and they called her Carcayçiona.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">امري شمدرا دابّرت اديل شبّدرأ أن ندرس اكريل شياتا أنّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And her mother died in childbirth and gave her father a wet nurse, who raised her for seven years.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">افزلا شبّدرا ان القصر شبرا ذرذ، ابّرد دامسناري افزلا ءانال بارجالاش كن أربلاش اريش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And her father made her a palace of gold, decorated with masonry, and in it were arboretums and rivers.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">تريلا الي تذش لش ءاشترمانتس كا بّد ابار، اذاشل الّي كن شش ذنزالّش فشت كا لاغ أتانار أنزا أنّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he brought all the instruments there could possibly be, and he left her with his ladies-in-waiting until she turned eleven.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءانبّواش بن ابارل شبّدرا كن لش غرنداش دا شراين، اتريلا بّركذش اشادش اجيش كنتذش لش دالايتاش كا بّذ ترءار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then, her father came to see her with the important people of his kingdom, and he brought her rich brocades and silks and jewels with all the treats he could carry.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> إا نتر ذُ ءاشتب الّ إ مر أ شفارمشر اينمرشا ذالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he entered where she was, and he saw her beauty and fell in love with her. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">اكمي ابابي كنالّ اكونذ ابيارن كمذ دشلا لدنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he ate and drank with her, and when they had finished eating, the damsel said to him: 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا ءاشتش خلاقذش داأنباراش إمجّاراش نفوارن خلافذش شن بّر كمار إبابار بّواش كنبيانا كا كيان فزا تلاش غرسيش كا سالش اغرداسكمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, these creations of men and women were created only to eat and drink, so it is appropriate that we should be thankful to Him, who made us such grace.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش يُ يا بّدرا أكيان لأغرداسارا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So father, whom do I thank?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> ديش ءالبّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The father said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">امي يا فجّ كاي ءافاجّ غرسي شبّرا تي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Me, daughter, for I have brought grace upon you.” 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لفجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The daughter said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إتُ، يا بّدرا، أكيان ل أغرداساش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“And you, father, whom do you thank for it?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ءاشتش غرسيش أنلش ءارادذ نواشش انتابّشذش أنّش دااترش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, these blessings have been inherited by our predecessors, one from another.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لفجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The daughter said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا كيان ل كمانس اكيان ل اكبّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, who started it, and who will end up with them?
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا تبّدرا ات اوال مريارن بّواش كيان فز ءاشتش غرسيش اكيان لش ءاراذر اكيان خلاق لش جانتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Your father and your grandfather died, so who made these blessings and who will inherit them and who creates men?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالراي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ، يُ تا درا تُ شانّر اشانّر داتش بّدراش أكال كا ن ءا كنسد أُتر شانّر شن ءال
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, I will give you your master and the master of your parents. I have not known another master except him.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلؤر مند ءالراي كالا ترياشان شُ إل كا ءار ذا أر ءاشملتذ كن الجوهر ابّيادرش بّاراسيشش كا تاني كورانت كبذش دالرغ ابانتا دا انجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And at that moment, the king demanded that they bring him his idol, which was enameled with gold, jewels, and precious stones, that was forty cobḏos 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Cobḏos are a unit measurement corresponding to the length of the forearm, from the elbow to the wrist or fingertips</p>
								</note> 
								long and twenty wide.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">اكوند لبذ لذنزالّ اغردلا، كنشلب شا كنال إدش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the damsel saw it, she thanked it and consoled herself with it, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا {بادرا} هز ما أن شانّر كم ءاستا بّر كا اذرا إشرب
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, make me a master just like this so I can adore and serve it.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش لؤر منذ ءالراي فزارلا أن إذل ذاأر ءاشملتذ كن الجوهر كا تاني لش أجش ذا بّربّر باردا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So, at that moment, the king commanded to make her an idol enameled with gold and with jewels, that had emerald eyes.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">افزيارنلا انكتراد داأر إلش بياداش دابّيادرش بّاراسيشش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So they made it for her, with a seat of gold and feet of precious stones.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إتريارنجّال دالنتا إيسجادشا لدنزالّ أ لا إذل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They brought it before her and the damsel bowed to the idol. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">اكذ ذي كم شليا ءالشل بني لفجّ دالراي اشش ذنزالّش كن ءالّ ايسجدبنشا أل إدل إهبلن كن ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And every day, like the sun would rise, the daughter of the king, with her other damsels, bowed to the idol and talked with the idol.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكونذ ءاشت راشبّنديلاش إبلس ملذجل الله ءانالكواربّ دال إدل إمندبلاش إبادب لش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when they were there, Ibliç
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>The devil</p>
								</note> - Allah curse him - responded to them from the body of the idol and he would command them in various ways and spread falsehoods.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش بن شبّدرا أبارل أُن ذي إتريلا مجّش جيش إكماراش إكمي كن الّ  
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So her father came one day to see her, and he brought her many jewels and foodstuffs, and he ate with her. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إمرل أش فارمشرإ رابّش أن رت إلابنتشا  أ ءالّ أباشل إدامندلا شكواربّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he looked at her beauty and pondered for a while, and he got up and kissed her and demanded her body. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إديش لفجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the daughter said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا، دما ت بّدرا ءاجّشا كن ش فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, tell me, did your father throw himself onto his daughter?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءال نُ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He said: “No.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش الّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش، يا بّدرا، بّركا كياراش تُ فزار كش كا تا أبارغونّشش. لش ديش دا ت بذ إيانبّواش دا ت موارتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“So, father, why do you want to do something that will shame you for the days of your life and through your death? 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أش أإد دازير دا ألغن راي كا هزياشا لشاماجنتا كن ش فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Have you heard it said that some other king might have done the same thing with his daughter?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> بّواش لؤر أُب ءالراي غرندا بارغوانس دا ش فجّ إشليشا دا ألّي 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So the king felt very ashamed because of his daughter, and he left.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إداشّل ءان شش بّلزاراش كم شلي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he left her surrounded by pleasurable things, as usual.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ابّبلكشا ل فارمشر إ داشكرسين ذا لذنزالّ بّر تذ لتيار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the news of her beauty and prudence was spread around the land.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دامندبنل لش هجّش دا لش راياش إن كاري شبّدرا كشرل بّر لكا بذي ءان الّ دا مجّ كرذر إبّارفسيان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The sons of kings demanded her, and her father did not want to marry her to any of them because of what he saw in her: much innocence and perfection.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إياشتنذ لدنزالّ أُن ذي ذالنتا دا شُ إذل هبا إبلس، ملذغل الله، ءان الكواربّ دال إدل اذيش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the damsel, one day, was in front of her idol, when Ibliç - Allah curse him - spoke to her from the body of the idol and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ذنرالّ تُ شباش كا ن أَي يتر شانّر شن يُ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, you know that there is no other master except me.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> يَ لُ شا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I know that already.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إياشتارنذ لدنزالّ إشللا دال نرز أُن مشك كن ءالغرندا ءاشتارنذ إديش الفجّ دال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the damsel sneezed and from her nose, a fly came out with the big sneeze, and said to her, the daughter of the king:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا دنزالّ كا ءاشا تُ كا أَش ءاشتارنذ إ نُ أَش ديجّ "الحمد لله رب العلمين"
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, is it you who has sneezed and not said, ‘Praise be to Allah, Lord of the Worlds’? ”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكونذ أُيُ إبلس، ملذغل الله، ءالنبارا ذا الله شلي فيانذ إكيُشا لإذل شبّرا شُ كر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when Ibliç - Allah curse him - heard the name of Allah, he left fleeing and the idol fell on its face.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكونذ أُيُ لفجّ دال راي نجرب اكال بّلبر دال مشك ءاشبّنتشا دالّ مجّ إلّاغرنشا أَءالّ شُش ذنزالّش إءالّ لّرنذ دامدذ لكلر ءاشبّنتذ ذشيارنلاّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the daughter of Naǧreb heard these words from the fly, she was very frightened, and her ladies gathered around her, and she was crying, pale, and frightened, and they said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا شانّر كا أَش أُيذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Miss, what have you heard?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا ءا أُإذ أُنّش بّلبرش كا ننك أُإ ششاماجنتا دالّش أَن ءانترذ ءان مِ كرسن كن مي غرنذا فوارس
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I have heard words the likes of which I have never heard before, and they entered my heart with a great force.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ بّانشذ ءان الذجّ دا "الحمد لله رب العالمين"
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I have been thinking about this saying: ‘Praise be to Allah, Lord of the Worlds.’
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَما أَتارابُيذ ءال كرسن دبارشش ذبذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In my heart, I have felt some doubts.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إدغ كا ءال شانّر ذال منذ كا ءاش غرن شانّر بّركا يُ ننك ءا أُإذ مش ذلساش بّلبرش كا سن ءاشتش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And I say that the master of the world is a grand master because I have never heard sweeter words than these.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Well, how sad, who will explain to me the meaning of these words?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش يا ترشتا دا مي كيان ما داكلرر لكا كياران دازر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دابّواش دا أَكاشت ترنشا لدنزالّ الشاربسي دال إدل أَشي كم شلِيا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After this, the damsel returned to the service of the idol as she was accustomed.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">باش كا أُن ذي ءاشتنذ دالنتا دا شُ إذل بنلا أُن بّلم  إأَشانتشا ءان لكباس دال ذنرالّ ذا أَلّي بل إأَشانتشا ءان لكباس دا لإذل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Here you see that one day, the damsel was in front of her idol, and a dove came to her and sat on her head, and from there, flew and sat on the head of the idol.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إقوبذ لبذ لذنزالّ مربالّشا دالّ إدا شُ فارمشر كا لبّلم ءار دأُرُ أَمرايلّ إش كُد دا بّارلش بارماجّش، شش بياداش دا بّلت، شُ بّك دا بّارلش بلنكش ءاشملتذ دا الجّهر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the damsel saw the dove, she was astounded by her and by her beauty, for the dove was golden-yellow, her tail was of red pearls, her feet of silver, and her beak enameled with brilliant white pearls.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش ديش لدنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So the damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ترشتا دا مي فواشاما يُ أَكالّ بّلم، كشتشاما لمايتد دا مِ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Woe is me. If only I were that dove, even if it cost me half my kingdom.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">مرندل مُي مربلّذ ذا شُ فاجّ ديش لبّلم كن لانو شوالت إبّلذن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And seeing her very astounded, the dove said in fluent and formal language:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دالراي نجرب دي "الحمد لله لا اله الّا الله وحدو لاشريك له" كا كيارا دازير لؤر ءاش أَذ الله نُ أَي أُتر شانّر شِن الله شُلُ شِن أَبّرسار أَءال ءاش ءالراشم إءال ءاش ش{بّرا} تذ كش بّذارش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of the king Naǧreb, say, ‘Praise be to Allah, there is no companion to him, alone,’ which means ‘Praise be to Allah, there is no other master, but Allah, without peers. To Him belongs the Kingdom,
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>The physical world</p>
								</note> 
								and He is above anything else powerful.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش كونذ أُي إبلس، ملذغل الله، ءالننبرميانت دا الله تن أَلت ءاش شلّ هيانذ إءال ذزياند
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When Ibliç - Allah curse him - heard the name of Allah, the high one, he fled, saying:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كامذ شي كن الفواغ دا جهنّم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I am burnt with the fire of Hell.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكي لإذل شبّرا شُ كر إكاذ لذنزالّ ءاشبنتذ مي تامارش مرنذ البّلم إدش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the idol fell on its face and the damsel remained frightened; looking very fearfully at the dove, she said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم فارمش، ءا أُإذ تش بّلبرش كا ننك أُإ مش بوانش بّلبرش ن مش ذلساش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Beautiful dove, I have heard your words, the likes of which I have never heard before, for they are so sweet. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كيان ءاراش تُ، يا بّلم، إكا بّلبرش شن أَكالّش كا ذشيشتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Who are you, dove? And what words are those that you just said?
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا أَ كياذ ش دلسر ءان مي كرسن دما أَلغ مش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">For their sweetness has fallen in my heart. Tell me something else.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب، دِ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله خلاقذر دالش سيالش إدا لتيار إدا تدش خلاقذش إدا شش الرزكاش، متذر، راببكذر دانبّواش دال موارتا بّر ءال ذي كا نُ أَبّرباجّر شن لبوان أُبّر إءال كا أَنتاش كارايار كن الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, say that there is no God except Allah, creator of Heaven and Earth and all creations and riches, He who takes life and resurrects it after death for the Judgment Day, when nothing can help a person except the good deeds that they performed in their lifetime, and their belief in Allah before.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دما مش داشش بّلبرش بونش كا شُ ذلسرا ءانترذ ءان مِ كرسن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Tell me more of those good words whose sweetness has entered my heart.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب ءاش الله أَكال كا نُ أَي أُتر شانّر شن ءال، خلاقذر دا لش سيالش إدا لش تيارش ءان شايش ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, it is Allah, there is no other God like him, creator of the heavens and Earths in six days.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دابّواش شا إولُ شبرا ءال أَلعرشا، ءانكبّرا لنجّا إءال ذي إءال شل أَلَ لُنَ الش ءاشتارالش أَشجّاتذش كن شُ منذميانت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After He filled out His throne 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>In efforts to be as precise as possible in our translation practices, this is a direct translation. However the meaning is somewhat idiomatic. To "fill out His throne," means to flesh out his creation of the universe and establish his power within it.</p>
								</note>
								, He covered the night and the day and sun and the moon and the stars and made them subjects under His rule.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءال ءاش ءال خلاقر إءال متر بانذيجّ ءاش الله شانّر داتذ ءال منذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He is the creator and the destroyer. Blessed is Allah, God of the entire world.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم، ءاشا شانّر كا تُ لنبرش، ءاش غرن شانّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, this master that you speak of is a great master.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش كاراساما مش داشش بّلبرش بوانش كا شاماجّنتا كا تُ نُ دريش شن بردذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Raise me up with these good words of truth that only you could tell me.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ذنزالّ دِ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله شل شن أَبّرسار، خلاقذر دا لش سيالش إذا لس تيارا إدا لكا ءاشت ءانتارالّش كا ءاشت دابش دا لّش فشت لش أَبشمش دال تيار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, say that there is no God except Allah alone, without peers, creator of the heavens and the lands and what is between them and what is below them until the abysses of the Earth.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم هزما أَشبار ذُ ءاشت ءاشا شانّر تن غرندا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, inform me where this great God is.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب نُ شا أَجّنتن ءان شاكرات تاراش كا نُ شاء ءال ءال كورت نِ كورت كا نُ شاء ءال سكان نِ سنك كا نُ شاء شاشت نِ مش نِ مانش دا أَكال كا ءال نُ شاء كن الّش ذندا كيارا كا أَشتن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, three do not unite themselves around a secret without a fourth, nor four without a fifth, nor five without a sixth, nor more nor less than that. He is always present.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم ءاشا شانّر نُ شا بوادا بار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Can this master not be seen?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب ءال شانّر دالش سيالش إدا لتيار بايا أَ تذش إن لبا أَ ءال نغن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, the master of the heavens and Earth sees everything and no one sees him.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءال ءاشت أَن ودميانت أَلت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He is in the highest protected heaven.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شبا لُ شاكارات إ لُ بّلك
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He knows secret things and public things.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نُ أَي شانّر شن ءال
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There is no master except him. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَ ءال شن لش لنباراش بانش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The most favorable attributes belong to him.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم ءاشا شانّر كا دزاش شانبلنسما أَذندا ءاشت أُكا ءاش أُكم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, this master you speak of, give me a semblance of where He is, or what He is, or what He is like.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب، ربنا تبارك وتعلى، بّرمار دا تذ كش إسغار ذا تد كش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, our lord, blessed and exalted, first of all things and last of all things.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نُ لُ الكنسن لش بشتش إءال أَلكنس لش بشتش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">No one’s sights can reach him, but He can see all sights.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءال ءاش ءال شبتل شبذر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He is subtly omniscient.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كوتذ كيارا أَلغن كش دزالا شاء إلواغ ءاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When He wants something, He says, “Let it be so,” and then it is so.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">خلاق شالعرشا شبّرا ءال أَو ذندا نُ أَبيا شل كا كلراشا نِ للن كا كرياشا نِ مر كا أُبداشا نِ أَيرا كا مبياشا نِ ري كريانتا نِ سيال فروذ نِ تيار تانذذ نِ كش كمانسذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He created His throne upon the water where there was no sun that shone, no moon that turned, no sea that made waves, no air that moved, no running river, no forged sky, no laid Earth, nothing begun.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">خلاق شياتا سيالش سيال شبرا سيال، إشياتا تيارش أُن شبرا أُترَ ءان شايش ديش شبرا ءال العرش شا إوَلُ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He created seven skies, sky upon sky, and seven Earths, one on top of the next, in six days. Then He filled out his throne.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription"> ذيش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم كا تن غرندا ءاش ءاشا شانّر كا بسفكا إأُنرذ شبّرا كيان كما شارزكا إشِربا أَ أُتر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, how great is this God; He makes peace and honor for those who eat His riches and serve it to others.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم أَي ننغن ءان المنذ كا دغ لُ كا تُ دزاش بّركا يُ ننك لُ أُإ شن ذْ تي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Dove, is there no one else in the world who says what you do? Because I have never heard it except from you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شي لش دالش سيالش  إدا لَ تيار دزان لُ كا يُ دغ شن لش داشكارايانتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Yes, those of the heavens and the Earth say what I do except for the non-believers.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نغرب ءاش إذل كا تشيارباش نُ أُيا نِ بايا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Daughter of Naǧreb, this idol you serve does not hear nor see.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ذن إ نُ أَبّرباجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He is destructive but no one profits from him.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لدنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم، كا ءاش اكالُّ كا هبل دانتر دا شُ كواربّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, who is it that speaks from within his body?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءاش ءال ملديجّ دا إبلس، ملدغل الله، ءانميغ دا الله، تن أَلت ءاش إءانميغ دا تبّدرا ادم عليه اسلام
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“It is the curse of Ibliç - Allah curse him - the enemy of Allah, the highest and most powerful, and the enemy of your ancestor, Adam, peace be upon him.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا لُ ءانغن إلُ شك دا الجن إءانغن أَشش فجّش فشت ءال ذي دال جّدسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Ibliç tricked Adam - peace be upon him - and took him out of paradise and tricked him and will trick his children 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Humanity</p>
								</note> until the Day of Judgment. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">داش ءال شاربسي دال إدل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Stop serving the idol.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">هزما أَشبار يا بّلم بّرءاشا شانّر كا ءاش ءاش ولرذن دا كيان لا أُباداسا إكا ءاش ءال كشتغ ذا كيان لا داشباداسا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Help me know, Dove, what is the reward for obeying this God and what is the punishment for disobeying?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب كيان أُباداسا أَدا الله أَدابداسالا ءال الجنّ إكيانل داشباداسا شُ بّان شار ءال فواغ دا جهنّم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, whoever obeys Allah can expect paradise and whoever disobeys him, his pain will be the fire of Hell.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم شانبلنسما ءال الجنّ أكال كا ذزاش كا در الله أَلش أُبديانتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, give me a semblance of paradise, that which you say Allah will give to those who are obedient.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب، كونذ شاأَكبرن لش أُرش دال منذ إشش ديش لُ حلال إلُ حرام إشا بّاردار لَ باردذ إشا دامشترر لَ منترا إهرن لش ملافسيش إبابارن ءال بن إهرن ءال أَزِنا إكنبرن ءال لغر إشا دامشترر ءال أَفلّميانت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, when the hours and days of the world come to an end, and that which is permitted and that which is prohibited come to an end, and when the truth is lost and the lies take over, there will be sin, and people will drink wine, and there will be adultery and usury and depravity.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلؤر ءانشنرشا الله شبرا لَ جانتا إمندر الله أَإسرافيل كا شفلا ءان ءال كوارن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And at that moment, Allah will inure himself upon the people, and He will command Içrāfil to blow the horn.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إشفلر ءان أُن شفل كا كيرن تدش لش جانتاش إيلملكاش أَمرتاسذش شن جبّريل إمكيل إإسرفيل إعزريائل كا نُ مرن شن ءانبّواش داموارتش لش خلاقذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he will blow the horn so loud that all the people will fall and the angels will faint except for Ǧibril, Mikā’il, Içrāfil, and Azaryā’il, who do not die unless the creator dies. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إدال فزتلاز دال موارتا دا إسرافيل شا تاراماسار لَ تيارا إنُ كاد ءانسم دال تيار كش فروذ كا نُ شا داربا شن لش ماسكدش إنُ كادر ءان سيال نِ أَن تيار كش بِبَ إكاذر تذ بزيُ دا مرذراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And from the fortress of the dead of Içrāfil, the Earth will tremble and nothing built on the Earth will remain except mosques, and nothing in the sky or on the Earth will remain alive, and every place will be devoid of inhabitants.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤرأَشمرشا الله عز و جل ال منذ إدر أُ منذ ذنذا شن تش أَربلاش  أُ منذ ذندا شن تش ريش  أُ منذ ذندا شن تس مرذراش  أُ منذ ذندا شن لش راياش إلش فجّش دالش رياش أُ منذ أَذ ءاشت ءال شل إلَ لن إ لش ءاشتارالّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, Allah - Almighty - will show himself to the world and say: ‘O, world! Where are your trees? O, world! Where are your rivers? O, world! Where are your inhabitants? O, world! Where are your kings and their sons? O, world! Where is the sun and the moon and the stars?’
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إنُ أَبر كيانلا راشبّند
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And there will be no one to respond. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكادر ءال منذ كورانت أَنّش إهر الله بّلبار أَو دال مر كا ءاشت دابش دال العرشا كا هزا نسار لش غواشش إلش كرناش إلَ شغارا أَش كم نسا ءال غرن دابش دال تانبّارإترنر كذ كبالّ إكذ ميانبر أَش لغر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the world will remain that way for forty years, and Allah will create rain from the sea beneath his throne. The water of this sea will resuscitate the bones and the flesh and blood as they are, like grain beneath fertile land and every hair and limb will return to its place. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دابّواش راببكر الله أَإسرافيل إشفلر ءان ال كوارن إدر أُ واشش ملذش أُ كوربش بدرذش إجّنترش ءاشبّرتدش إبانش كرتدش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After, Allah will revive Içrāfil, and he will blow the horn and say: ‘O, minced bones! O, rotten bodies and separated joints and cut veins! 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">الله أُش مند كا أُش أَجّنتايش بّر لَ داكلرسين دال ذي دال جّدسي بّرتمرش كوانت إدرش ولرذن دا بواشش أُبرش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Allah commands you to join together for the declaration of the Day of Judgment to take account of yourselves and so that you may be rewarded for your deeds. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلابنترشا أَن لش خلاقذش لش الرّحاش دالش مسلماش كلرش كن لَ كلردذ دال كارايانسي إلش الرّحاش دالش داشكارايانتاش ءاشكرش كن لَ ءاشكرادذ دال داشكارايانسيَ إيانترشا كذ الرح ءان شُ كواربّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the creations will rise. The spirits of the Muslims will be light with the lightness of their faith, and the spirits of the non-believers will be dark with the darkness of their disbelief, and each spirit will enter into his own body. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إبارايس تدش لش جّانتاش لابنتذش إيالش ءاشبّارنذ لش مربلّش إتامراش ذال ذي دال جّدسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And you will see all the risen people, and they will be awaiting the marvels and the fears of the Day of Judgment. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دانبّواش تمر الله كوانت أَلش جّانتاش إبّرن أَلش أُبديانتاش ءان لَ كش دا شُ كنتانتميانت إبّرن أَلش داشبيانتاش ءان لَ كش داش بّان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After, Allah will take an account of the people and put the believers in the house of contentment and the disbelievers in the house of pain.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم كا راببكر الله أَلش خلاقذش دابّواش دال موارتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, Allah will revive his creations after death!”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شي كم لش خلاق دا أَو إتاشك دالش لُمش دا تُ بّدرا أَلَ مدرا دا تُ مدرا إشلشتا أَل منذ كريتر جّك
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Yes, like He created them from water; like He took you out of the loins of your father into your mother and from your mother, you came out into the world as a female creature. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إتاكري كن شُ بّتانسيَ إكنبش ءان تِ تش ميانبّرش إتُ شابتذ أَشنتا متر إتاترنر أَ راببكر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And He raised you with his potency and composed your limbs and your sense. And as such, He will kill you and return to revive you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم فاجّما أَش أَشبار كن فاجّ كا يُ ءاشتيُ دالّ نُ كرنتا إتُ ذزاش باردذ أَن تذجّ بّار هزما أَشبار كا كش ءاش الجنّ ءاش كا دزاش كا ولرذنر الله كن أَلّ أَلش أُبذيانتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, help me know, as a fact without doubt, that you speak the truth in your words. Help me know what is this paradise that you speak of, with which Allah will reward his obeyors?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب لش دا الجن شن لش أُبذيانتاش أَل مندميانت ذا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, the inhabitants of paradise are those who are obedient to the command of Allah. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان أَلّ نُ مواران نِ أَبان ترشتر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There, they do not die, and there is no sadness. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَلكنسرن تذ لُ كا داشاارن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They achieve everything they want. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بارذربلاش ءان القصراش دا أُر إبّلت إبّيادرش باراسيشش إدا بّربّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They reside in castles of gold and silver and precious stones and purple. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شُ تيار ءاش أَلمسكا شش أَوش شن ذلسا شش أَربلاش أَفرُتش دربلاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The earth is musky; the waters are sweet; the trees and fruits are durable. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لش فرُتش دا دبارشش شبّراش إكلراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The fruits are diverse in taste and color. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لش دا الجنّ تيانان سيان غردش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The people of paradise enjoy one hundred domains.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا شي تدش لش جّانتاش دال منذ شا أَجّنتشان نُ هرين أُن دالّش بّركا ءان أَلّش أَي مربلّش إركازش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If all the people in the world joined together, they would not be able to replicate one of the domains because in each there are so many marvels and riches. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ بّرمار غرد ءاش دا بّلت إشُ تيار دا أَلمسكا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The first domain is of silver, and its ground is musk. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلَ شاغند ءاش دا أُر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The second domain is of gold. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ تارسار دا بّالرش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The third is of pearls. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلَ شاتان يَ با ءان أَلّ لُ كا نُ أَي أُجّش كا بوادن بار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And in the sixth, you see what your eyes cannot see. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لانو دازير إبّشر بّر كرسناش دا أُنباراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Its language is of speech that passes directly into the hearts of men. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إءال كا مش باكان غرد أَلكنسا شياتا أَلقصراش دا أُر إبّلت إبّارلش إبّيادرش باراسيشش ذا دبارشش كلراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He who reaches the smallest domain achieves seven castles of gold and silver and pearls and precious stones of different colors. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش كونذ شلان دا شش لغراش كبالغن ءان أَنملاش كا بلن كن الّش ذندا كياران فشت لَ بّوارت دا أَلجنّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When these figures travel from anywhere to anywhere else, they ride animals that fly with them to wherever they want to go, until they arrive at the door of paradise. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَلّي نسا أُن فوانتا كن ذش رمش إكونذ بابان ءان ءال أُن دا ألّش دش رمش شك دال كوارب تذ لَ ءانبذي إءانغن إملدد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And there a fountain with two branches emerges, and when one drinks from one branch of the fountain, all the envy and deceit and evil leaves one's body. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءانبّواش بننشا ءان أَل أُتر إترننشا جّباناش كا ننك مش شا مدن دا شش كلراش نِ دا باراشنش إكلمن أَ لش أَسِترش دال بّوارت إفزا أُن شنذ كا ننك أُيارن لش جّانتاش مش دلسا كش 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After, one bathes in the other branch and becomes young and can never become old. And he can knock on the door and make a sound sweeter than any sound ever heard.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إشلان لش الحرش دا أَلجنّ أَ لَ بّوارت كا شن كا الله سبحانه أَ دذ كنسميانت أَلش أُنباراش أَجدرين أَ ءالّش إيانترنكن لش أُنباراش أَلجنّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the female-angels 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>These figures symbolize purity.</p>
								</note> 
								answer the door. Believers know about this door because of the will of Allah - glory be to him. The female-angels bow to them and then they enter into paradise. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكونذ كيارا ءاتررشا ءال أُنبارا ءان القصر كا بايا ذزانلا ءالّش: أَدالنتا أَي أُتر ماجّر يا الولي ذا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when a man wants to enter a castle he sees, they say to him: ‘Up ahead, there is a better one, companion of Allah.’
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءانبّواش لّاغا أَتر القصر كلر كا شا بّراسا ذانذا فوا تذ لُ ذا دانتر إكيارا ءال أُنبارا ءانتررساش ءان أَل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then they arrive at another castle of light; it seems to be transparent, exposing what it contains inside, so the man wants to enter. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ذزنلا ءالّش أَدالنتا أَي أُتر ماجّر بّشذ يا أَميغ دا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They say: ‘Up ahead there is a better inn, friend of Allah.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إنُ ساشن دا أَندر كن ءال دا القصر ءان القصر فشت كا لّاغن أُن القصر كا تذ ءاش ءاشملتذ إيانغشتنذ ءان بّيادرش باراسيشش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they don’t stop walking with him, from castle to castle, until they arrive at a castle completely enameled with gold and mounted with precious stones.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا أَي ءان أَل شتانت كمرش أُنّش شبّرا أُترش أَراادش دا تذش أَرااش إورنسيناش إجّيش سالاشتريلاش كلرافكذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And inside there are sixty chambers, some on top of others, hanging from harnesses, and platters and clarified, celestial jewels. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إبّنارلا أَ أُن كرن ءان لَ كباس كا تيانا شاتانت رنكناش ءان كذ رنكن أَي بياذر باراسيش كا رالنبّر تاراش جّرندش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they put a crown that has seventy nooks on his head, and in each nook is a precious stone that sparkles three times as bright as daylight. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إشُ كر كم لُنَ إشُ مَنُ أُن بارذغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His face becomes like the moon, and in his hand appears a sword. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إشبّرا شُ باراشن شاتانتا كربارترش دا شاد إبّركذ دا ذبارشش كلراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His body is covered with seventy shrouds of silk, woven from diverse colors. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءاشتند أَشي بيانالا أُن مجّار دالش الحرّش دا الجنّ كن أَتبيش مي هارمشش رالنبرنتاش كم ءال شل كا كن لَ بشت دالّ أُلبذ ءال نبارا تذ كونت أَ بشت 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Like that, in very handsome attire that sparkles like the sun, they bring him to a woman of the angels of paradise, and when he sees her like that, he forgets anything he has seen before.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إدر لَ مجّار تُ ءاراش مِ أَمد إيُ شي تُ أَمذ 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the woman will say: ‘You are my beloved, and I am your beloved.’
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إأَشيانتشا ءان بّر دال ءان كم أَكنبنّد دا شتانت الحرّش إكاذ ءال نبارا كن أَلّش ءان غرسي فانكنتا إبذ دالايتش ءان لَ بازنذذ دال شانّر دال منذ إلش الملكاش دنذ السلام شبّر ءال 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they sit, as a pair, on a bed, accompanied by seventy female-angels, and the man remains in real grace and delightful life, close to the God of the world and with angels welcoming him.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إنُ داشان كش كا نُ لَ الكنسن الّي ذنذا شا ءاشتن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they do not want anything that they can’t reach there, right where they are. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان الجنّ أَي الحرّش كا شِ ءاشكبّياشان ءان لَ مر شاترنري دلسا ءال مر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In paradise, there are female-angels that will turn the sea sweet if they spit in it. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إتيانان ءاشكربّت ءان شش فارانتاش كا دزا كيان داشا أُن مجّار كم يُ أُبّرا كن لَ أُبادانسي دا مشانّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they have an inscription on their brow that says: ‘Whoever wants a woman like me, act with obedience to my God.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان الجنّ أَي أُن أَربل كا شلّم ءال أَربل دال بوان أَبانترنس كا لُ بّلنت الله تعلى كن شُ مَنُ كا ش ترنك ءاش دا أُر شش بانش دا بّلت شش فريتش كرشتلاش شش رمش كرلاش شش فجّش ءاشملتدش شغلر المسكا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In paradise, there is a tree called The Tree of Good Adventure, that Allah - the Superior - planted with His hand. Its trunk is golden; its veins are silver; its fruits are crystals; its branches are corals; its leaves are enameled; and its odor is musky. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان ءال أَي دا تدش لش نترلازش دا فريتش دا الجنّ ءان شبّر إكلر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In it, there are all the natural fruits of paradise in flavor and color. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان الجنّ أَي أَربلاش كا شلان دا ألّش أَنملاش ورداسذش بلنتاش كا ننك أُرنن نِ هزان رداز ننغن كا ليابن أَلش أُبذيانتاش أَذندا كياران
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In paradise, there are trees from which flying animals come out who never urinate nor defecate, and who transport those who are obedient to wherever they want. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان الجنّ أَي أُن رِيُ كا شا دزا الكوثر كا شلا دابش دا العرشا كا ءاش مش دلسا كا ميال إمش بلنك كا لاجّا كا كرا شبّرا لشش دا بّارلش إبّيادرش باراسيشش المسكدش كا من دا أَلّي لَ فوانتا دا ساسبل إلَ فوانتا دا الكافر إلَ فوانتا دا تسنيم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In paradise there is a river called “al-Kawthar”; it originates at the throne of Allah and is sweeter than honey and whiter than the milk that runs on pearl tiles; it is musky; precious stones flow from there to the fountain of Çalçabil and the fountain of al-Kafur and the fountain of Taçnim. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إنُ أَي ءان الجنّ شن لش لنلّش إلش سجّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And in paradise, there are only pupils and eyebrows.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>This is a curious characterization. One interpretation is that these figures represent consciousness and expression, free from bodily mandate. What is clear, however, is the absence of the flesh.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إلش ريش دا الجنّ تذش ساركذش دا كترادش داشترذش إفريتش ذا الجنّ إبابّرجّاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the rivers in paradise are surrounded by chairs and raised platforms and fruits of paradise and beverages. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نُ هزان رداز ننغن شلا لداجشتين ءان شذر دا ماجّرغلر كا المسكا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They never defecate: excrement leaves the body in a sweat of the best odor of musk.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لش مرذراش دا الجنّ نُ شا ءانباجّاسان نِ ءانفارمن نِ مواران
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The residents of paradise do not age, nor do they get sick or die. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نِ بايان بّاشر نِ ءاشبّنتن نِ ترشتاز نِ تربلسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They do not experience sorrow, fright, sadness, or tribulation themselves, and they do not see it in others. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شش ربش ننك شا رنبّن نِ شا ءانباجّاسان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their clothes never tear or become worn. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ أُن دا لش دا الجنّ بّشياشا شُ من ءان ءال منذ نُ كاذري سياغ كا نُ بياشا نِ موارت كا نُ راببكشا نِ داشكارايانتا كا نُ كاراياشا نِ ءانفارم كا نُ شنشا نِ أَو شلذ كا نُ فواش ذلسا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If one inhabitant of paradise put his hand in the world, there wouldn’t be a blind person who couldn’t then see, a dead person who wouldn’t revive, a non-believer who wouldn’t then believe, a sick person who wouldn’t become healthy, nor salty water that wouldn’t become sweet. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ أُن ذا لش دا الجنّ أَشمشا شُ كرأَلَ تيارّ إءاجّشا أُن شلب ءان أَلّ ترنري تذ المسكا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If one of the inhabitants of paradise peeked his face out to the Earth and spit on it, everything would turn to musk. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ شِ أُن دالش دا الجنّ شكشا شكر أَلَ تيار ترنري لَ كلر ذال شل إ دا لَ لُنَ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If one of the inhabitants of paradise exposed his face to the Earth, the heat of the sun would become like the heat of the moon.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ شِ لش جّانتاش شبياشان لش دالايتاش دا الجنّ مرين تذش بّر شُ داشا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And if the men knew of the delights of paradise, everyone would die because they desired it so much. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ نُ بشتاري ننغن أَ دازير لش غرسيش دا الجنّ نِ شش مربلش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And it would not be enough for anyone to simply desire the graces of paradise and its marvels.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم بّر شاماجّنتا دا أكال أُبّررن لش أُبّرنتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, the believers worked in order to attain that paradise. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم دا أَكال شانّر تن غرندا كا دزاش أَ كذ ءان مِ كرسن أَمر مي غرندا كا ننك ساسرا دا شُ شاربسي إ أُبدانسي فشت كا لُ ءانكوانتارا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Dove, this powerful God you speak of, who has landed in my heart with such a great love, I will never stop serving him and obeying him until I find him. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَغر هزما أَ شبار كا شار لَ بّان دا كيان داشباداسا أَد الله إكما شُ أَرزقا إ شربا أَ أُتر شانّر مانش دال
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Now help me understand the pain of whoever disobeys Allah and consumes his divine fortune and worships another God besides him.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لبّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كيان داشباداسا أَذ الله شُ بّان ءاش ءال فواغ دا جهنّم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Whoever disobeys Allah, his pain is the fire of Hell. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا نُ مواران نِ بابان إ كذ دي لاش كاراسن بّان شبّرا بّان لش كتبش ءان الفواغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He does not live or die, and every day, pain grows upon itself; he is a captive in the fire. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا ننك ءاش كت شُ كتبّري نِ أَليبيانسد شُ بّان نِ كنشلد شُ ترتش نِ ءاشكلراذ شُ ءاشكرادذ نِ أُإدش شش كاجّش نِ أَبيدذ شُ بز
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their captivity is never revoked; their pain is never alleviated; their sadness is never consoled; their murkiness is never clarified; their desires are never heard, nor is their voice. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شُ ترشتاز ءاش فوارتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their sadness is strong. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شُ شلر ءاش فنذ شُ أَو ءاش بّسنّ 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their loneliness is deep, and their water is rancid.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شش أَراش شن فيارش شُ بّان ءاش ذلرش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their chains are iron, and their pain is truly painful. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شُ لانّ ءاش بياذرش إجّانتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The firewood is composed of rocks and people. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نِ شا راغل شُ فيار نِ شا مت شُ فواغ نِ شا أَكب شُ بّان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The iron does not yield, nor does the fire die, nor does their pain end. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَل ءاشتن تيانبّش شِن كوانت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There, there is time without counting. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شش كمسش ءاش أَلكترن أَرديانتا شش كاسش بّاز ءانساندذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their shirts are burning tar; their shoes are ignited tar. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شش ربش سفرا فلماانتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their clothes are made of flaming sulphur. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شش بناتاش فيار رشيانتا إشبّرا ءالّش أَلملكاش فوارتاش كالش ترنارن كن غرفيش دا فيار فغانتا شُ بابرجّا ءاش كبّرا داراتذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their caps are iron--pink with heat, and above them are strong angels who return with flaming iron, whose potion is deteriorated copper. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">جهنم تيانا شياتا بّوارتش دا بّوارت أَبّوارت أَندذرا دا كنيانتش أَنش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Hell has seven doors, and from door to door, the walk takes five hundred years. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ بّرمار شْ لَم جهنم بّركا كما لش كرناش دا لش كافراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The first door is named Ǧahannam because the flesh of non-believers is eaten there. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ شاغنذ شْ لم لظا بّركا كما لش بّياداش إلش منش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The second is called Laẓẓā because the hands and feet are ingested there. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ تارسار شْ لم سقر بّركا ءانسياندا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The third is called Çaqar because it is aflame. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ كورت شْ لم أَلحطم بّركا ترشبّش شُ فواغ تذش لش ميانبّرش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The fourth is called al-Ḥuṭama because its fires pass through all of the limbs and organs of those who enter. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ كنت شْ لم سعير بّركا شُ فواغ ننك شا مت جّمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The fifth is called Çaᶜir because its fire never dies. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ شايشان شْ لم أَلجحيم كا أُن سانتالّ كامري تذ ءال منذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The sixth is called al-Ǧaḥim because one spark from its fire will burn the whole world. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لَ شاتان شْ لم أَلهاوي كا كيان ءانترر ءان أَل ننك شلا جّمش ءان أَل ءاشت ءال بّز دا أَلهبهب كا كونذ شا ابّرا كام أَلتر فواغ دا جهنم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The seventh is called al-Hāwiya because he who enters never leaves, and inside is the well of al-Habhab, and when it opens, its fire burns all the other fires of Hell. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ أَل فواغ دا جهنم ءاش ناغر ءاشكر إشبرا كد بّوارت دا جهنم أَي مل كباسش دا فواغ ءان كد كباس شاتانت مل كباسش دا فواغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the fire of Hell is black and dark, and upon each door of Hell, there are one thousand busts of fire
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>These "busts" mean, roughly, structural protrusions. It is unclear if they refer to the exact kind of sculpture that in English would be called a bust (a representation of a human figure including their head to their upper chest). They are structural features that the text multiplies ad infinitum to create an effect of unimaginable quantities.</p>
								</note> and on each bust there are seventy-thousand busts of fire. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إدزا جهنم ءال ذي دا لجّدسي شانّر كاراسا ءان مي ءالرذر إ لَ فرتلاز بّر كا تما أِي بانغنس دا أَكالش كا تْ داشباداسيارن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And Hell speaks on the Day of Judgment and says: ‘God, grow my ardor and fortress so that I can take revenge today on those who have disobeyed you.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إكونذ لش ءاجّن دانتر لّرن لغرمش فشت كا شا ءانشغن إ شنغارا غشت كا شا أَكبا إ متاري فشت كا شا داشاكن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when he throws the non believers inside, they shed tears until they have been soaked, blood until there is no more, and matter until they are desiccated.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لّرن تنت كا شِ ءاجّشان نباش ءان شش لغرمش كرارين كم ءان لَ مر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they cry so much that if you threw ships into their tears, they would sail as they do in the sea. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ننك شن أَبّيدذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they are never pitied. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ قونذ بارن لش جّانتاش أَ جهنم كيرن أَمرتاسذش دا شتامر إ نُ رواغ ننغن شن بّر شي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the people see Hell, they fall dead from fear and no one begs for anyone else except himself. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">فيرن لش مدراش دا لش فجّش إ لش فجّش دا لش مدراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Mothers flee from their sons, and sons flee from their mothers.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">هزازشا أَن كنشش لش مسش بّواش كونذ تش منسابش شن لابذش أَل فواغ دزيانذ أُ نواش جّبانتد مل أَبانترذش بّواش ءال فواغ أَ دا شار نواش مرد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the youth become hoary. When the young men are taken to the fire, they say: ‘O, our youth! Bad luck! The fire will be our new home.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كونتشس مجّاراش فارمشش كارن ذزيانذ أُ نواش فارمشر إبالدذ مل ءانبالااد بّواش كا ءال فواغ ءاش نواش مرد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So many beautiful women who go and say: ‘O, our handsomeness and beauty is wasted. Well, the fire is our new home.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كونتش بياجّش كنش كا أَرن أَل فواغ دزيانذ أُ نواشش كنش إ فلكاز مل غشتذ بّواش أَل فواغ أَ دا شار نواش مرذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">So many hoary old people that go to the fire, say: ‘O, our grey hairs and frailty are poorly spent! Well, the fire is our new home.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شارن أَبّرذش دالله إ بّرتذش ذا شُ بّدذ إ داشبادذش داشش غرشيش إ بينش لغدش شش منش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They will be ignored by Allah and parted from His piety, removed from their graces and property; their hands are tied. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءانكداندش شش كوالش ءانساندذش شش لانوش ناغرش شش كرش لرغ شُ ترشتاز ذرنتا شُ بّان هنبّريانتش شاذيانتش دلرشش دزيانذ يَ نش أَبّرك شُ بّان ترشتاش دا نشترش بّرلُ كا ذافلاسمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Their necks are chained; their tongues are ignited; their faces are black; their sadness is long; their pain endures hunger, sweat, and aches, saying: ‘Your pain already encompasses us, poor creatures, for our failures. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ شا كاشن نُ لش أَبّيدن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If they complain, no one pities them. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ كلمن نُ لش راشبّندان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If they clamour, no one responds. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دزان شانّر فوامش يارذش أَلبيناسا شبرا نشاترش لَ بّان أُن ذي شل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They say: ‘God, we have erred. Alleviate our pain for just one day.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر لابنتشا أُن نبا ناغر دافواغ إ يالش دامندن أَو إ بّيانشن كا لش أَبّيدن كن أَو
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then a black cloud of fire rises, and they demand water, and they think they will receive pity in the form of water.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لّوابا شبّرا ءالش بّيادرش إأَو بلانتا كالش ترشبش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And rocks rain upon them and harsh water washes over them.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دا فواغ كمان دا فواغ بابان إ شبّرا فواغ شا أَكواشتن 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They eat fire; they drink fire; and upon fire they sleep.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شبّرا فواغ كلمن أَمالك دزا الله يا مالك راشبّندا أَ لش لزرذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Burning, they clamour to Malik. Allah says: ‘Malik, respond to the disgraced.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر دزالاش مالك يا أَكالّش كا شا أَ ءانشنذ شبّرالّش كا كارايش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, Malik says to them: ‘Provokers of Allah’s anger, what do you want?’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دزانلا يا مالك دنش أَبابار أُن بابد دا أَو كا رافيارا بّواشش كواربّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They say to him: ‘Malik, give us a drink of water to refresh our bodies.’ 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر ذلاش أَبابار أَو ذ أَلجحم كا ءانتر بّر لش بكش إ دارب لش ديانتاش إ بّرش لش ءانترنش إدارتا لش كرناش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, he gives them water to drink from al-Ǧaḥim that enters their mouths and demolishes their teeth and burns their bowels and melts their flesh. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">هزا بلّر لش ماذلّش ءان لش كباسش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It makes their brains boil in their heads. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا شي أُن غت كيلّشا شبّرا لَ تيار دا أَكالّ أَو مرين لش جّانتاش دا شُ هاذر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If one drop of this water fell on the Earth, men would die from its stench. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شبّرا كذ بّوارت دا جهنم أَي مل مراش دا فواغ ذا أَنذذر ذا كنيانتش انّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Around every door in Hell there are one thousand seas of fire, the length of which would require walking for five hundred years. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان كد مر مل سبدداش دا فواغ ءان كد سبدذ مل الجباش ذا فواغ ءان كد الجبا مل كشش دا فواغ ءان كد كش مل فوانتاش دا فواغ دا كد فوانتا شلان مل ريش دا فواغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">In each sea, there are a thousand cities of fire, and in each city, there are one thousand wells of fire, and in each well, there are one thousand houses of fire, and in each house there are one thousand fountains of fire, and from each fountain, one thousand rivers of fire emanate. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا شِ أُن غت كلّشا دا أَكال أَو ءان لَ تيار أَبّرشري تذ ءال منذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If one drop of the water that comes from these rivers fell on Earth, it would burn the whole world. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ نُ أَي كش مش أَبّرذ ءان بّدار ذا الله كالش دال فواغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There is nothing more hated in the power of Allah than those who are in the fire.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر فواشا لَ بّلم إ كاذ لَ ذنزالّ دزيانذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, the dove departed and left the little damsel saying:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ترشتازدا مي يا ترشتاز كا بّك أَ شيذ مِ كنسميانت كن مي كريذر غوي دا لش شاربذراش دا لش إذلش ءان جهنم إيانش بّان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My sadness, O! Woe is me. How little I knew about my creator. Woe are the idolaters in Hell and in pain. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">غوي دا مي كا شار دا مي كونذ ما بّررا دالنتا دا مِ شانّر أَلَ كوانت إشابّرر ءال بّاش أَشا تردار ءالصراط ترشتا دا مي أَكال ذي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">O, Woe is me. What will become of me when I come before my God for judgment, and he weighs my virtues and sins
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>A fundamental concept in Islam. On the day of judgment, a person's good and bad deeds are said to be weighed against one another to determine that person's integrity and posthumous merit.</p>
								</note> 
								on the Judgment Day and readies the cord 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>A possible reference to the umbilical cord</p>
								</note> 
								to be cut? My sadness on that day!”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ أُدي ششبّر إكيُ أَمرتاسد إ نُ راكرذ شن أَبّاراش دا تاراش ديش فشت كا لّاغ لَ نواب أَ شُ بّدرا إبن أَ بارلُ إدش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she sighed and fainted and did not remember anything. Three days later, the news reached her father, who came to see her and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ بّلزار دا مش أُجّش كا ءاش تُ فاجّ كا أَش أَبذ كا ما ءا كابّرنتذ كن تُ مل مِ كرسن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, pleasure of my eyes, what is your condition? You have disrupted my heart with your poor condition.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر لابنتشا لَ ذنزالّ دامدد لّرند دامدد دا كلر إذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, the damsel rose, pale and crying, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا دافياندما كن الله دال فواغ دا جهنم إ دا شش بّانش أَكالش كا نُ أَبّيذرن أَلبياجّ بّر شُ باجّاس نِ أَلجِك بّر شُ بّاكاناس نِ أَلمجّار بّر شفلكاز
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, defend me with Allah from the fire of Hell and its pains, from those who do not pity the old for their age nor the young for their youth nor woman for her frailty.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ذيش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ أَش بشت أَلغ ءان تُ درمر أُ ءاشتش هاجّزد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, have you seen something in your sleep or are you bewitched?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said to him:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا أَنتاش دامنذ بّاردن أَدا الله مِ شانّر إ تُ شانّر داش ءال شاربسي دالش إذلش أَكالّش كا نُ أُيان نِ بّاءان نُ نوازان نِ أَبّرباجن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, first, ask for pardon from Allah - my God and your God. Leave the service of idols, those who neither hear nor see, neither harm nor benefit.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر مند ءال راي ترءار شُ إدل إدشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, the king commanded that her idol be brought, and he said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ءاشتا ءاش تُ شانّر إ مِ شانّر أَكال كا نُ كنسامش شن أَ ءال ترنتا ءان تُ شانتذ إ شربا أَ تُ شانّر إ نُ شاش يارذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, this is your God and my God, and we do not know another like him. Return to your senses and serve your God and don’t be mistaken.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا تُ ءاراش ءاليارذ داش ءال شاربسي دالش إذلش إ دِ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله شل شن أَبّرسار ءان ال سيال ءاش شُ العرشا إ ءان لَ تيار شُ بّتاشتذ إ شانّريُ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, you are mistaken. Leave the service of idols, and say that there is no God except Allah alone - without companion. This throne is in the heavens, and on Earth is his power and reign.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كونذ أُي إبلس ملذغل الله ءال ننبّرميانت دا الله شلّ دال إدل هيانذ إ أَل كا ذزيَ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation"> When Ibliç - God curse him - heard the name of Allah, he left the idol, fleeing, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا راي نجرب يَ شا أَنبذ ءان تُ تيار أَن فاجّ كا نُ ترنرءا أَ تُ إذل ءان جّمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“King Naǧreb, something new is happening in your kingdom and so the day has come when I will never return.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">تم ءال راي بّر أَشت غرندا بّيانش إذش أَ شُ فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This caused the king to think for a long time, and he said to his daughter:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ترنتا دا لُ كا ءاشتش إ نُ أَفوالّاش تُ لاي نِ تا أَبّرتش أَ ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, revert to what you were. Do not leave your laws nor draw away from the idol.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ديشلا شُ فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And his daughter said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا داش ما أُن بّك
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, leave me for a little.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش لؤر داشل إ فواشا ءالّ أَ شُ إذل إ ياشمانزل تد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">As soon as he left her, she went to the idol and crumbled everything that was on it. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ تم ءال أُر إل بّلت إلش بّارلش دا شُ إذل إبّرتيل أَلش بّبراش ءان شاربسي دا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she took the gold and silver and pearls from the idol and gave them to the poor in service of Allah. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ بن شُ بّدرا إ هلّ لَ إدل كابّرذ إ ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And her father came and found the idol broken and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ فاجّ أَشكش مي غرندا كا شي أُتر لُ أُبياشا فاجّ بّانرل إ يَ كن ترمانتش فوارتاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, you have done a very repulsive thing. If another had done this, I would have tortured him gravely.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا شِ فواشا شانّر كم تُ ذزاش نُ شا أَبّري داشذ ءاشمانزر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, if it were a God, like you say, it wouldn’t have been decimated by my crumbling it. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا مِ شانّر ءال كا يُ شيارب خلاقذر دالش خلاقذش ءال كا دَ لش أَلرزكاش تانداذر دا لش غرسيش نُ لا دنّ كش ننغن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">My God, the one I serve - Creator of the creations, He who gives riches, Keeper of blessings--nothing hurts Him.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالراي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ترنتا دا لك أَشتش شِ نُ يُ تا بّانرا بّان فوارتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, revert to what you were, otherwise I will punish you with great pain.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ دزيانذ ءاشت فواشا إ داشل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And saying this, he went away and left her. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش بلبيشا لَ ذنزالّ ءان دينر إ هزار أَصلى إ كمار بّن دا سابد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then, the damsel returned to her pious devotion and prayed and ate barley bread. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ رغ أَذا الله كا لا ءانبايش لبّلم إ بنلا أَ أَلّ إ هلّ هزياند أَصلى
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She begged Allah to send the dove, and the dove came and found her praying. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ دي أَلسلام شبّرالّ إ ترن ءال سلام إ ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He bestowed peace upon her, and she greeted the dove and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يُ شي مي أَلاغرا كن تُ بايد
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I am very happy that you came. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يُ كارا ءان الله إ لاشرب إ نُ بّنغ أَبّرسار كن أَل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I believe in Allah, and I serve him, and I do not consider anyone his peer.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لَ بّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب أَلاغرتا كا الله أَ راسابذ تُ رابتانسي أَ بّارذنذ تُ بّاكذ لؤر كا أَش داشذ ءال شاربسي دال إدل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, be happy that Allah has accepted your repentance and has pardoned your sin the moment you abandoned the service of idols. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءال سلام شاء شبّرا تِ إ بّيدذ دا الله شاء شبّرا تِ إ شُ باندسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Peace be upon you, and may Allah’s mercy and his benediction be upon you as well.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ فواشا لَ بّلم إ ترنشا لَ ذنزالّ أَهزار أَلصلى إ دينر إ رغر أَذ الله كا لَ شلبشا دال بّان دا جهنم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the dove left, and the little damsel returned to prayer and to fasting, begging Allah to save her from the pain of Hell. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إبّلكشا شُ فاجّ ءان تذ شُ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And her state [of piety] was made public in the whole kingdom. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">هبلبن دالّ لش جّانتاش راتبن أَلراي دزيانذلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The people gossiped about her, and rebuked her to the king and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ ذاشش أَ تُ فجّ أَشي كم ءاشت بّاردارشا أَ تُ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“If you allow your daughter to continue like this, you will lose your crown.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ تم ءال راي مي غرندا كيدذ إ فواشا أَ ءال إ دشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king became very cautious, and he went to her and said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ترنتا دا لُ كا ءاستش إ نُ ما ءاجّاش أَ بّاردار مي رين نِ تا أَبّرتاش دا نواشتر شانّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, return to what you were, and don’t make me lose my kingship and don’t part from our God.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديشلا شُ فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">His daughter said to him:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا {يُ تْ} اءال ادشلا شرسي دا الله إ تُ كلمشما أَل شاربسي دالش إدلش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, I call you to the service of Allah, and you beg me to serve idols. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا، أُباداسا أَد الله إ دِ كم يُ دغ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله شل كا نُ أَي أَبّرسر كن أَل إ درتا الله ءال ألجن إ شلبّرش دا فواغ دا جهنم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Father, obey Allah and say what I say, that there is no God except Allah - alone - who has no peers, and give yourself to Allah, and save yourself from the fire of Hell.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ شِ نُ تا دابيادش دا لُ كا ءاشتش كرتارتا لش منش إ شكرتا دا مِ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, if you do not deviate from what you have become, I will cut off your hands and expel you from my kingdom.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا نُ ما ترنرا دا لبّلبر دا لا اله الا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, I will not change myself from believing the words, ‘There is no God except Allah.’”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دشلا شُ بّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Her father said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ يُ تانغ مياذ كا تا أَرابّانترش كونذ نُ تا أَبّرباجّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I am afraid that you will regret this when it does not serve you. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا شِ نُ تا ترنش دا لُ كا ءاشتش كرترتا لش منش إ شكرتا أَ لش منتاش كن لش أَنملاش فيارش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If you do not change from what you are, I will cut off your hands and banish you to the mountains with the wild animals. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ نُ تْ بّدرش أَبّرباجر كن تش منش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">You will not be able to survive without your hands.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش كعب أَلاحباركا نُ كاراسي لَ ذنزالّ شن ءان أَل شاربسي دا الله تعلى
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār said that the damsel would not grow in her religious devotion unless she served Allah - the Superior. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لش جّانتاش فبلبن دالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The people spoke about her.
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>These are the people to whom Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār is recounting this story.</p>
								</note>
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أُنش دزين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Some said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لُ كَ شا أَ ترند
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“She has gone crazy.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أُترش دزين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Others said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَ هلّد أُتر مجّر لاي كا شُ بّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“She found a better rule than that of her father.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش أَل ركنتدر كا بلبيُ شُ بّدرا ءال إ ذشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The storyteller said that her father returned to her and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ترنتا دا لُ كا ءاشتش شِ نُ يُ هرا لُ كا ذيجّ تانغ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, return to what you were or I will do what I have said. I have to.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا أَأُنك ما كرتاش إ ما كاماش كن فواغ نُ كاراسار شن ءان ءال شاربسي دا الله مِ شانّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Father, even if you cut me or burn me with fire, I will not grow unless I serve Allah - my God.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّدرا داش ءال شاربسي دالش إذلش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Father, leave the service of idols. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا يُ شي داشانغننّتا دا تي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It is for that that I have disengaged from you. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دِ كم يُ دغ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله شل شن أَبّرسار كن أَل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Say, as I say, and there is no God except Allah - alone, without peers.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش ديش كعب أَلاخبار كا كونذ بذ أَكالّ شُ بّدرا منذ بانر شُ شلّين بّر كرترلا لش منش إ كونذ ءالّ لُ بذ ءاشتاراجّشالا ءال كرشن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Well, as Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār said, when her father saw this, he ordered an executioner to come and cut off her hands, and when she saw him, her heart began to narrow. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لابنتا شُ كباس أَل شيال لّرنذ إ أَيال كا ذزي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She lifted her head towards heaven, crying, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا كيان خلاق لش سيالش رافرم مِ كارسن بّن سفرانسي ءان مي نُ تا أَيراش كن مي نُ داش لغر أَلشّطن ءان مِ فاجّ أَبّدما كن تُ بّيدذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“He who created the heavens, make my heart sure. Give me patience. Do not be angry with me. Leave no place for devils in my constitution. From your mercy, give me mercy.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">راكوانت كعب أَلاخبار كا ءان أَشتا بّش لا ءانبي الله لَ بّلم إ بّششا جنت أَ ءال إ دشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Kaᶜbu al-Aḥbār recounted that in that moment, Allah sent the dove and put it next to her, and it said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ دا نجرب أَلاغرتا كا لَ غرسي دا الله ءاش كن تِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter of Naǧreb, be happy that the grace of Allah is with you. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">سفرا كا الله تا در ءال أَلجنّ ءال ذي دال جسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Suffer so Allah will give you paradise on the Day of Judgment.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لش أَلملكاش رغبن لّرنذ بّر أَلّ إ لش أَلحرش دا أَلجنّ كا شا أَشمبن أَ ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the angels begged for her, crying, and the women of paradise summed it up for her: 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش سفرا كن لُ كا شا أَشانتذ كن تِ إ نُ شا تُ سفرانسي شن كن الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Have patience with what has been prescribed to you, and with Allah, it will not be your own suffering.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر دشلا شُ بّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, her father said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ ترتا دا لُ كا ءاشتش أَنتاش كا تا كرتا لش منش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Daughter, pull yourself away from what you are before I cut off your hands.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">هز لُ كا كارش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Do what you want. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا نُ ترنرا دا لُ كا ءاشتي نِ داشرا لَ وبادانسي بّرلَ داشوبادانسي نِ ءال خلاقذر بّرءال خلاقذ ن أَلجنّ بّر جهنم نِ ذاشرا أَذ الله بّر لش إذلش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I will not change who I am, nor will I leave my obedience for disobedience, nor the creator for the creation, nor paradise for Hell, nor Allah for idols.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش لؤر منذ شُ بّدرا كرترلا لش منش إ يالّ كا دازيَ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, her father ordered her hands to be cut off, and she said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">باسم الله شانّر دا لش سيالش باسم الله شانّر دا لش تيارش باسم الله ءال ترنتا ءان أَل شانّري
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“In the name of Allah - God of the heavens, in the name of Allah - God of the Earth, in the name of Allah - the Master of power. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر دَما سفرانسي إ أَفرمما ءان تُ أُبادايسي 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">God, give me suffering and affirm me in your obedience.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كنشوال مِ كرسن
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Console my heart.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لّربن تذش أَرانكربنشا أَذ الله لش دالش سيالش إ دا لش تيارش إ ذزين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Everyone cried and lamented Allah of the heavens and Earth, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر مر لُ كا شا أَ أَشانتذ كن أَكالّ ذنزالّ بّر تُ أُبادانسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“God, look what has happened to this damsel because of her obedience to you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دزا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Allah said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">تذ ءاش أَ مِ بشت بّر مي انر إ نبلاز
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Everything in my vision is honorable and noble. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا يُ لا درا ولرذن كنبلذ إ لَ بّرنا ءان لَ غرذ دا لش أُنرذش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I will give her a complete reward, and I will make her an honored figure.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ كرترنلا لش منش إ كترنلا لش جيش كا تانيا إ ياجّرنل أَلش يارمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they cut off her hands, and they took the jewels that she had, and they threw her into the wilderness. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كاد كن غرندا ءاشبّنت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She was very frightened. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كلم كن لَ مش أَلت داش بز لرنذ إ ذزيانذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She clamoured with the loudest voice she had, crying, and saying:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا مِ شانّر إ مِ كودلّ إ مِ باركرذر أَشا ءانباراباسد مِ بّدرا كوانتر مِ أَما شكذ أَ ءاشاتش يارمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My God, my leader, my agent who has made my father enraged with me, who has brought me to the wilderness. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر الله كنشوال مِ شلادذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Allah, console my loneliness.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش أَندنذ بّر أُن شرل غيُل الله أُن كواب أَلهلد دا أُن منتا إ هلّ أُنش إ لبش إ أُترش أَنملاش دال تيار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Walking on a path, Allah guided her to a cave at the seat of a mountain, and she found bears and wolves and other animals of the Earth. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لؤر كن أَكردرشا دا لُ كا لا أَبي ديجّ شُ بّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And at that moment, she came to terms with what her father had said. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">سارتافكشا كن لَ موارتا إ ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She knew it was certain that she would die, and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لا اله الّا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“There is no God except Allah. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شِ ما كمارن لش أَلمنش نُ بّانرا شن أُن أُر إ يانبّواش ترنر أَ لش غرسيش دا مِ شانّر أَن أَلجن بّر شيانبارا جمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">If the animals eat me, I will not be in pain except for an hour, and after, I will return to the graces of my God in paradise forevermore. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَنشي أَنتر ءان لَ كواب إ ساركرنل لش أَلمنش إ ذبنلا أَلسلام أَ ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Then she entered the cave, and the animals approached her and bestowed peace upon her. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ذزينلا أَ ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَلاغرتا كا لبّيدذ دا الله ءاش شبّرا تِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Be happy. The piety of Allah is upon you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ جغبن كن أَلّ كم ءالبّار كن ش أَم إ تراينلا دالش فريتش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they played with her like a dog with its owner, and they brought her fruits. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ كمي ءالّ إ أَشتب أَشي لُ كا كِش الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She ate the fruits, and she behaved as Allah desired. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">فشت كا أُن دي شلّ أَكس ءال راي دا أَنتاقيا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">[Things continued like this] until one day, the king of Antaqiya 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Antioch</p>
								</note> 
								went out hunting. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ أَيانكنترشا كن أُن سيارب إ شيلَ فشت كا شا لنس ءان لَ كواب كا ءاشتب لَ ذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He came upon her servant, and he followed the servant until he entered the cave where the damsel was. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ أَلّ ءار مجّار هارمش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she was a beautiful woman. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كونذ لَ بذ ءال راي أَنمرشا دالّ إ ذشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When the king saw her, he fell in love with her and said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ذنزالّ ءارش بّارشن أُ ءاراش أَلجنا 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, are you a person or a fairy? 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا كوش أَشاذ لَ تُيَ كا أَش أَبانذ أَ أَشتا لغر كن لش أَنملاش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">What is the cause for your coming here, to this place with these animals? 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شلتا أَ مي كا شي ءال راي دا أَنتاقيا يُ تا تمر بّر مجّار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Come out with me. I am the king of Antaqiya, and I will take you for my wife.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">دش الّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يُ شيا كيان شِ كشيار شانّرش ءان أَلمنذ يَ تاني لُ كا تُ كيدش كا تياناش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“If I were someone who wanted power in this world, I would already have it. I already have what you covet.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا دنزالّ دما كيان ءاراش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, tell me who you are.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لَ ذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The little damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا راي مِ ننبارا ءاش كركيسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“King, my name is Carcayçiona. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شي فجّ دال راي نجرب شانّر دالش رمنش دا الهند
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I am the daughter of king Naǧreb, Lord of the Romans of India. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">داشا ءال شاربسي دالش إذلش إ شارب أَذ الله شانّر دالش سيالش إ دا لَ تيار إ أَبراسيما مبّدرا افز كنميغ لكا باياش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I left the service of idols, and I served Allah - God of the heavens and the Earth - and my father hated me and did what you can see.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ دش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ذنزالّ بانتا أَ مي كا يُ م كشرا كن تِ إ أَدالنترتا شبّرا تذش لش دا مِ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, come with me so I can marry you, and I will put you before everyone else in my kingdom. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا أَكال شانّر كا تُ ما أَش ننبّرذ ننك لُ أُي ننبر شن أَغر أَ تِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">This God you have named, I have never heard his name before except now, from you. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">داكلرما أَلغ مش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Tell me more.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش داكلرلا لَ ذنزالّ تذ أَلكالّ كا لا أَبي ديجّ لَ بّلم دا ل غرنداز دا الله إ دا لش غرسيش دا أَلجنّ إ دا لش بّانش دا جهنم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel told him everything the dove told her, about the grandeur of Allah and the blessings of paradise and the pains of Hell. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, the king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ذنزالّ كشتا كن ميغ كا يُ تا شاغرا ءان لَ راغل إ يُ دغ كا نُ أَي شانّر شن الله شل شن أَبّرسار ننغن كن أَل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Damsel, marry me, and I will follow your rule, and I say that there is no God except Allah - alone, without peers.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لَ ذنزالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The damsel said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا راي نُ شي بشتنتا بّر تِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“King, I am not enough for you. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا تانغ لش منش كرتداش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">My hands are cut off.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يُ ما كنتانت أَشي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I am content with you like this.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ديلا أُمانجّا دا كارايار كن الله إ لاّبل كن شغ إ كششا كن أَلّ إ لابشا لَ سيارب كن أَلّ أَ شّ كش إ كشتغ أَ شُ بّدرا إ أَتذش لش شيش إ كا لونرشان إ أَل أَكتشان إ وباداسياشان بّرشانّر إ ميرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he gave the damsel a promise of his belief in Allah, and he took her with him and married her and brought the servant to the damsel's house and punished the damsel's father and his companions and made them honor her and support her and obey her as a lord and a superior. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ بّلزيلا أَ شُ مدرا إ أَ تذش لش شيش كن أَلّ إ كركيسين بّاربّر أَلشواغر أَل كاراياناسي فشت كا شا هز مسلم لَ بياجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she pleased his mother and all the followers, and Carcayçiona convinced her mother-in-law to believe [in Allah] until the old woman converted to be a Muslim. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش أَكاسلّي كا ءال راي أُب دار أُن كمن لرغ أَ كستغ أَ لش شيش إ منذلاش كا أَكتشان مجّ أَ شُ مجّار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">It happened that the king had to go on a long trip, and he advised his followers and ordered them to care for his wife.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ أَشي كم ءال راي فوا بّرتذ كركيسين بّري أُن فجّ إ لش أُتراش مجّاراش أُبيرن غرندا ءانبيدي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when the king was gone, Carcayçiona had a son, and the other women were very envious.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لَ أُردنارن أُن كرتا كم كا ءال راي لَ ءاسكربي أَشمدرا كا ذزي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And they wrote a letter as if the king wrote it to his mother that said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شانّر مدرا كونذ لاغر ءاشت مِ كرت شكرايش أَ لهاجّزار دا مي أَلقصر إ راين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Mother, when this letter arrives, you will remove the sorceress from my castle and kingdom. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا ءالّ نش أَ هاجّزذ أَ تذش إ نّش هاجّ داشر نواش لاي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She has bewitched us and made us abandon our laws. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا أَكال فجّ كا أَ بّرذ نُ ءاش ميُ إ شن هزاش لُ كا يُ منذ ننك مش ما بارش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The son she had is not mine, and if you don’t do what I say, you will never see me again.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش كونذ لَ بياج ليُ لَ كرت بّاشلا مجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When the old lady read the letter, it weighed on her very much.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ هز غرندا لّنت بّر أَل مجّ أَمر كا تاني كن أَلّ إ كلمل إ ليلا لَ كرت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She cried a lot because of the great love she had for Carcayçiona, and she beckoned her and read the letter. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش كركيسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Carcayçiona said: 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا مِ شواغر هز لُ كا كارّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My mother-in-law, do what you want. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا الله ءاش ءال كنتذر دامش ذيش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">God is the counter of my days. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ شبّرأَل ما أَبّاركر إ أَ ءال ما داشانبّر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He has cured me, and to him, I am united.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش لؤر أَبارت شبّرأَلّ شش رباش إ شك أَ شُ فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, she grabbed her clothes and took her son. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ شكرنل أَ أُن منتنا ميُ أَلت إ لَ سيارب كن أَلّ إ نُ ساش كركيسين ذا أَندر بّر لش يامش لّرنذ أَرانكرنذشا أَذ الله فشت كا لا ءانبي الله لَ بّلم إ دي السلام شبّراءالّ إ دشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">They took her out to a very tall mountain, her servant with her, and Carcayçiona did not stop walking through the wilderness, crying, running toward Allah until Allah sent the dove, who brought peace upon her and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا كركيسين أَلاغرتا كا الله ءاش كن تِ إ ءال ت أَبياذر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Carcayçiona, be happy that Allah is with you, and he has taken pity upon you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش كركيسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Carcayçiona said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا لَ بّلم ءال اسلام شاء شبّر تِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, may peace be upon you.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش لَ بّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا كركيسين رواغ أَذ الله كا تا ترنا تش منش بّر كا تا أَيدا شبّرا تُ فجّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Carcayçiona, beg Allah to restore your hands so that he will help you with your son.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش كركيسين
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Carcayçiona said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم يُ ءا باروانس دا ذامنذرلا أَذ الله ننغن ماناشتار ءان ءاشتا منذ بّر نُ بّاردار لُ سالاشتريل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, I am ashamed to demand anything from Allah in this world because I don’t want to lose entry to paradise.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ فواشا لَ بّلم إ ذي الله شوان أَ كركيسين إ درميشا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the dove went away, and Allah gave Carcayçiona a dream, and she went to sleep. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ قونذ شا ءاشبّارت هلّشا كن شش منش بّر لسانسي دا الله تن أَلت ءاش إ ديش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when she woke up, she found herself with her hands, with the approbation of Allah - the High one - and said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لور ءاش أَذ الله أَكال كا ما أَ ترند مش منش دابّواش كا ما لش كرت مِ بّدرا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Praise be to Allah who has restored my hands after my father cut them off.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لوذ ءاش الله شانّر كا ما شك دال شاربسي دا لش إذلش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Praised is Allah, who took me away from the service of idols.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لوذ شاش يا مِ شانّر كا راسيباش لُ بك دال أُبر إ ذش ءال ولرذن شن كوانت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">May you be praised, my God, because you receive a little bit of our labor and grant us innumerable rewards.” 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّواش فواشا أَل هلد دا ونمنتا إ هز دالش رمش أُن ءاشتنسي ذندا أَبتشا إ لَ سيارب شيبار إب كن ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she went to the base of a mountain and made an abode of the branches, in which she lived, and her servant was always with her. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ءان ءاشت بن ءال راي دا شُ كمن إ دامنذ بّر شُ مجّار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Meanwhile, the king returned from his journey and demanded to see his wife. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لؤر شكالا شُ مدرا لَ كرت إ دشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, his mother took out the letter and said to him:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا فجّ تُ ما ءاشكارابشتا ءاشت كرت يُ هزا لُ كا بّرأَلّ ما منداشتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Son, you wrote me this letter, and I did what you ordered me to do.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كونذ ءال راي ليُ لَ كرت إ كنسي لَ تريسين كا بّر ءالّ شا أَبيَ أُردانذ كيُ أَمرتاسذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">When the king read the letter and recognized the treason organized against her, he fainted.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ كونذ راكرذ شلّ أَ بشكر شُ مجّار بّر لش منتاش لّرنذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And when he regained consciousness, he went out to the mountains to search for his wife, crying. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ ءال كا دزي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَذ ءاشتش مِ بيانكشت إ بّلزار دا مش أُجّش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Where are you, my beloved and pleasure of my eyes? 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">شابّر الله وردلش أَ لش ذش دا تربجّ أَ ءالّ إ يل كريتر إ دمالش بّر ءانكوانتر
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Allah, keep them both, her and her newborn, safe from strife and help me find them.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ غيل الله أَ دنذا ءال ءاشتب إ ءال كلمنذ كن لَ مش أَلت دا شُ بز إ نُ لا كاري راشبّندر بّركا لا أَبي هاجّ تراسين إ مدرل ءاجّر دا شُ كش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And Allah guided him to where she was, and he clamoured with the highest voice he had, and she did not want to respond to him because he had been treasonous and ordered her to be thrown out of her house. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يانبيلا الله لَ بّلم إ دشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And Allah sent the dove, who said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا كركيسين راشبند أَ تُ مريذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Carcayçiona, respond to your husband. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نُ ل أُياش ءال بلر كا بّر تِ هزا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Do you not hear his crying-out for you?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا بّلم تانغ تامر كا شا أَ بّرتذ دال شاربسي دا الله أَ كا شا أَ ترنذ أَلشاربسي دا لش إدلش إكبّرانتذ أَلأُمناجّ كا ما هز
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Dove, I am afraid that he has left the service of Allah and has returned to the service of idols and has broken the promise he made me.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديشلا لَ بّلم
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The dove said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">راشبّندالا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“Respond to him. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا يُ تا جر بّر الله كا نُ داشذ تُ أَلدين نِ تا مند ءاجّر دا شُ كش
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">I swear to you that he has not abandoned your faith and did not order for you to be thrown out of your house.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">لؤر راشبنديلا كركيسين دزياند
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">At that moment, Carcayçiona responded, saying:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">كا تا بلزا كتما أَكِ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“What will please you? I am here.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ فواشا ءال راي إ لش شيش فشت ذند ءالّ ءاشتب إ أَبّرسل إ باشل إ ذيشلا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king and his companions went to where she was and hugged her and kissed her and said to her:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا مِ أَمد كا أَ شاذ دا تِ ءان ءاشتا تيانبا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My love, what has become of you in this time? 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">بّركا أَ شاذ غربا بّر مِ لُ كا أَش بّشذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Because for me, what has happened here has been terrible.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءالّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا ءال راي كا أَ فاجّ الله كن مِ مجّ بيان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“King, Allah has made everything very well for me: 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَ ما ترند مش منش إ ما أَ ءاشكبّد مِ فجّ إ تُيُ بّر شُ أَلفضل إ غرسيا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">He restored my hands, and I escaped with my son and yours because of Allah’s preference and grace.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ يلاغرشا ءالراي أَلاغري مي غرند إ لؤر أَذ الله مجّ أَغارداسيلا ءال بيان كا لا فز
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the king was very happy and praised Allah and thanked him very much for the wellness that he had brought upon them. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">أَبّاراش ديش الّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">After, she said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا مِ مرذ تُ ءاشكارابشت أَ تُ مذر تل كرت
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My husband, did you write such a letter to your mother?”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">نُ بّر الله شانّر دا لش سيالش إ دا لتيار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“No, by Allah - God of the heavens and Earth.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">الؤر كارايل
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And she believed him. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش ءال راي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">The king said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يا مِ أَمد بمانش أَ نواش رايان
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“My love, let’s return to our kingdom.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ديش الّ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">She said:
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">يُ نُ ترنرا أَلغر د تن مل جانتا
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">“I will not return to a place where there are such bad people.”
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ نُ سش ءال راي دا راغرل إ دازيرلا كا لافري أُن سيبدذ دا نواب بّرا كا دامشترشان ءان أَلّ ءال أَلدين دا الله 
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And the king did not stop begging her and said that he would make a new city to demonstrate his faith in Allah.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ لابل ءال راي إ فرولا أُن سبدذ ءان لَ ماجّر كمرك إ مش أَبنذش دا أَو كا أَبيَ ءان شُ راين ءان ال ري دا أَلفرار
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And he took her with him, and built her a city in the best district, and the most abundant with water that there was in his kingdom on the river al-Firāri. 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>The Euphrates</p>
								</note> 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إ فوا لواغ ببّلذ ءان بّك تيانبّ إ لّمرنل لَ سبدد دا كركيسين إ دامشتررن ءان ءالّ ءال دين دا الله
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">And it was populated in little time, and they called it the City of Carcayçiona 
								<note anchored="true">
									<p>Carcassone</p>
								</note> 
								and in it, they practiced their faith in Allah. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">إبنيارن ءان أَل لُ كا كش الله إ شربيارن أَد الله بارذذار شاربسي
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Whoever lived there, did so only for as long as Allah prescribed, and served Allah faithfully.
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">اك شا اكب لراكنتسين دا لذنزالّ دكركسين كن للؤر اد الله البوان دا ش ايذ
							</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">Here ends the tale of the damsel of Carcayçiona with the praise of Allah and the goodness of His help. 
							</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
					<s>
						<app>
							<lem wit="#Transcription">ولا حول ولا قوة الا بالله العلي العظيم والحمد لله رب العلمين</lem>
							<rdg wit="#Translation">There is no time nor power except in Allah - the highest; and praise be to Allah - Lord of the worlds.</rdg>
						</app>
					</s>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>