<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Legend of the Damsel Carcayçiyona</title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"<!--Title in English-->" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English Translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title in original language, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title in English, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">بِسْمِ اِللهِ اِلرًحْمَانِ اِلرًحِيمِ وَصَلًى اَللهُ عَلَى سَيِدِنَا ُمُحَمَدٍ / اِلْكَرِيمِ وَعَلَى ءَالِهِ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In the name of God, the Most Merciful, the Most Compassionate;
							<note type="critical" anchored="true"><p>These words form the basmala, the formula with which each surah of the Qur’ān begins, except the ninth. Additionally, each tale of the manuscript (J57) begins with this formula, and the manuscript itself is closed by a variation on these words.</p></note>
						and God bless our generous lord Muhammad and his family.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ءَاسْتَ ءَاشْ ءَالْرَاكُنْتَمِيانْتُ // دَا لَذُنْزَالً, كَرْكَيْسِيُنَ فِجَ دَالْرًايْ نَجْرَبْ / كُنْلَ بًلُمَ رًاكُنْتَذُ بٌرْ عَلِي اِبْنُ اَبَالْحَسَنْ / اِبْنُ جَابِرْ فِجُ دَاعَبْدُ اَللهْ اِبٌرْ سَعِيدْ فِجُ / دَا طًهِرْ اِبٌرْ عُمَرْ فِجُ دَا سَعِيذْ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This is the legend of the damsel Carcayçiyona,
							<note type="critical" anchored="true"><p>This name is appears as Carcayona in CSIC, Ms. J3 and Arcayona in BNE, Ms. 5313.</p></note>
						daughter of King Najrab, and the dove, retold by ᶜAli son of Abā-l-Ḥasan, son of Jābir, son of ᶜAbdu Allah, and by Saᶜīđ son of Ṭahir, and by ᶜUmar son of Saᶜīđ.
							<note type="critical" anchored="true"><p>This chain of names forms an “isnād” or a chain of transmisión through which this tale passed orally before being preserved in written form. In Islamic texts, the isnād verifies the authenticity of the text that follows.</p></note>
					</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="3">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دِزَانْ كَا / ءَانْتَرَنْذُ ءَالَمَاسْكِدَ دَالْمَانْشَجَارُ دَا اَللهْ مُحَمَّدْ / صعم هَلًرُنْ اُنْكُرٌ ذَا جَانْتَا اِيَاشْتَبَ / ءَانَالٌشْ عُمَرْ اِبْنُ اَلْحَطَبِّ اِ عَلِي اِبْنُ اَبِي طَالِبْ / اِ كَعْبُ اَلَاخْبَارْ لَؤُرَ دِيشُ عَلِي اِبْنُ اَبِي طَالِبْ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">They say that when entering into the mosque of the messenger of God, Muhammad, may blessings and peace of Allah be upon him, they found a huddle of people, and among them was ᶜUmar son of al-Ḥaṭṭabi, and ᶜAli son of Abi Ṭālib, and Kaᶜbu al- Akhbār.
							<note type="critical" anchored="true"><p>An early convert to Islam in the seventh century, Kaᶜb al-Akhbār is considered the principal authority on ‘isra’iliyyat,’ that is, the narrative traditions that entered Islam from Jewish, Christian, or even Zoroastrian sources.</p></note>
						Then, ᶜAlī son of Abī Ṭālib said:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="4">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">/ يَا كَعْبُ اَلَاخْبَارْ كُوَانْتَنُشْ اَلْغُنَ كُشَ / مَرَبِلٌشَ</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">“Kaᶜbu al-Akhbār, tell us something marvelous."</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription">دِيشُ كَعْبُ اَلَاخْبَارْ بًلَزَامَا يَا رًايْ / دَا لُشْ كَارَايَانْتَاشْ اَشْدَا شَبَارْ كَا ءَانْلُشْ / بٍرِمَارُشْ دَالْمُنْذُ اَبِيَ اُنْرًايْ دَا لُشْ رٌمَنُشْ / كَا بِبِيَ ءَانَلْهِنْدَا كَا اَذُرَبَ اَ لَشْ اِذُلَشْ / اِيَارَ رًايْ دَا مُيْ بُوَانَ كُنْدِسِيُنْ غُبَارْنَبَ / شُرًايْنُ كُنْمُجٌ اَمُرْ اِ جُشْتِسِيَ ءَاشْتَا رًايْ / نُ ءَانْجَانْذُرُ كِرِيَتُرَ فَشْتَ كَا تُبُ سِيَانْتَا / اَنٌشْ اِ بًانْشُ ءَالْرًايْكُمُ نُتَانِيَ فِجُ كَيُلَا // بٌرَالٌ غَرَنْدَا بٍيَانْشُ اِ مَنْذُ اُنْذِيَ كَااشَا / اَلًاغَشَانْ تُذُشْ لُشْ شَبِيُشْ دَا شُرًايْنُ اِيَلًا / غَرُنْشَا تُذُشْ اِ ذِشُلًاشْ ءَالرًايْ كَا مِرَشَانْ / ءَانْشُشَبَارْ اِ سَانْسِيَ شِ اَبِيَ دَا تَانَارْ فِجُشْ / اُبٌرْ كَا لَارَ دَابَاذَذُ اِ مِرَرُنْ لُشْ شَبِيُشْ بٌرْ / شُشَبَارْ ءَانْلَمَادَاسِنَ اِ دِشِيَارُنْلَا شَانٌرْ / اَشْدَا شَبَارْ كَا تُ كُوَارْبٌ ءَاشْ فِرِيُ اِ شَلًا دَا تِ / لَ ءَاشْبًارْمَ مُيْ فِرِيَ اِ نُبٌوَاشْ كُنْسَابِرْ اَشْ / مَانَاشْتَارْ كَا تَا بٌرُبِيَانْدَاشْ دَاشْبًاسِيَشْ / كَا شَااَنْ مُيْ كَلِيَانْتَاشْ فَشْتَ كَا شَلْغَ / دَا تِ لَ ءَاشْبًارْمَ كَلِيَانْتَا</lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation">Kaᶜbu al-Akhbār said: “Indulge me, oh King of the Believers, you should know that in the beginning days of the world, there was a Roman king who lived in India, who worshipped idols, and was a very wealthy king who governed his kingdom with great love and justice. This king did not produce a child until he was one hundred years old, and he thought, “Why do I not have a child?” Thus, a grand idea came upon him and one day he ordered all the sages in his kingdom to come to him. And all of them came and the king told them to look in their knowledge and science to see if it was to have children or why this was forbidden / inhibited to him. And the sages searched through their knowledge of medicine and told him: “Sire, you must know that your body is cold and your semen comes forth from you very cold, and so you do not conceive. You must provide yourself with very hot spices until you ejaculate hot sperm.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="5">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription">اِ فِزُلُ ءَالْرًايْ / اَشِي اَبًارَاشْ دِشِيَارُنْلَا لُشْ ءَاشْتُلُلُغُشْ / شَانٌرْ نُ اَيْ ذُبْدَ شِنُ كَا اَشْ دَا اَبَارْ كِرِ / يَتُرَ بًارُ نُشَبَامُشْ شِشَارَ مَجٌ اُفَانْبَرَ / بٌرْكَا بَامُشْ لَ ءَاشْتَارَالً ذَا بَانُشْ اَشَانْتَذَ شُبْرَا / ءَالْشِغنُ</lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation">And the king did as such. Afterward, the astrologers told him: “Sire, there is no doubt that you will have a child, but we do not know if it will be male or female because we see the star of Venus situated upon the sign.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="6">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription">بٌوَاشْ ءَالْرًايْ كُنْبِنُ كُنشُ مُجَارْ / اَلْكُمِيَانْسُ دَالْذِيَ اِيَانْبًارَانٌشَا لَمُجَارْ //  ابًرِيُ اُنَ كِرِيَتُرَ دَا لَشْ مَشْ فَارْمُشَشْ دَا لَشْ / مُجَارَاشْ اِ لًمَرُنْلَ كَرْكَيْسِيُنَ اِ مُرِيُ / شُمَدْرَا دَا بًرْتُ اِ دِيُلَ شُبًدْرَا اَ اُنَ نُدْرِسَ / اِ كِرِيُلَ شِيَاتَا اَنٌشْ اِ فِزُلَا شُبًدْرَا اُنَ اَلْقَصَرْ / شُبْرَا ذُرَذُ اُبْرَدُ دَا مَسُنَارِيَ اِ فِزُلَا ءَانَالْ / بَارْجَالَاشْ كُنْاَرْبُلَاشْ اِ رٍيُشْ تَرَيُلَا اَلٍي / تُذُشْ لُشْ ءَاشْتُرْمُانْتُس كَا بٌذُ اَبَارْ اِ ذَا / شُلَ اَلٍ كُنْشُشْ ذُنْزَالًشْ فَشْتَ كَا لًاغُ اَ تَانَارْ / اُنْزَا اَنٌشْ ءَانْبٌوَاشْ بِنُ اَبَارْلَ شُبًدْرَا كُنْ / لُشْ غَرَنْدَاشْ دَا شُرًايْنُ اِ تَرَيُلَا بُرَكَذُشْ / اِ شَادَشْ اِ جُيَشْ كُنْتُذُشْ لُشْ دَالَايْتَاشْ كَا بٌذُ / تَرَءَارْ  اِيَانْتُرُ ذُ ءَاشْتَبَ ءَالً اِ مِرُ اَ شُفَارْمُشُرَ / اِيَنَمُرَاشَا ذَالً اِ كُمِيُ اِ بَابِيُ كُنَالً اِ كُوَ / نْذُ اُبِيَارُنْ كُمِذُ دِشُلَا لَدٌنْزَالً</lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation">So the king laid with his wife at the start of the day and she became pregnant and gave birth to a child who was among the most beautiful of women, and they called her Carcayçiyona. And her mother died in childbirth, and her father gave her to a wet nurse who raised her for seven years. And her father made her a palace covered in gold, worked of masonry, and he made within it arboretums and rivers, and he brought for her all the instruments that there could possibly be. And he left her there with her ladies-in-waiting until she turned eleven. Then, her father came to see her with the important people of his kingdom, and he brought her rich brocades and silks and jewels with all the treats that he could carry. And he entered where she was, and he saw her beauty and fell in love with her. And he ate and drank with her, and when they had finished eating, the damsel said to him:</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription">يَا بًدْرَا / ءَاشْتُشْ خَلَاقَذُشْ دَا اُنْبَارَاشْ اِ مُجَارَاشْ نُفُوَارُنْ / خَلَافَذُشْ شِنُ بًرَ كُمَارْ اِ بَابَارْ بٌوَاشْ كُنْ / بِيَانَا كَا اَ كِيَانْ فَزَا تَلَاشْ غَرَسِيَشْ دَا لَشْ // اَغَرَدَاسْكَمُشْ بٌوَاشْ يُ يَا بًدْرَا اَ كِيَانْ / لُاَغَرَدَاسَارَا</lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation">“Father, these creations of men and women were created only to eat and drink; so, it is appropriate that we should give thanks to the one who makes such graces. So father, whom do I thank?”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription">دِيشُ ءَالْبًدْرَا اَ مِي يَا فِجَ كَا يُ / ءَا فَاجٌ غَرَسِيَ شُبْرَا تِي دِيشُ لَفِجَ اِ تُ يَا بًدْرَا / ا َكِيَانْلُ اَغَرَدَاسَاشْ دِيشُ يَا فِجَ ءَاشْتَشْ / غَرَسِيَشْ اَنْلَشْ ءَارَادَذُ نُوَاشُشْ اَنْتَابًشَذُشْ / اُنُشْ دَا اُتْرُشْ دِيشُ لَفِجَ يَا بًدْرَا كِيَانْلُ / كُمَانْسُ اِ كِيَانْلُ اَكَبَرَ كَا تُبًدْرَا اِ تُ / اَوَالُ مُرِيَارُنْ بٌوَاشْ كِيَانْفِزُ ءَاشْتَشْ غَرَسِيَشْ / ا ِكِيَانْلَشْ ءَارَاذَرَ اِ كِيَانْ خَلَاقُ لَشْجَانْتَاشْ / دِيشُ ءَالْرًايْ يَا فِجَ يُتَا دَرَا تُ شَانٌرْ اِ شَانٌرْ / دَا تُشْ بًدْرَاشْ اَكَالْ كَا نُ ءَا كُنُسِدُ اُتْرُشَا / نٌرْ شِنُ ءَالْ</lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation">The father said: “To me, daughter, for I have brought grace upon you.” The daughter said: “And you, father, whom do you thank for it?” He said: “Daughter, these blessings have been inherited by our predecessors, one from another.” The daughter said: “Father, who started this and who will end it, for your father and your grandfather perished? Who made these blessings and who will inherit them, and who created people?” The king said: “Daughter, I will give you your lord and the lord of your parents. I have not known another lord except him.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="7">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>