<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>To the tune “Drunk under the Shadow of Flowers”&#8212;"In Thin Fog"</title>
				<author>Li Qingzhao</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 284.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Qian Jia</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Notes by</resp>
					<name>Nina Du</name>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Runqi Zhang</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
				<p>Li Qingzhao wrote this <hi rend="italic">ci</hi>> during her marriage, which was marked by long separations from her husband due to his work. Like other <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> which she composed, it captures the loneliness of a speaker whose feelings jar against the happy scenes around her. In this case, the mention of the festival of Double Ninth (a harvest festival associated with expressions of gratitude) emphasises her alienation. Festivals such as this were occasions to gather together and socialize, but here we encounter the speaker entirely alone.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>Text based on Tang, Guizhang 唐圭璋 (ed.). Quan Song Ci 全宋詞. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhonghua shu ju, 1965, 284. </p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">醉花陰</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">To the tune “Drunk under the Shadow of Flowers”</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>To the tune “Drunk under the Shadow of Flowers”&#8212;"In Thin Fog"is part of <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi>, a digital compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. This larger project comprises computer-readable transcriptions and/or editions of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century, and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia; accompanied by new English translations; high-resolution digital images of manuscript/early print sources, where available; an apparatus that includes critical introductions, textual notes and annotations; and a flexible user interface with which to navigate these materials.</p>
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<punctuation marks="all">Punctuation follows the edition.</punctuation>

				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">醉花陰</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To the tune “Drunk under the Shadow of Flowers”&#8212;"In Thin Fog"</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1">
				<!--Each stanza needs its own line group <lg>-->
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">薄霧濃雰愁永晝。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">In thin fog and heavy mist, I am dismayed by the eternal daytime.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">瑞腦銷金獸。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The dragon-brain<note anchored="true">The “dragon brain incense” refers to a type of incense made from a subspecies of camphor tree, which was thought to look like a dragon.</note> incense melts in the metal beast<note anchored="true">The "metal beast" refers to the incense holder, many of which were shaped like animals.</note>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">佳節又重陽，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">It is again the festival of Double Ninth<note anchored="true">The Double Ninth Festival is one of the most important traditional festivals in China. It takes place annually in early fall, the traditional harvest time, and thanks is given for nature's bounty.</note>.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">玉枕紗廚，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Jade pillow<note anchored="true"> In this period, wealthy individuals would sometimes sleep on a hard pillow made of carved jade.</note> and gauze canopy;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5"><!--Lines are continuously numbered through the song so check that they are correct-->
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">半夜涼初透。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">at midnight, a chill starts to pierce through.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
			<lg n="2">
				<!--Each stanza needs its own line group <lg>-->
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">東籬把酒黃昏後。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">By the eastern fence, I drink after dusk.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">有暗香盈袖。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">There is a faint fragrance filling up my sleeves.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">莫道不銷魂，</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Do not say that it does not consume the soul:</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">簾卷西風， </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">the western wind rolls up the curtain;</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10"><!--Lines are continuously numbered through the song so check that they are correct-->
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">人比黃花瘦。</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">I<note anchored="true">The character 人, translated here as "I", literally means "the person", but refers to the speaker.</note> am thinner than the yellow flower.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>




