<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Of the names of the Prussian false gods before the time of the conversion, from Prussian Chronicle</title>
				<author>Simon Grunau</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription based on</resp>
					<name>Simon Grunaus Preussische Chronik, volume 1, eds Perlbach, M., Philippi, R., and Wagner, P., Duncker and Humblot, 1876, Leipzig.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Thomas Hewitt</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">Vonn dem namen der Preuschen abgöttir vor der zeit der bekehrungk</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">Of the names of the Prussian false gods before the time of the conversion</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Of the names of the Prussian false gods before the time of the conversion" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<p n="1">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Von anbegin die einwoner des landes zu Preussen wusten noch von gotte noch von gotthin zu sagin, sundir die sonne sie geerht haben.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">From the beginning the inhabitants of the land of Prussia knew neither of god or gods to speak of, rather they honored<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p></p></note>the sun.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Do aber die Cimbri qwomen, die brochten mit ihn 3 bilde ihrer abgotte, den einen Patollo sie nanten, das ander Potrimpo, das dritte Perkuno.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Then however the Cimbri came, they brought with them three images of their false gods, one they called Patollo, the second Potrimpo, the third Perkuno.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Diese zu wirdigen sie haben gezwungen ire nogwer und sie moste sie fur almechtige gotthe halten.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To honor them they conquered their neighbours, and they had to consider them as almighty gods.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="2">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Patollo der obirster abgott der Bruteni also ettwan genant die einwoner Brudenie itzundt Preussen genant.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Patollo [was] the superior<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>In the sense of highest, most senior.</p></note>false god of the Bruteni, as the inhabitants of Brudenie, now called Prussia, were formerly known.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dieser war ein irschrocklicher got des nachtes spuck im hause zu treiben sunderlich in den hofen der edlinge.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This one was a terrifying god of the night, haunting in houses [and] floating particularly in the courtyards of the nobles.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Voraus er unsinnigk thette, wen man des Kirwaidens beful nit hilt, und qwam viel mol, wie ehr ettlich erschreckt des nachts, domit sie den todt dovon hetten.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Above all he would act unreasonably, if the command of the high priest was not followed, and came many times, as he frightened some during the night, so that they died from it.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So imandt war und seinem bilde zu Rickoyott ein erungk gelobet hette, so er is nicht balde hilt, er mit seim schuldiger dy passio spilte, und sein opphir war alles theuer dingk.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If someone was and had vowed an honour to his image in Rickoyott, if he did not keep it soon, he [Patollo] played out the Passion with the offender, and his sacrifice was all expensive things.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So war er auch ein got der todtin.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Thus he was also a god of the dead.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So imandt man starb und man wolt bekarjen<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Bekargen → to live a poor and meagre life. Thus, to give poor and meagre sacrifices.</p></note>die oppherungk der götthin und erungen den waydtlotten, so qwam er ins gehoffte des vorstorbenen und spuchte die nacht, und sie wenig ader nix thettin, er qwam widder, sie musten me thun und gebin, quam er zum dritten mole, so muste man menschin blut opphirn.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If someone died and one wanted to be niggardly with the sacrifice to the gods and tributes for the priests, then [Patollo] came into the farmstead of the deceased and haunted [in] the night, and [if] they did little or nothing, he came again, [and] they had to do and give more, [if] he came for a third time, then human blood must be sacrificed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Darumb mit namen nicht lange geharret, man qwam ken Rickoiot und gab eim waidlotten ein gobe, und dieser im schnet eine wunden in den arm, domit das blut herausliff, noch welchem man horte ein brummen in der eichen, und dis war ein zechen, und es solt vorricht sein, und qwam dornoch nimmer wider und spuchte.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore with names not long delayed, one came to Rickoiot and gave to a priest a gift, and this one cut him a wound on the arm, so that blood flowed out, after which one heard a humming in the oak, and this was a sign, that it should be satisfied, and thereafter [he] came and haunted no more.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="3">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Potrimppo der ander abgott der von Brudenia war, und dieser war ein gott des gluckis in streitten und sust in anderen sachin.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Potrimppo was the second false god from Brudenia, and this one was a god of good fortune in conflicts and in other things.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Wen man diesem Potrimppo sust ein ehr solt thun, der waydlotte muste 3 tage fasten und auff der blosen erden schlaffen, und weiroch zum irsten must man in dem feuer burnen, das mit waxe irnehrt werde, und dieser teuffel auch wolt, man solt ein kindtlein tödten zu ehre, und man is auch thette.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">When one should do an honor to his Potrimppo, the priest had to fast for 3 days and sleep on the bare earth, and above all incense must be burned in the fire, which was fed with wax, and this devil also wanted a small child to be killed to honor [him], and this was also done.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Uber die mosze Patollo Potrimppo hetten ein wolgefallen in menschin blute, so man is im vorgos zur ehre vor der eichen.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Patollo and Potrimppo had a lust for human blood beyond measure,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Mosze → Mose or Mosse → Masse</p></note>thus one shed it for him in honor before the oak tree.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="4">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Perkuno war der dritt abgott, und man in anruffte umbs gewitters willen, domit sie regen hetten und schon wetter zu seiner zeit und in der donner und blix kein schaden thett, und so is qwam, und ein gewitter war im gantze lande und wo dy woren, die diesen gott anbeten, sie knitten sich nieder und schrien: dewus Perkuno abselo mus, wen sie dis vor ein festes hilten, zu der zeit des gewitters ire gotthe mit dem kirwaiden und mit anderen waidlotten redte, und sie gobin is auch ausz vor ein worheit, und sie mit in geret hetten und dem folcke stetis wu was neues einsatzten zu halten. </lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Perkuno was the third false god, and one called upon him for the sake of the weather, so that they would have rain and nice weather in due time and thunder and lightning would do no damage, and thus it came, that a storm was in the whole country and where they were, those who prayed to this god, they knelt down and cried: “dewus Perkuno abselo mus” if they held this before a feast[day], at the time of the storm their gods spoke with the high priest and with other priests, and they passed it off as a truth, that they had spoken with them and [said] constantly to the people about what new commitments to maintain.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="5">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Wurschayto abir Borsskayto war der fierde abgot.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Wurschayto or Borsskayto was the fourth false god.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Die 3 genanten götthe Patollo, Potrimppo, Perkuno man nindert mit oppherungk mochte ehren den zu Rickoyott, do ir bilde stundt in der eichen, diesem Borskaiten abir sie mochtenn im opphernn in allen dorffernn, wo ag ein eiche stunt.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">One might honor the three aforementioned gods Patollo, Potrimppo, Perkuno with sacrifices nowhere but at Rickoyott, where their images stood in the oak tree, this Borskaiten however they could sacrifice to him in all villages, where an oak tree also stood.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Diesen die Bruden in selber zu einem gott irwelten, wen is war ihr kirwait gewesen Bruteno und er sich mit Witouito irem konige und seinen brudern selbir geopphirt umb gnade willen der gantzen gemein.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This one the brothers themselves chose as a god, when he had been their high priest Bruteno and he himself with Witouito their King and his brother sacrificed themselves for the sake of mercy for the whole community.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Das oppher, das man im that, war ein jung fich, und dis so is zu Wurschayto aber Borszkayto qweme und is solt bitten den gott, und er den dienern sein wulte vil fich geben und is gesundt behalten.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">The sacrifice, that one gave to him, was a young animal, and this came to Wurschayto or Borszkayto and it should be offered to the god, and he would give many animals to those who wanted to be servants and keep them healthy.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="6">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Szwaybrotto war der funffte gott, und in auch selber die Brudeni einen gott gemacht haben um der liebe willen, wen so er ihr koning war und Witowuto genant mit seinem bruder Bruteno dem kirwaiten; sie sich lebendigk vorbrandten vor der eichen, wie den obene ist gesagtt worden, mit welchem tode die Bruteni meinten, die zwene bruder hetten gottheit irlangt und sessen bey in.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Szwaybrotto was the fifth god, and the Brudeni had also made him a god themselves for the sake of love, when then he was their king and called Witowuto with his brother Bruteno the high priest; they burned them alive before the oak tree, as is said above, with which death the Bruteni believed the two brothers had attained divinity and remained with them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Diesem man auch uberall oppherte vor einer eichen und war ein gott, der in bescherte vil hunner, gense, entvogil und man im muste opphiren ein jungk sogefarckill.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To this god one sacrificed also anywhere before an oak tree and he was a god, who gave them many chickens, geese and ducks and one had to sacrifice to him a young piglet.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p n="7">
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Curcho war der 6. gott, und diesen sie hetten von den Masuren genomen.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Curcho was the sixth god, and this one they had adopted from the Masovians.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Dieser gott war ein gott der speise von dem, das zu essen und trincken tochte.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">This god was a god of the food and that which qualified for eating and drinking.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Darumb auff der stel itzundt Heiligenbeil genant sein bilt und eiche mit dem feuer war, und do man brandte gedrossen korne, wezen adir meel, honigk, milch und dergleichen.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Therefore in the place now called Heiligenbeil there was his image and [an] oak tree with the fire, and where one burned threshed grain, wheat or flour, honey, milk and the like.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Diesem man auch vorbrandte zur ehren die ersten garben des getreides und solchir manirung vil.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">To honor this god one also burned the first sheaves of corn and many of such manner of things.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">So ist am Hockerlande am habe ein stein genant zum heiligen stein, auff diesem ein iglicher fischer im den irsten fisch zur ehren vorbrandte, dan er im gerne irgreiff.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">At the port in Hockerlande there is a stone known as the holy stone, upon which a common fisherman burned the first fish to [Curcho] in honor, which he gladly took from him.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">Und ein solchs man auch andirswu thun mochte, idoch alhie war seine sonderliche stelle zu dem lobe.</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And such a thing could be done elsewhere, however this was his particular place of worship.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>