<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Babylonian Talmud, Tractate Sotah, 7a-8b</title>
				<author><!--Anonymous if unknown--></author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcription by</resp>
					<name><!--Name of editor if based on published edition--></name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>James Redfield</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true"></note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p><!--Manuscript/print witness that transcription is made from, e.g. location and shelf number of MS--></p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription"><!--Title in original language--></witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation"><!--Title in English--></witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Babylonian Talmud, Tractate Sotah, 7a-8b" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title in original language, which may be a longer form than that used elsewhere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Rabbinic Rites of the Suspected Adulteress</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div1>
			<stage>
				<app>
					<lem wit="#Transcription">מתני׳</lem>
					<rdg wit="#Translation">Mishnah:</rdg>
					</app>
			</stage>
			<p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">מתני׳ היו מעלין אותה לבית דין הגדול שבירושלים ומאיימין עליה כדרך שמאיימין על עדי נפשות <hi rend="underline">ואומר</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>ואומרין, ואומרים (Liss 1977: 66-67, nn. 67-69).</p></note>לה בתי הרבה יין עושה הרבה שחוק עושה הרבה ילדות עושה הרבה שכנים הרעים עושין <hi rend="underline">עשי</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>אל תעשי לשמו, עשי למען שמו (Liss 1977: 67, nn. 81-82).</p></note>לשמו הגדול שנכתב בקדושה שלא ימחה על המים</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Mishnah: They would take her up to the High Court in Jerusalem and admonish her in the same way that they admonish witnesses in capital cases. And <hi rend="underline">he</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Tannaitic sources differ on whether "he" refers to the priest (Sifre Numbers 12) or a member of the court (Rabbi Yosi bar Ḥaninah, folio 7b below, may take either position.) Medieval witnesses (Meiri, Maimonides) have the plural ("they say"), clearly referring to the court, as do generally good Mishnah mss. (Parma, Kaufmann; the latter might be corrected to that reading.)</p></note>says to her, “My daughter, much wine, much levity, much childishness, and many bad neighbors cause [sin]. <hi rend="underline">Cause [rather] this [confession] for</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The reading in the majority of mss., also reflected in a different formulation of Sifre Numbers, is "Do not cause his great name..." Other mss. read "…for the sake of His great name." The printers have conflated the two readings.</p></note>His great Name, written in holiness, that it may not be blotted out by the waters.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ואומר לפניה דברים <hi rend="underline">שאינם כדי</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>שאינה כדאי (Liss 1977: 68, nn. 86 and 92).</p></note> לשומען היא וכל משפחת בית אביה</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And he tells her of things that <hi rend="underline">one</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p> Rashi and most mss.: "she should not hear." Rashi comments that she is not permitted to hear the sins of the patriarchs [Mishnah, tractate Megillah 4:10: the sin of Reuben may be "recited but not translated in public"] but this case is an exception, as it may elicit her confession (like Judah and Reuben, who "confessed and were not ashamed"–see 7b below.) Meiri adds that the patriarchs' sins and confessions will overwhelm even the most intransigent sotah–even if she is surrounded by the supportive presence of "her father's house." Meiri therefore interprets the Mishnah as "things that she cannot [bear to] hear," rather than simply "she should not hear."</p></note>should not hear, [neither she] nor any relation of her father’s house.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">אם אמרה טמאה אני שוברת כתובתה ויוצאת ואם אמרה טהורה אני מעלין אותה <hi rend="underline">לשער המזרח</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>שערי המזרח (Liss 1977: 69, nn. 100-101).</p></note>שעל פתח שער נקנור ששם משקין את הסוטות ומטהרין את היולדות ומטהרין את המצורעין</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If she said, “I am defiled,” she writes a receipt for her marriage-contract and she is released. But if she said, “I am pure,” they take her up to the <hi rend="underline">Eastern Gate</hi>,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Many witnesses and parallels read: "Eastern gates." Rashi reads "Eastern gate" and comments that this is the outer gate from which one entered the Temple Mount–not the Niqanor or "upper" gate, which he places between the women's courtyard and the courtyard of Israelites. Most other commentators read the Eastern and Niqanor gates as identical, as does Rashi himself in his commentary to Numbers (5:18). This contradiction may arise from Rashi's reading of this Mishnah in the Gemara (bottom of 7b below), where the stam adds that "they take her up" from gate to gate "in order to wear her out." In this context, then, Rashi sees the Niqanor Gate as the "upper gate," with the sotah going up and down between the two gates. But as Saul Lieberman notes in his commentary to the parallel at Tosefta Sotah 1:4 (New York: JTS, 1967, vol. 8, 613), both ms. Parma of the Mishnah here and ms. Vienna of the Tosefta lack "Niqanor." That name seems to have crept in later, as a clarification. The original reading was likely closer to Josephus, Antiquities III.6, who refers simply to "the gates which face toward the Temple."</p></note>at the entryway of the Niqanor Gate, where they give the sotah [bitter waters] to drink, and purify a [recently] delivered woman, and purify those with skin-affliction.</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><hi rend="underline">וכהן</hi> אוחז בבגדיה אם נקרעו נקרעו ואם נפרמו נפרמו עד שהוא מגלה את לבה וסותר את שערה</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And <hi rend="underline">a</hi><note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Medieval commentators (Tosafot; Meiri) and a parallel (Numbers Rabbah) read "the priest," i.e. the priest who is chosen by lot to expose her body (Tosefta Sotah 1:7)–not just any priest. This reading is even reflected in the Gemara itself (II.b.iii below.)</p></note>priest seizes her clothes–if they are torn, they are torn; if they are ripped, they are ripped–until he exposes her chest, and he uncovers her hair [and unbraids it].</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
			<div2>
			<lg type="stanza">
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><hi rend="underline">רבו</hi>סרבי<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>סותרו (Liss 1977: 71, n. 126).</p></note> יהודה אומר אם היה לבה נאה לא היה מגלהו ואם היה שערה נאה לא היה סותר היתה מתכסה בלבנים מכסה בשחורים היה<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>היו (Liss 1977: 71, n. 134).</p></note>עליה כלי זהב</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Rabbi Yehudah says: If her chest was attractive, he wouldn’t expose it, and if her hair was attractive, he wouldn’t uncover [it]<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The object pronoun is missing in Vilna, but not in most other witnesses.</p></note>[and unbraid it].</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">וקטליאות נזמים וטבעות מעבירין ממנה כדי לנוולה<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>לביישה (בגליון: לנוולה). כ׳׳י אוקספורד, 2675,2.</p></note>ואחר כך מביא חבל מצרי<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>חבל המצרי (Liss 1977: 72, n. 10).</p></note>וקושרו למעלה מדדיה</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If she was dressed in white, he dresses her in black; if she had on<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Most other witness have, correctly, the plural: "if gold jewelry, etc., were [Vilna: was] on her."</p></note> gold jewelry, chokers, nose-rings, rings: they take them off her in order to sully<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Ms. Oxford 2675,2: shame [in margin: sully]. This variant reveals the social function of the act.</p></note> her. After that, [the priest] takes a reed<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Most witnesses: "the reed rope" [ḥevel ha-mitsri]. Rabbi Yitsḥaq comments, in the earlier parallel in the Palestinian Talmud (Sotah 1:6): "because she acted according to the deeds of the Egyptians [ha-mitsrim]," i.e. fornication (see Ezek. 16:26–also a key intertext of this Mishnah.) Maimonides (Mishneh Torah, Sotah 3:11) preserves that position. However, as Rashi notes, the word actually comes from netser ("reed"), as in Babylonian Talmud, tractate Eruvin 58a: "a rope of reeds [netsarim] for a sotah." See editor's note in Albeck's edition of Mishnah Nashim, 381.</p></note>rope and ties it above her breasts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">וכל הרוצה לראות בא<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>לראות בה בא (Liss 1977: 72, n. 15).</p></note>לראות חוץ מעבדיה ושפחותיה מפני שלבה גס בהן<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>גס בה (Liss 1977: 73 n. 23).</p></note>וכל<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>ושאר כל הנשים (Liss 1977: 73 n. 24).</p></note>הנשים מותרות<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>מוֹתְרוֹת (חייבות – Liss 1977: 73 n. 25).</p></note>לראותה שנאמר ונוסרו כל הנשים ולא תעשינה כזמתכנה</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">And everyone who wants to gaze may come,<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Several witnesses, including Rashi and the Gemara (8b below): "to gaze upon her may come." The phrase "upon her" (bah) likely fell out, due to similarity to the adjacent word "come" (ba’). More importantly, this translation of the implied modal ("may") reflects only Rava's reading of the Mishnah at folio 8b in the Gemara (II.c.iii below): anyone, male or female, may come to gaze, but women who attend must gaze. Abbaye holds that only women may attend and they are permitted–but not obligated–to gaze.</p></note>except male slaves and maidservants, for she is shameless<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>As Rosen-Zvi shows (2012: 89-92)–with the exception of the parallel at Tosefta Sotah 1:6–this phrase [literally, <hi rend="italic">her heart swells</hi>] usually means that a woman is "shameless" before her social inferiors, rather than "emboldened" by her social peers. He applies the more usual sense here. Rashi, by contrast, reads it in the unusual sense of "emboldened," as is clear from his reading ("her heart swells <hi rend="italic">within her</hi>") and his comment ("When a person sees the members of his household, his resolve is strengthened and he does not become afraid or confess.") See Meiri's interpretation of the clause "nor any of her father's house" along the same lines, n. 3 above.</p></note>before them. And all women<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>Meiri: "all <hi rend="italic">other</hi> women," i.e., other than her maidservants.</p></note>are permitted<note type= "critical" anchored="true"><p>The debate over <hi rend="italic">may vs. must</hi> come (see critical note above) led Shlomo Adani (d. 1629) to "correct" the <hi rend="italic">Mishnah</hi> in line with the <hi rend="italic">Gemara</hi> by re-vocalizing and glossing the word as <hi rend="italic">obligated</hi>. Yet, if that were the reading known to Abbaye &#38; Rava, their subsequent debate could never have arisen.</p></note>to see her, as it is said: that all womenmay be taught not to do after your lewdness. [Ezek. 23:48] [I.a.]</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
			</lg>
		</div2>
		</div1>
		<div1>
			<stage>
				<app>
					<lem wit="#Transcription">גמ׳</lem>
					<rdg wit="#Translation">Gemara:</rdg>
					</app>
			</stage>
			<p>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">מנהני מילי א"ר חייא בר גמדא א"ר יוסי בר' חנינא אתיא תורה תורה כתיב הכא ועשה לה הכהן את כל התורה וכתיב התם על פי התורה אשר יורוך מה להלן בשבעים ואחד אף כאן בשבעים ואחד</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Where are these matters [<hi rend="italic">They take her up to the High Court…</hi> to be derived] from [in Scripture]? –R. Hiyya bar Gamda said that R. Yosi bar Haninah said, “It is brought from [an analogy between two instances of] ‘Torah’ and ‘Torah’. Here it is written, ‘the priest shall execute upon her [the <hi rend="italic">sotah</hi>] all this Torah’ [Num. 5:30], and there it is written, ‘According to the sentence of the Torah which they shalt teach thee’ [Deut. 17:11]. Just as the latter is about [the High Court of] seventy-one [judges], here, too, it is about [the High Court of] seventy-one [judges].</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ומאיימין עליה וכו' ורמינהו כדרך שמאיימין עליה שלא תשתה כך מאיימין עליה שתשתה אומרים לה בתי אם ברור לך הדבר שטהורה את עמדי על בורייך ושתי לפי שאין מים המרים דומין אלא לסם יבש שמונח על בשר חי אם יש שם מכה מחלחל ויורד אין שם מכה אינו מועיל כלום</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><hi rend="italic">And admonish her</hi> etc. And we counterpose the two [sources to raise a contradiction, i.e. this <hi rend="italic">mishnah</hi> with the following <hi rend="italic">baraita</hi>]: Just as they admonish her not to drink, so do they admonish her to drink. They tell her, “My daughter, if the matter is quite clear to you that you are pure, then rest assured in your clarity and drink, as the bitter waters may be likened to nothing more than a dry ointment spread upon living skin: if there is a wound there, it pierces and goes in. If there is no wound, it brings about nothing at all.”</rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>

				<s>
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">
							<note type= "critical" anchored="true">
								<p><!--This is an example note. Notes on textual interpretation should usually be contained within the <rdg> and not the <lem>-->
									
								</p>
							</note>
						</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"></rdg>
					</app>
				</s>
			</p>
		</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>