<?xml-stylesheet href="../src/vmachine.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/vmachine.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
[
<!ENTITY % Menota_entities SYSTEM
'../menota/menota-entities.txt'   >
%Menota_entities;]
>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>"Let the days do as they please"</title>
				<author>Muḥammad ibn Idrīs al-Shāfiʿī</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Text based on</resp>
					<name>al-Shāfiʿī, M. 1911. Dīwān al-Imām Muḥammad ibn Idrīs al-Shāfiʿī, ed. Maḥmūd Ibrāhīm Haybah. al-Qāhirah: Maṭbaʿat al-Taqaddum, page 8.</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Translation by</resp>
					<name>Sherif Abdelkarim</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded in TEI P5 XML by</resp>
					<name>Danny Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi></publisher>
				<availability>
					<p><hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook</hi> is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<p>“Let the days do as they please” comes from the collected poems ascribed to Muḥammad ibn Idrīs al-Shāfiʿī, better known as al-Imām al-Shāfiʿī (d. 820). We have no extant manuscripts from his period that include his poetic works, which appeared in various anthologies since the Middle Ages. Only relatively recently, at the turn of the twentieth century, was the poetry ascribed to him published in a single dīwān, or poetry collection. These poems were penned by different hands at different points in history. In the preface to his second edition of the Dīwān, Dr. Mujāhid Bahjat notes that the majority of poems ascribed to al-Shāfiʿī may be ascribed to other poets or are otherwise unconfirmed as his own; he traces only twelve directly to him, whereas a given edition may include over 160 poems and poetic fragments (Bahjat 3-4, 19-20).</p>
				<p>Although primarily recognized as the namesake to one of the four main jurisprudential schools (or madhāhib, sg. madh'hab) in Sunni Islam, al-Imām al-Shāfiʿī equally distinguished himself as a master of language and adab (belles-lettres). Growing up, this descendant of the prophetic line of the Banū Hāshim tribe lived among the Hudhayl—a clan known for the purity of their Arabic—in order to immerse himself in the study of the language. This training cemented his reputation as a poet and poetic critic. Years later, in Baghdad, the famed philologist and grammarian al-Aṣmaʿī (d. 828) would visit al-Shāfiʿī to take Hudhalī poetry from him. As did all eminent scholars who sought him out (there were many), al-Aṣmaʿī marveled at his double command of language and poetry.</p>
				<p>al-Imām al-Shāfiʿī was born in Gaza in 767. With the death of his father, he and his mother moved to Mecca two years later. His pursuit of knowledge (or ṭalab al-ʿilm) brought him at a young age to Medina, where he studied ḥadīth (prophetic narrations) and fiqh (Islamic law) under al-Imām Mālik ibn Anas until the latter’s death in 795. He then accepted a post in Yemen as governor of Najran, although a revolt in 803 prematurely ended his political career when it led to his arrest and summoning to the court of the Abbasid caliph Hārūn al-Rashīd (d. 809) in al-Raqqah, a city in Syria. There, he would meet the jurist Muḥammad al-Shaybānī (d. 805), who helped secure his acquittal. Under al-Imām al-Shaybānī’s tutelage, al-Shāfiʿī relocated to Baghdad. (Among al-Shāfiʿī’s most important students there was al-Imām Aḥmad ibn Ḥanbal (d. 855)). al-Shāfiʿī would make one more major move in 814 to Egypt, where he continued to study and teach a variety of subjects, primarily jurisprudence, until his death in 820 at the age of 54.</p>
				<p>The verses ascribed to al-Shāfiʿī probably reflect a lifetime’s worth of occasional compositions and pronouncements, and certainly reflect their author’s erudition, fine manners, and familiarity with classical meters. Precise and brief, the poetry nevertheless employs a range of sophisticated rhetorical strategies, from ṭibāq (contrariety) to bayān (eloquence), to jinās (paronomasia), to additional instances of badīʿ (ingenuity)—stylistically unique tropes and schemes (Bahjat 29-37, 42-43). Thematically, the poems touch on the matters of wisdom literature, including personal comportment, friendship, the pursuit of knowledge, and the cultivation of virtues.</p>
				<p>Bahjat, Mujāhid M. “Muqaddimat al-Ṭabʿah al-Thāniyah” (“Preface to the Second Edition”). Dīwān al-Shāfiʿī: al-Imām al-Faqīh Abū ʿAbd Allāh Muḥammad ibn Idrīs al-Shāfiʿī, edited by Mujāhid Muṣṭafā Bahjat, Dār al-Qalam, 1999.</p>
				<p>Chaumont, E. “al-S̲h̲āfiʿī”, in: Encyclopaedia of Islam, Second Edition, edited by P. Bearman, Th. Bianquis, C.E. Bosworth, E. van Donzel, W.P. Heinrichs, 2012. Consulted online on 25 August 2020.</p>
				<p>Farrin, R. Abundance from the Desert: Classical Arabic Poetry. Syracuse UP, 2017.</p>
				<p>van Gelder, G. Classical Arabic Literature: A Library of Arabic Literature Anthology. New York UP, 2012.</p>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				 <p>al-Shāfiʿī, M. 1911. Dīwān al-Imām Muḥammad ibn Idrīs al-Shāfiʿī, ed. Maḥmūd Ibrāhīm Haybah. al-Qāhirah: Maṭbaʿat al-Taqaddum, page 8.</p>
				<listWit>
					<witness xml:id="Transcription">دع الأيام تفعل ما تشاء</witness>
					<witness xml:id="Translation">"Let the days do as they please"</witness>
				</listWit>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
            	<p>"Let the days do as they please" is published by <hi rend="italic">The Global Medieval Sourcebook (GMS)</hi>, a free, open access, and open source compendium of medieval texts in their original languages and in English translation. <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> comprises computer-readable transcriptions or editions alongside new translations of texts dating from the ninth to the sixteenth century and originating in Europe, North Africa, the Middle East, and Asia. The <hi rend="italic">GMS</hi> platform includes critical introductions as well as sources for further reading.  
            </p> 
         	</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
	        	<p>Transcriptions and translations are encoded in XML conforming to TEI (P5) guidelines. The original-language text is contained within &lt;lem&gt; tags and translations within &lt;rdg&gt; tags.</p>
        		<interpretation>
        			<p>Texts are translated into modern American English with maximum fidelity to the original text, except where it would impair comprehension or good style. Archaisms are preserved where they do not conflict with the aesthetic of the original text. Scribal errors and creative translation choices are marked and discussed in the critical notes.</p>
        			<p>For clarification, I have added diacritics to letters left unmarked in this edition.</p>
				</interpretation>
				<segmentation>
				</segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<front>
			<head>
				<title type="main">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation"><!--Title as should be displayed above text. Put nothing here if the title in the text matches the title used elsewhwere--></rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
				<title type="sub">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">من ديوان الشافعي</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">from Dīwān al-Shāfiʿī</rdg>
					</app>
				</title>
			</head>
		</front>
		<body>
			<lg n="1">
				<l n="1">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دع الأيام تفعل ما تشاء<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>وطب نفساً بما حكم القضاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let the days do as they please,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>And take heart with what destiny decreed.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="2">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ولا تجزع لحادثة الليالي<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فما لحوادث الدنيا بقاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Don’t sweat the nights’ emergencies;<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>The world’s afflictions lack perpetuity.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="3">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وكن رجلا على الأهوال جلداً<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>وشيمتك المروءة والوفاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Be a man indifferent to fear,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Of noble, loyal nature.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="4">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وإن كثرت عيوبك في البرايا<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>وسرّك أن يكون لها غطاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Should your faults accrue among creation,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>And you’d like to drape them,</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="5">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">تستر بالسخاء فكل عيب<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>يغطيه كما قيل السخاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Drape them with generosity, for every fault<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Generosity enshrouds, as the saying goes.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="6">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ولا تر للأعادي قط ذلاً<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فإن شماتة الأعدا بلاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Never show foes a fault;<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Their schadenfreude’s a sure misfortune.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="7">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ولا ترج السماحة من بخيل<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فما في النار للظمآن ماء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Expect no bounty from the miser;<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Jehennem waters not the parched.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="8">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ورزقك ليس ينقصه التأني<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>وليس يزيد في الرزق العناء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Unhurriedness will not diminish your provisions,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Nor will overexertion increase them.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="9">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ولا حزن يدوم ولا سرور<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>ولا بؤس عليك ولا رخاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Despondency passes, as does joy;<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>Neither poverty nor affluence are on you.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="10">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">إذا ما كنت ذا قلب قنوع<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فأنت ومالك الدنيا سواء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">If you possess a satisfied heart,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>You own the world.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="11">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">ومن نزلت بساحته المنايا<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فلا أرض تقيه ولا سماء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">On whomever Death descends with its appointment,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>No earth can shelter, no sky.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="12">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">وأرض الله واسعة ولكن<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>إذا نزل القضا ضاق الفضاء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Allāh’s earth is wide. However,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>When fate strikes the space contracts.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>
				<l n="13">
					<app>
						<lem wit="#Transcription">دع الأيام تغدر كل حين<space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>فما يغني عن الموت الدواء</lem>
						<rdg wit="#Translation">Let the days betray every age,<lb/><space quantity="10" unit="chars"></space>For death knows no antidote.</rdg>
					</app>
				</l>

			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
